<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;

<!ENTITY % ISOnum  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent">  %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent">  %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> %UVAsupp;

<!ENTITY % xref 'INCLUDE'>
<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED>
]>


<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of Visitors</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors meeting</title>
                <author n="110">
                    <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription and uva-dl-tei markup (TEI P4 with
                        local customizations)</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <biblScope type="date">
                    <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                </biblScope>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">43</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date value="2009">2009</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20060728</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Minutes of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">BOV minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">University of Virginia Board of Visitors
                            minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of
                            Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors
                            meeting</title>
                        <author n="110">
                            <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                            <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                        </author>
                        <biblScope type="date">
                            <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                        </biblScope>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Public minutes</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent n="300">?? pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <idno n="090" type="UVa call number">Accession# RG-1/1/</idno>
                        <idno type="UVa Title Control Number">a2846310</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note n="500">
                            <p n="500|a">The official minutes contain salary information. Access to
                                minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the
                                procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of
                                Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary
                                of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these
                                records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the
                                Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public
                                minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no
                                restrictions. </p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="524">
                            <p n="524|a">Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special
                                Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="520">
                            <p n="520|a">Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body
                                which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded
                                in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions
                                concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities,
                                gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and
                                resolutions. </p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc> &projectDesc; <editorialDecl> &editorial_correction;
                &editorial_normalization; &editorial_hyphenation; &editorial_quotation;
                &editorial_stdVals; </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="AAT">
                    <bibl>Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng" n="008" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <term n="610">University of Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="AAT">
                    <term n="655">Minutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="uva-form">
                    <term>serial volume</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>


    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">
            <div1 type="contents" id="d3">
                <pb/>
                <head type="main"> RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED BY THE BOARD OF VISITORS <lb/>
                    <dateRange from="2006-07-28" to="2006-07-29">JULY 28-29, 2006</dateRange>
                </head>
                <p>
                    <table cols="2" rows="7">
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="label">PAGE</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Approval of the Thomas Jefferson Foundation<lb/> Medal in Civic
                                Leadership </cell>
                            <cell>7150</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Approval of Legislative Proposal – Duties and<lb/> Powers of the
                                Auditor of Public Accounts </cell>
                            <cell>7152</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Approval of Legislative Proposal – Investment of<lb/> Public
                                Funds </cell>
                            <cell>7155</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Health Care Practitioner Workforce Shortage </cell>
                            <cell>7157</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Transfer of Endowment Funds from the University to<lb/> the
                                College Foundation of the University of Virginia </cell>
                            <cell>7158</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Amendment to the Resolution Establishing the Shure<lb/>
                                Professorship in Pediatric Neurology </cell>
                            <cell>7158</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="roll-call" id="d4">
                <pb n="7148"/>
                <head type="main">
                    <dateRange from="2006-07-28" to="2006-07-29">July 28-29, 2006</dateRange>
                </head>
               <p> The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia convened, in
                    Open Session, in Retreat at 10:00 a.m., Friday, <date value="2006-07-28">July
                        28, 2006</date>, at the Williamsburg Inn; <name>Thomas F. Farrell,
                    II</name>, Rector, presided. All Members of the Board - <name>W. Heywood Fralin,
                        Daniel R. Abramson, A. Macdonald Caputo, The Honorable Alan A. Diamonstein,
                        Ms. Susan Y. Dorsey, Ms. Georgia Willis Fauber, G. Slaughter Fitz-Hugh, Jr.,
                        Ms. Glynn D. Key, Vincent J. Mastracco, Jr., The Honorable Lewis F. Payne,
                        Don R. Pippin, Gordon F. Rainey, Jr., Warren M. Thompson, E. Darracott
                        Vaughan, Jr., M.D., John O. Wynne, and Ms. Anne Elizabeth Mullen</name> -
                    were present. </p>
               <p> Present as well were <name>John T. Casteen, III, Leonard W.
                        Sandridge, Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., Paul J. Forch, Ms. Nancy N. Rivers,
                        and Ms. Jeanne Flippo Bailes</name>. </p>
                <p> Present at the first session on July 28<hi rend="super">th</hi>, were <name>Gene D.
                        Block, Ms. Colette Sheehy, J. Milton Adams, George A. Stovall, Ms. Carolyn
                        S. Wood, and Ms. A. Megan Lowe. Robert D. Sweeney</name> was present during
                    the afternoon of July 28th. </p>
               <p> The first portion of the Retreat was devoted to the work of the
                    Special Committee on Planning and consisted both of a report on work
                    accomplished and work yet to be done, as well as a general discussion by the
                    Board of some the issues raised by the Committee. </p>
               <p> The Rector opened the meeting with a summary of his charge to the
                    Committee and the work done by the Committee to date. <name>Mr. Wynne</name>,
                    the Chair of the Committee, spoke on the background of the charge and the
                    Committee's deliberations. Basically, the Committee is trying to devise a ten
                    year plan for the University, but like any good ten year plan, it is not
                    complete and probably never will be. The Committee has not yet decided on
                    priorities, and he observed that if priorities are based entirely on <pb
                        n="7149"/> dollars the plan won't work, because every other institution is
                    trying to raise the dollars necessary for the fulfillment of their plans. </p>
               <p> At the Chair's request, <name>Ms. Sheehy</name> led a discussion
                    on performance measures and distributed a manual on performance measurement. The
                    Chair and the Rector observed that the manual should be a guide and that the
                    Board should not attempt to micromanage this. The Chair noted that <hi rend="italic">U.S. News
                        &amp; World Report</hi>, in its annual ranking of colleges and universities, does
                    not measure efficiency of operation, only dollars spent per student - which
                    works to the detriment of the University, an efficiently run organization. </p>
               <p> After a short recess, <name>Mr. Rainey</name>, who had to leave
                    because of another obligation, thanked Board Members for their commitments to
                    the Campaign. </p>
               <p> The meeting resumed with the following motions to go into
                    Executive Session: </p>
               <p> That the Board of Visitors into Closed Session to discuss and
                    review fund-raising and gift development strategy, donor prospects and related
                    performance goals of identifiable personnel of the University in connection with
                    the University's Capital Campaign; and also to discuss and seek further legal
                    guidance of General Counsel as may be needed with respect to gifts, gift
                    development and coordination of University-related foundations, for the purpose
                    of guiding and coordinating the future private financing and support of the
                    University and sustaining its continued excellence for the long-term, as
                    permitted by Section 2.2-3711 (A) (1), (6), (7) and (8) of the <hi rend="underline">Code of Virginia</hi>. </p>
               <p> That the Board of Visitors into Closed Session to evaluate and
                    discuss the performance and the performance goals and objectives of the
                    University's President and the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating
                    Officer, as provided for in Section 2.2-3711 (A) (1) of the <hi rend="underline">Code of Virginia</hi>. </p>
               <p> The Board went into Executive Session. </p>
                <pb n="7150"/>
               <p> After a recess for dinner, the Board resumed its deliberations, in
                    Executive Session, until 10:15 p.m., when it recessed for the evening. </p>
                <p> The Board resumed at 8:30 a.m., Saturday, July 29<hi rend="super">th</hi>, once more in
                    Executive Session. </p>
               <p> After adopting the following resolution certifying that its
                    deliberations in Executive Session had been conducted in accord with the
                    exemptions permitted by the Virginia Freedom of Information Act, the Board went
                    into Open Session at 10:00 a.m.: </p>
               <p> That we vote on and record our certification that, to the best of
                    each Board member's knowledge, only public business matters lawfully exempted
                    from open meeting requirements and which were identified in the motion(s)
                    authorizing the closed session, were heard, discussed or considered in closed
                    session. </p>
               <p> The meeting continued with reports by the several Committee Chairs
                    on the attainment of their Committee goals - established at the Board Retreat in
                    July, 2005 - over the past year, as well as the goals they have set for the
                    forthcoming year. (These reports will be issued as a Supplement to these
                    Minutes.) </p>
               <p> The President presented a proposal to establish a third Thomas
                    Jefferson Foundation Medal, an award to be presented jointly by the Thomas
                    Jefferson Foundation and the University. The new medal, to be called the Thomas
                    Jefferson Foundation Medal in Civic Leadership, would follow the Thomas
                    Jefferson Foundation Medal in Architecture, established in 1966, and the Thomas
                    Jefferson Foundation Medal in Law, established in 1977, both of which are
                    awarded each year at Founder's Day. The Medal in Civic Leadership would be
                    established for three years, after which there will be a review of its success. </p>
               <p> On motion, the Board adopted the following resolution approving
                    the establishment of the Medal: </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d5">
                <head type="main"> APPROVAL OF THE THOMAS JEFFERSON FOUNDATION MEDAL<lb/> IN CIVIC
                    LEADERSHIP </head>
               
                        <p> WHEREAS, the Thomas Jefferson Foundation and the
                            University of Virginia, with generous gifts from the 
                  
                    <pb n="7151"/>
                            
                            Foundation, established the Thomas Jefferson Foundation Medal in Architecture in
                            1966 and the Thomas Jefferson Foundation Medal in Law in 1977; and
                        </p>
                   
                        <p> WHEREAS, the two Medals commemorate two of Thomas
                            Jefferson's passions, architecture and the law, by recognizing each year
                            at Founder's Day distinguished practitioners in both professions; and </p>
                     
                        <p> WHEREAS, <name>Mr. Jeffrey Walker</name>, an alumnus of
                            the University, with the concurrence of the Thomas Jefferson Foundation,
                            has proposed a third award, the Thomas Jefferson Foundation Medal in
                            Civic Leadership, to recognize extraordinary leadership by a private
                            citizen in any field of endeavor, consistent with the interests of
                            Thomas Jefferson; and </p>
                     
                        <p> WHEREAS, the medalist would be chosen by a committee of
                            five members appointed by the Rector of the University and consisting of
                            the President of the University, or his or her representative, who will
                            serve as chair; the President of the Thomas Jefferson Foundation, or his
                            or her representative, who will serve as secretary; two members of the
                            faculty of the University; and one person chosen by the other four
                            members of the selection committee; and </p>
                       
                        <p> WHEREAS, the conditions and funding of the Thomas
                            Jefferson Foundation Medal in Civic Leadership are to be enumerated in a
                            policy statement prepared by the President; </p>
                       
                        <p> RESOLVED, the Board of Visitors approves the
                            establishment of the Thomas Jefferson Foundation Medal in Civic
                            Leadership and thanks <name>Mr. Walker</name> and the Foundation for
                            this latest instance of their generosity and their furtherance of the
                            mutual goals of the University and the Foundation. The Board establishes
                            three years as the interval before the first sunset review, this review
                            to be conducted by the President consistent with the Board's directions
                            at the time. Further, the Board requests the President to conduct
                            similar reviews of all three medals, one each year. </p>
          
                <pb n="7152"/>
               <p> The Board went on to consider several other business matters, the
                    first two of which were legislative proposals explained by <name>Mr.
                    Sandridge</name>: legislation proposed by the University must be sent to the
                    Governor's Office for approval, and this must be done before the next regularly
                    scheduled meeting of the full Board. The first of these has to do with a
                    proposal to amend provisions of the <hi rend="italic">Code of Virginia</hi> relating to the duties and
                    powers of the Auditor of Public Accounts of the Commonwealth and the second with
                    the investment of public funds. </p>
               <p> On motion, the Board approved the two proposals. </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d6">
                <head type="main"> APPROVAL OF LEGISLATIVE PROPOSAL - DUTIES AND<lb/> POWERS OF THE
                    AUDITOR OF PUBLIC ACCOUNTS </head>
               
                        <p> RESOLVED, the Board of Visitors of the University of
                            Virginia approves and endorses the proposed legislation to clarify that
                            private gifts are excluded from the transaction data to be reported to
                            the Auditor of Public Accounts of the Commonwealth for inclusion in a
                            statewide database. </p>
               <p> The proposed legislation, which follows, would amend § 30-133,
                    subsection H: </p>
                <p> H. 1. The Auditor of Public Accounts shall compile and maintain on its Internet
                    website a searchable database providing certain state expenditure, revenue, and
                    demographic information as described in this subsection. In maintaining the
                    database, the Auditor of Public Accounts shall work with and coordinate his
                    efforts with the Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission in obtaining,
                    summarizing, and compiling the information to avoid duplication of efforts. The
                    database shall be updated each year by October 15, to provide the information
                    required in this subsection for the 10 most recently ended fiscal years of the
                    Commonwealth. </p>
               <p> The online database shall be made available to citizens of the
                    Commonwealth to allow public access to historical revenue collections and
                    appropriations with related demographic information, to the extent that the
                    information is available and provided to the Auditor of <pb n="7153"/> Public
                    Accounts. All state departments, courts officers, boards, commissions,
                    institutions, or other agencies of the Commonwealth shall furnish all
                    information requested by the Auditor of Public Accounts and shall cooperate with
                    him to the fullest extent. </p>
               <p>
                    <hi rend="underline"> For purposes of reporting pursuant to this subsection and
                        implementing the above database, the Auditor of Public Accounts shall
                        include all appropriated funds and other sources under the control of
                        state-supported institutions of higher education, except for the activity of
                        private gifts, including endowment funds and unrestricted gifts referenced
                        in §23-9.2 of the Code of Virginia notwithstanding anything as may be to the
                        contrary herein. The exclusion of this activity does not affect the public
                        access to these records unless otherwise specifically exempted by law. </hi>
                </p>
                <p> 2. The database shall contain the following for each of the 10 most recently
                    ended fiscal years of the Commonwealth: </p>
                    <list>
                        <item> a. Major categories of spending by each secretariat and for major
                            agencies; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> b. The number of full-time state employees; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> c. Total fiscal year revenues from state taxes, fees, and other
                            charges, and total fiscal year revenues from state taxes, fees, and
                            other charges computed on a per capita basis and as a percentage of
                            personal income in the Commonwealth; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> d. With regard to state taxes, fees, and other charges computed on a
                            per capita basis and as a percentage of personal income, a comparison of
                            such statistics for Virginia with the same statistics for other states; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> e. Total fiscal year revenues from federal sources, including the
                            major categories of spending for such revenues; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> f. Total population and total population by various age groups
                            including, but not limited to, school-age population and the population
                            of persons 65 years of age and older; </item>
                   
                    <pb n="7154"/>
                  
                        <item> g. Student enrollment in grades K through 12; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> h. Enrollment in public institutions of higher education of the
                            Commonwealth; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> i. Enrollment in private institutions of higher education in the
                            Commonwealth; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> j. The annual prison population; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> k. Virginia adjusted gross income and Virginia taxable income by
                            various age groups; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> l. The number of citizens in the Commonwealth receiving food stamps; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> m. The number of driver's licenses issued; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> n. The number of registered motor vehicles; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> o. The number of full-time private sector employees; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> p. The number of households; </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> q. The number of prepaid tuition contracts outstanding pursuant to
                            Chapter 4.9 (§23-38.75 et seq.) of Title 23 and the estimated total
                            liability under such contracts; and </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item> r. Other data as the Auditor deems appropriate relating to the
                            Commonwealth of Virginia. </item>
                    </list>
          
                <p> 3. By October 15th of each year, the Auditor shall also produce a paper copy or
                    a computer file containing the information described in this subsection and
                    shall distribute the copy or file to newspapers of general circulation in the
                    Commonwealth. The distribution shall include the address of the Internet website
                    for the searchable database. </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d7">
                <pb n="7155"/>
                <head type="main"> APPROVAL OF LEGISLATIVE PROPOSAL - INVESTMENT OF<lb/> PUBLIC
                    FUNDS </head>
                
                        <p> RESOLVED, the Board of Visitors of the University of
                            Virginia approves and endorses the proposed legislation to add other
                            University funds to those funds that may be invested by the Board of
                            Visitors in financial securities other than fixed-income securities.
                        </p>
                <p> The proposed legislation, which follows, would make exempt from §2.2-4500 -
                    2.2-4517 the following: </p>
                <p> §<xref url="http://leg1.state.va.us/cgi-bin/legp504.exe?000+cod+23-76.1"
                    >23-76.1</xref>. Investment of endowment funds, endowment income, and gifts;
                    standard of care; liability; exemption from the Virginia Public Procurement Act. </p>
                <p> A. The board of visitors shall invest and manage the endowment funds, endowment
                    income, gifts, <hi rend="italic">all non-general fund reserves held by the University, all local
                    funds, tuition, education and general fees, or research and sponsored program
                    funds</hi> of the University in accordance with this section and the provisions of
                    the Uniform Management of Institutional Funds Act (§<xref
                        url="http://leg1.state.va.us/cgi-bin/legp504.exe?000+cod+55-268.1"
                    >55-268.1</xref> et seq.). </p>
                <p> B. No member of the board of visitors shall be personally liable for losses
                    suffered by an endowment funds, endowment income, gifts, <hi rend="italic">all non-general fund
                    reserves held by the University, all local funds, tuition, education and general
                    fees, or research and sponsored program funds</hi> arising from investments made
                    pursuant to the provisions of subsection A. </p>
                <p> C. The investment and management of endowment funds, endowment income, gifts,
                    all non-general fund reserves held by the University, <hi rend="italic">all local funds, tuition,
                    education and general fees, or research and sponsored program funds</hi> of the
                    University shall not be subject to the provisions of the Virginia Public
                    Procurement Act (§<xref
                        url="http://leg1.state.va.us/cgi-bin/legp504.exe?000+cod+2.2-4300"
                    >2.2-4300</xref> et seq.). </p>
                <pb n="7156"/>
                <p> D. In addition to the investment practices authorized by the Uniform Management
                    of Institutional Funds Act (§<xref
                        url="http://leg1.state.va.us/cgi-bin/legp504.exe?000+cod+55-268.1">55-
                    268.1</xref> et seq.), the board of visitors may also invest or reinvest the
                    endowment funds, endowment income, gifts, <hi rend="italic">all non-general fund reserves held by
                    the University, all local funds, tuition, education and general fees, or
                    research and sponsored program funds</hi> in derivatives, options, and financial
                    securities. </p>
                <p> 1. In this section, "derivative" means a contract or financial instrument or a
                    combination of contracts and financial instruments, including, without
                    limitation, any contract commonly known as a "swap," which gives the University
                    the right or obligation to deliver or receive delivery of, or make or receive
                    payments based on, changes in the price, value, yield or other characteristic of
                    a tangible or intangible asset or group of assets, or changes in a rate, an
                    index of prices or rates, or other market indicator for an asset or a group of
                    assets. </p>
                <p> 2. In this section, an "option" means an agreement or contract whereby the
                    University may grant or receive the right to purchase or sell, or pay or receive
                    the value of, any personal property asset including, without limitation, any
                    agreement or contract which relates to any security, contract or agreement. </p>
                <p> 3. In this section, "financial security" means any note, stock, treasury stock,
                    bond, debenture, evidence of indebtedness, certificate of interest,
                    collateral-trust certificate, pre-organization certificate or subscription,
                    transferable share, investment contract, voting-trust certificate, certificate
                    of deposit for a security, fractional undivided interest in oil, gas, or other
                    mineral rights, any put, call, straddle, option, or privilege on any security,
                    certificate of deposit, or group or index of securities (including any interest
                    therein or based on the value thereof), or any put, call, straddle, option, or
                    privilege entered into on a national securities exchange relating to foreign
                    currency, or, in general, any interest or instrument commonly known as a
                    "security," or any certificate of interest or participation in, temporary or
                    interim certificate for, receipt for, guarantee of, or warrant or right to
                    subscribe to or purchase, any of the foregoing. </p>
                <pb n="7157"/>
               <p> The third proposal was a resolution, to be sent to Richmond,
                    supporting a legislative study of the serious shortage of health care
                    practitioners. </p>
               <p> The Board, on motion, approved the following resolution: </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d8">
                <head type="main">HEALTH CARE PRACTITIONER WORKFORCE SHORTAGE</head>
               
                        <p> WHEREAS, the demand for health care in the Commonwealth
                            continues to grow, and is anticipated to increase exponentially in the
                            next few years; and </p>
                       
                        <p> WHEREAS, one of the major causes of the demand is that
                            the "baby boomer" population is reaching age 65. Those between the ages
                            of 65 and 80 need three or more times the rate of health care as younger
                            people; and </p>
                       
                        <p> WHEREAS, although the 60-80 year old population is
                            anticipated to quadruple by 2030, the number of doctors, nurses and
                            other health care practitioners is not increasing at the rate of the
                            aging population, which will cause a workforce shortage; and </p>
                       
                        <p> WHEREAS, the impact of a health care workforce shortage
                            will likely result in limitations to health care for citizens of the
                            Commonwealth; </p>
                       
                        <p> RESOLVED, the Board of Visitors recognizes a growing
                            workforce shortage of health care practitioners and supports a study, by
                            the General Assembly and academic health centers, of methods to ensure
                            an adequate supply of health care practitioners to serve the
                            Commonwealth's population into the future. </p>
                <ornament type="characters">- - - - - - - -</ornament>
               <p>
                    <name>Mr. Sandridge</name> then proposed a resolution to transfer certain
                    endowment funds from the University to the College Foundation of the University
                    of Virginia. </p>
               <p> On motion, the Board approved the following resolution: </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d9">
                <pb n="7158"/>
                <head type="main"> TRANSFER OF ENDOWMENT FUNDS FROM THE UNIVERSITY TO<lb/> THE
                    COLLEGE FOUNDATION OF THE UNIVERSITY OF<lb/> VIRGINIA </head>
              
                        <p> WHEREAS, the Hamrick family contributed funds, using a
                            gift annuity, to the University to benefit the History Department in the
                            College Arts and Sciences; and </p>
                       
                        <p> WHEREAS, the Hamrick family later established an
                            endowed fellowship fund with the College Foundation of the University of
                            Virginia that provides for a graduate fellowship in the Corcoran
                            Department of History in the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences; and </p>
                     
                        <p> WHEREAS, the Hamrick family has requested that the
                            funds held by the University be transferred to the College Foundation of
                            the University of Virginia so that they may be added to the Hamrick
                            Graduate Fellowship Fund; </p>
                     
                        <p> RESOLVED, the Board of Visitors authorizes transfer of
                            the <name>George L. Hamrick</name> Gift Annuity funds, currently held by
                            the University, to the College Foundation of the University of Virginia,
                            to be added to the Hamrick Graduate Fellowship Fund. </p>
                <ornament type="characters">- - - - - - - - -</ornament>
               <p> Finally, the Secretary proposed a resolution correcting the
                    designation of a professorship, established by the Board by resolution on June
                    9th, of this year. </p>
               <p> On motion, the Board approved the following resolution: </p>
            </div1>
                <div1 type="resolution" id="d10">
                <head type="main"> AMENDMENT TO THE RESOLUTION ESTABLISHING THE<lb/> SHURE
                    PROFESSORSHIP IN PEDIATRIC NEUROLOGY </head>
              
                        <p> RESOLVED, that the resolution establishing the Shure
                            Professorship in Pediatric Neurology, adopted by the Board of Visitors
                            on <date value="2006-06-09">June 9, 2006</date>, be amended to read that
                            the Professorship is to be held in the Department of Neurology in the
                            School of Medicine. </p>
                <ornament type="characters">- - - - - - - - - - - - -</ornament>
                <pb n="7159"/>
               <p> The Rector asked <name>Ms. Mullen</name>, the Student Member, if
                    she had any general comments to make on the matters considered by the Board at
                    the Retreat. <name>Ms. Mullen</name> replied that from the point of view of the
                    students at the University, it is very important to try to reduce the size of
                    undergraduate classes. </p>
                <ornament type="characters">- - - - - - - - -</ornament>
               <p>On motion, the Retreat was adjourned at 10:54 a.m.</p>
                <signed>Respectfully submitted, <lb/>
                    <name>Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr.</name><lb/>Secretary </signed>
                <trailer> AGG:jb<lb/> These minutes have been posted to the University of Virginia’s
                    Board of Visitors website. <xref
                        url="http://www.virginia.edu/bov/publicminutes.html"
                        >http://www.virginia.edu/bov/publicminutes.html</xref>
                </trailer>
            </div1>
                <div1 type="addenda" id="d11">
                <pb n="7160"/>
                <head type="main"> ADDENDUM TO THE OFFICIAL MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF THE BOARD OF
                    VISITORS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA <lb/> Meeting Date: <dateRange
                        from="2006-07-28" to="2006-07-29">July 28-29, 2006</dateRange>
                </head>
                <lb/>
                <head type="sub">CERTIFICATION OF EXECUTIVE MEETING</head>
                <p> The Board of Visitors, sitting in Open Session, unanimously adopted a resolution
                    certifying that while meeting in Executive Session - as permitted by the
                    relevant provisions of the <hi rend="underline">Code of Virginia</hi> - only public business authorized by
                    its motion and lawfully exempted from consideration in closed session. </p>
                <signed>Respectfully submitted, <lb/>
                    <name>Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr.</name><lb/>Secretary </signed>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
