<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?dlps id="bov_20070727"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="ocr"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent">  %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent">  %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> %UVAsupp;
<!ENTITY % xref 'INCLUDE'>
<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED>
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
]>


<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of
                    Visitors</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors
                    meeting</title>
                <author n="110">
                    <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription and uva-dl-tei markup (TEI P4 with
                        local customizations)</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services, University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville
                        Virginia</name>
                </respStmt>
                <biblScope type="date">
                    <date value="2007-07-27">July 27, 2007</date>
                </biblScope>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">33</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20070727</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Minutes of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">BOV minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">University of Virginia Board of Visitors
                            minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of
                            Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors
                            meeting</title>
                        <author n="110">
                            <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                            <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                        </author>
                        <biblScope type="date">
                            <date value="2007-07-27">July 27, 2007</date>
                        </biblScope>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Public minutes</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent n="300">?? pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <idno n="090" type="UVa call number">Accession# RG-1/1/</idno>
                        <idno type="UVa Title Control Number">a2846310</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note n="500">
                            <p n="500|a">The official minutes contain salary information. Access to
                                minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the
                                procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of
                                Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary
                                of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these
                                records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the
                                Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public
                                minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no
                                restrictions.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="524">
                            <p n="524|a">Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special
                                Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="520">
                            <p n="520|a">Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body
                                which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded
                                in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions
                                concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities,
                                gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and
                                resolutions.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc> &projectDesc; <editorialDecl> &editorial_correction;
                &editorial_normalization; &editorial_hyphenation; &editorial_quotation;
                &editorial_stdVals; </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="AAT">
                    <bibl>Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language n="008" id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <list>
                        <item>University of Virginia::Board of Visitors</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <term n="610">University of Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="AAT">
                    <term n="655">Minutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="uva-form">
                    <term>serial volume</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2010-06-29">June 29, 2010</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name id="lsc6v">Lorrie Chisholm, (Digital Curation Services, University of
                        Virginia Library)</name>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>The physical page 7398 contains an error in the enrollment goals. Corrected
                    the error in the electronic text.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">
            <div1 id="d3" type="statement">
                <pb n="7392"/>
                <head>SUBJECT TO THE APPROVAL OF THE BOARD OF VISITORS <lb/>
                    <dateRange from="2007-07-27" to="2007-07-28">July 27-28, 2007
                    </dateRange></head>
                <p>The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met, in retreat, on Friday
                    and Saturday, <dateRange from="2007-07-27" to="2007-07-28">July 27, and 28,
                        2007</dateRange>, at The Hotel Roanoke in Roanoke. <name>W. Heywood
                        Fralin</name>, Rector, presided over all sessions. </p>
                <p><name type="present">John O. Wynne, Daniel R. Abramson, A. Macdonald Caputo, the
                        Honorable Alan A. Diamonstein, Ms. Susan Y. Dorsey, Thomas F. Farrell, II,
                        G. Slaughter Fitz-Hugh, Jr., Ms. Glynn D. Key, Austin Ligon, Vincent J.
                        Mastracco, Jr., the Honorable Lewis F. Payne, Warren M. Thompson, E.
                        Darracott Vaughan, Jr., M.D., and Carey J. Mignerey </name> were present. </p>
                <p><name>Gordon F. Rainey, Jr.</name>, participated by telephone. </p>
                <p>Present as well were <name type="present">John T. Casteen, III, Leonard W.
                        Sandridge, Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., Paul J. Forch, Arthur Garson, Jr.,
                        M.D., Ms. Carol Wood, and Ms. Jeanne Flippo Bailes</name>. </p>
                <p><name type="present">Ms. Patricia M. Lampkin, Ms. Colette Sheehy, Robert D.
                        Sweeney, Craig K. Littlepage, Milton Adams, George Stovall, Benjamin Y.
                        Cooper, IV, Ms. Julie Caruccio, Justin Watkins, and Keith D. Vanderbeek,
                        were present for portions of the Retreat</name>. </p>
                <p><name>Charles W. Steger</name>, the President of Virginia Tech, was present
                    briefly on the morning of July 28<hi rend="super">th</hi>, as a special guest. </p>
                <p>The Retreat began at 12:10 p.m., on <date value="2007-07-27">Thursday, July 27<hi
                    rend="super">th</hi></date>. </p>
                <p>The Rector opened the first session with general remarks on what he sees as the
                    Board goals over the next two years, goals that will be his during his term as
                    Rector. Implementation of the plans to be proposed by <name>Messrs. Wynne</name>
                    and <name>Caputo</name> special committees will be important, and there will be
                    a continuing emphasis on diversity. The Board must continue to focus on the
                    Capital Campaign and make sure that it will exceed expectations, with the
                    opportunity to raise perhaps &#x0024;4billion, &#x0024;1billion over the present
                    Campaign goal. </p>

                <pb n="7393"/>

                <p>Particular emphasis, he said, must be placed on the College, the "backbone of
                    this University and we must focus on providing the necessary resources for it to
                    be the best it can be, preparing our students for a global economy."</p>
                <p>He went on to say that as specified in the University's long range plan, there
                    must be a strengthening of the focus on research, a focus which includes support
                    for graduate students, faculty, and the need for new facilities. </p>
                <p>The University must expand on its successes at The University of Virginia at Wise
                    to provide educational opportunities for more students; these efforts are vital
                    to the economic well being and development of Southwest Virginia. </p>
                <p>The Rector said that support for the principles of diversity, and improvement of
                    diversity at the University, "must be at the top of our list of goals." He noted
                    that the long range plan for the University, soon to be finished, must be
                    implemented and not allowed to languish. </p>
                <p>Work must be done, too, on identifying a successor to <name>Mr. Sandridge</name>. </p>
                <p>Finally, the Rector emphasized the proper role of the Board: the President and
                        <name>Mr. Sandridge</name> are charged with running the University on a day
                    to day basis, with the Board providing advice and oversight. </p>
                <p><name>Mr. Diamonstein</name> remarked, however, that the Board should not be a
                    "rubberstamping" body. The Rector agreed, but said there should be a balance
                    between the role of the Board on one hand and that of the administration on the
                    other. </p>
                <p><name>Mr. Wynne</name> stressed the importance of developing, soon, criteria for
                    priorities. </p>
                <p>The Board then heard a presentation on planning, as is being developed by the
                    Special Committee on Planning. <name>Ms. Sheehy</name>, <name>Messrs. Adams and
                        Stovall</name>, <name>Dr. Garson</name>, and <name>Mr. Wynne</name>, the
                    Committee Chair, all participated. </p>
                <p>Following this portion of the Retreat, the President and <name>Mr.
                        Sandridge</name>, the Chief Operating Officer, commented briefly on their
                    annual reports. </p>
                <pb n="7394"/>
                <p>Among other topics, the President noted his concerns about the low rate of
                    participation in mathematics courses by incoming students. He pointed out the
                    correlation between this and low enrollments in science courses. </p>
                <p><name>Mr. Rainey</name>, National Chair of the Capital Campaign, and <name>Mr.
                        Sweeney </name> discussed the possibility of raising the Campaign goal, as
                    suggested in the Rector's opening remarks. The Rector proposed that the Campaign
                    Executive Committee consider the matter and make a recommendation to the Board. </p>
                <p>On motion, the Board went into Executive Session at 2:30 p.m.</p>
                <p>That in connection with the University Capital Campaign and beyond, the Special
                    Committee on Foundations go into Closed Session to discuss and to further
                    consult with the General Counsel, seeking his continued legal advice and
                    guidance in the matters of gift development and coordination of fund-raising
                    activity, costs and expenditures with University-Related Foundations, as
                    provided for in Section 2.2-3711 &lpar;A&rpar; &lpar; 4&rpar;, &lpar;6&rpar;,
                    &lpar;7&rpar; and &lpar;8&rpar; of the <hi rend="underline">Code of
                        Virginia.</hi>
                </p>
                <ornament type="characters">- - - - - - - - - - - - - </ornament>
                <p>The Board resumed in Open Session at 3:40 p.m., and adopted the following
                    resolution certifying that its discussions in Executive Session had been
                    conducted in accordance with the exemptions permitted by the Virginia Freedom of
                    Information Act: </p>
                <p>That we vote on and record our certification that, to the best of each Board
                    member's knowledge, only public business matters lawfully exempted from open
                    meeting requirements and which were identified in the motion&lpar;s&rpar;
                    authorizing the closed session, were heard, discussed or considered in closed
                    session. </p>
                <p>The Board then held a short business session, during which the following
                    resolutions were adopted: </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d4">
                <head>APPROVAL OF LEGISLATIVE PROPOSAL </head>
                <p>RESOLVED, the Board of Visitors approves and endorses the proposed legislation to
                    exempt sensitive donor information from public disclosure pursuant to the
                    provisions of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act. </p>
                <pb n="7395"/>
                <p>The proposed legislation, which follows, would amend &#x00A7; 2.2-3705.4 of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Code of Virginia</hi>: </p>
                <p>&#x00A7;2.2-3705.4. Exclusions to application of chapter; educational records and
                    certain records of educational institutions. </p>
                <p>The following records are excluded from the provisions of this chapter but may be
                    disclosed by the custodian in his discretion, except where such disclosure is
                    prohibited by law: </p>
                <list>
                    <item n="1">
                        <p>1. Scholastic records containing information concerning identifiable
                            individuals, except that such access shall not be denied to the person
                            who is the subject thereof, or the parent or legal guardian of the
                            student. However, no student shall have access to &lpar;i&rpar;
                            financial records of a parent or guardian or &lpar;ii&rpar; records of
                            instructional, supervisory, and administrative personnel and educational
                            personnel ancillary thereto, that are in the sole possession of the
                            maker thereof and that are not accessible or revealed to any other
                            person except a substitute. </p>
                        <p>The parent or legal guardian of a student may prohibit, by written
                            request, the release of any individual information regarding that
                            student until the student reaches the age of 18 years. For scholastic
                            records of students under the age of 18 years, the right of access may
                            be asserted only by his legal guardian or parent, including a
                            noncustodial parent, unless such parent's parental rights have been
                            terminated or a court of competent jurisdiction has restricted or denied
                            such access. For scholastic records of students who are emancipated or
                            attending a state-supported institution of higher education, the right
                            of access may be asserted by the student. </p>
                        <p>Any person who is the subject of any scholastic record and who is 18
                            years of age or older may waive, in writing, the protections afforded by
                            this subdivision. If the protections are so waived, the public body
                            shall open such records for inspection and copying. </p>
                    </item>
                    <item rend="indent2" n="2"> 2. Confidential letters and statements of
                        recommendation placed in the records of educational agencies or institutions
                        respecting &lpar;i&rpar; admission to any educational agency or institution,
                        &lpar;ii&rpar; an application for employment, or &lpar;iii&rpar; receipt of
                        an honor or honorary recognition. </item>
                    <pb n="7396"/>
                    <item rend="indent2" n="3"> 3. Records of the Brown v. Board of Education
                        Scholarship Awards Committee relating to personally identifiable
                        information, including scholarship applications, personal financial
                        information, and confidential correspondence and letters of recommendation. </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item rend="indent2" n="4"> 4. Data, records or information of a proprietary
                        nature produced or collected by or for faculty or staff of public
                        institutions of higher education, other than the institutions' financial or
                        administrative records, in the conduct of or as a result of study or
                        research on medical, scientific, technical or scholarly issues, whether
                        sponsored by the institution alone or in conjunction with a governmental
                        body or a private concern, where such data, records or information has not
                        been publicly released, published, copyrighted or patented. </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item rend="indent2" n="5"> 5. All records of the University of Virginia or the
                        University of Virginia Medical Center or Eastern Virginia Medical School, as
                        the case may be, that contain proprietary, business-related information
                        pertaining to the operations of the University of Virginia Medical Center or
                        Eastern Virginia Medical School, as the case may be, including business
                        development or marketing strategies and activities with existing or future
                        joint venturers, partners, or other parties with whom the University of
                        Virginia Medical Center or Eastern Virginia Medical School, as the case may
                        be, has formed, or forms, any arrangement for the delivery of health care,
                        if disclosure of such information would be harmful to the competitive
                        position of the Medical Center or Eastern Virginia Medical School, as the
                        case may be. </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item rend="indent2" n="6"> 6. Personal information, as defined in &#x00A7;
                        2.2-3801, provided to the Board of the Virginia College Savings Plan or its
                        employees by or on behalf of individuals who have requested information
                        about, applied for, or entered into prepaid tuition contracts or savings
                        trust account agreements pursuant to Chapter 4.9 &lpar;&#x00A7; 23-38.75 et
                        seq.&rpar; of Title 23. Nothing in this subdivision shall be construed to
                        prohibit disclosure or publication of information in a statistical or other
                        form that does not identify individuals or provide personal information.
                        Individuals shall be provided access to their own personal information. </item>
                    <lb/>
                    <item rend="indent2" n="7">
                        <hi rend="italic">7. Records that contain personal information concerning
                            donors and prospective donors in connection with fundraising by or for a
                            public institution of higher education; except that the amount, date and
                            purpose of any pledge or donation, and the identity of the donor, unless
                            the donor has requested anonymity in connection with or as a condition
                            of making the pledge or donation shall be released. </hi>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d5">
                <pb n="7397"/>
                <head>APPOINTMENT OF BOARD OF VISITORS REPRESENTATIVE TO THE INSTITUTE FOR SHIPBOARD
                    EDUCATION BOARD OF DIRECTORS </head>
                    <p>WHEREAS, the University of Virginia became the academic
                        sponsor of the Institute for Shipboard's Education Semester at Sea program
                        by agreement dated <date value="2005-12-12">December 12, 2005</date>; and </p>
                    <p>WHEREAS, this agreement states that the Institute for
                        Shipboard Education will add two voting members to its Board of Directors,
                        one appointed by and representing the Board of Visitors, the other a member
                        of the senior administration of the University of Virginia appointed by and
                        representing the President; and </p>
                    <p>WHEREAS, <name>Gene D. Block</name> resigned his appointment
                        as the Board of Visitors appointee effective <date value="2007-06-30">June
                            30, 2007</date>; and </p>
                    <p>WHEREAS, the Executive Vice President and Provost of the
                        University plays an important role in the relationship with the Institute
                        for Shipboard Education because of the academic sponsorship. </p>
                    <p>RESOLVED, the Board appoints <name>Arthur Garson, Jr.,
                            M.D.</name>, to serve as the Board of Visitors representative to the
                        Board of Directors of the Institute for Shipboard Education for a term of
                        three years. </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d6">
                <head>APPROVAL OF APPOINTMENT TO THE BOARD OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA COLLEGE AT
                    WISE </head>
                    <p>RESOLVED that <name>Mr. Roger C. Viers</name> be appointed
                        to The University of Virginia's College at Wise Board for a four-year term
                        ending <date value="2011-06-30">June 30, 2011</date> in accordance with the
                        terms of the Board bylaws. </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d7">
                <pb n="7398"/>
                <head>APPROVAL OF SCHEV ENROLLMENT PROJECTIONS </head>
                <p>RESOLVED, the Board of Visitors approves the enrollment
                    projections for The University of Virginia College at Wise for the fall of 2007
                    through the fall of 2013, as recommended by The University of Virginia's College
                    at Wise Board. </p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label" cols="7"><hi rend="center">ENROLLMENT GOALS</hi></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Fall<lb/>2007</cell>
                        <cell> Fall<lb/>2008</cell>
                        <cell> Fall<lb/>2009</cell>
                        <cell> Fall<lb/>2010</cell>
                        <cell> Fall<lb/>2011</cell>
                        <cell> Fall<lb/>2012</cell>
                        <cell> Fall<lb/><corr resp="lsc6v" sic="2113">2013</corr></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1936</cell>
                        <cell>1957</cell>
                        <cell>1983</cell>
                        <cell>2003</cell>
                        <cell>2030</cell>
                        <cell>2052</cell>
                        <cell>2077</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Enrollment Data provided by the Office of Admissions, Registrar
                    Office, and the Institutional Research Office. <lb/> &#x002A;FTF means full-time
                    freshmen.</p>
                <ornament type="characters">- - - - - - - - - </ornament>
                <p><name>Ms. Key</name>, as Chair of the Educational Policy
                    Committee, gave a presentation on technology transfer, focusing on the marketing
                    of technology developed at the University. At the end of her presentation, it
                    was agreed that she, the Provost, the Vice President for Research, and <name>Mr.
                        Sandridge</name> would study the problems in this regard and report back to
                    the Board. </p>
                <p>The Board recessed at 4:35 p.m.</p>
                <p>The Board resumed its Retreat, in Open Session, at 8:15 a.m., on
                        <date value="2007-07-28">Saturday, July 28<hi rend="super">th</hi>,</date> and met with <name>Mr.
                        Charles Steger</name>, the President of Virginia Tech. <name>Mr.
                        Steger</name> thanked the Board for the University's support in the
                    aftermath of the tragic events at Blacksburg in April, talked a bit about
                    Virginia Tech's role in the state, and mentioned his school's many joint
                    ventures and other cooperative efforts with the University. </p>
                <p>At the conclusion of his remarks, at 8:40 a.m., the Board went
                    into Executive Session after adopting the following motion: </p>
                <p>That the Board of Visitors go into Closed Session to review with
                    the Chair of the Honor Committee the Committee's procedures and specific student
                    cases and to discuss same with the General Counsel, seeking his legal advice and
                    guidance in connection therewith, as provided for in Section 2.2-3711
                    &lpar;A&rpar; &lpar;2&rpar; and &lpar;7&rpar; of the <hi rend="underline">Code
                        of Virginia</hi>. </p>
                <pb n="7399"/>
                <p>The Board resumed its meeting in Open Session at 10:40 a.m., and
                    adopted the following resolution certifying that its meeting in Executive
                    Session had been held in accordance with the provisions of the Virginia Freedom
                    of Information Act: </p>
                <p>That we vote on and record our certification that, to the best of
                    each Board member knowledge, only public business matters lawfully exempted from
                    open meeting requirements and which were identified in the motion&lpar;s&rpar;
                    authorizing the closed session, were heard, discussed or considered in closed
                    session. </p>
                <p>The Board then heard a presentation by <name>Mr.
                    Littlepage</name>, Director of Athletics, and <name>Mr. Vanderbeek</name>,
                    Associate Athletic Director for Business Operations, on Athletics financing and
                    operations. They went into some detail on revenues and expenses, both at present
                    and projected, and on the finances of the John Paul Jones Arena. <name>Mr.
                        Littlepage</name> talked, too, of other concerns: facility needs &mdash;
                    both new capital projects and renovations and maintenance, the recruiting and
                    retention of coaches and staff, and so on. </p>
                <ornament type="characters">- - - - - - - - - - - - </ornament>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="statement" id="d8">
                <p>On motion, the meeting was adjourned at 12:15 p.m.</p>
                <signed>Respectfully submitted, <lb/>
                    <name>Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr.</name><lb/> Secretary</signed>

                <trailer>AGG:jb <lb/> These minutes have been posted to the University of Virginia
                    Board of Visitors website. <lb/>
                    <xref url="http://www.virginia.edu/bov/publicminutes.html"
                        >http://www.virginia.edu/bov/publicminutes.html </xref></trailer>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="addenda" id="d9">
                <pb n="7400"/>
                <head>ADDENDUM TO THE OFFICIAL MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF THE BOARD OF VISITORS OF
                    THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA </head>
                <p>Meeting Date: <dateRange from="2007-07-27" to="2007-07-28">July
                        27-28, 2007</dateRange>
                </p>
                <div2 type="resolution" id="d10">
                    <head>CERTIFICATION OF EXECUTIVE MEETING </head>
                    <p>The Board of Visitors, sitting in Open Session, unanimously
                        adopted a resolution certifying that while meeting in Executive Session
                        &mdash; as permitted by the relevant provisions of the <hi rend="underline"
                            >Code of Virginia</hi> &mdash; only public business authorized by its
                        motion and lawfully exempted from consideration were discussed in closed
                        session. </p>
                    <signed> Respectfully submitted, <lb/>
                        <name>Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr.</name><lb/> Secretary</signed>
                    <trailer>AGG:jb </trailer>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
