<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="bov_20000111"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>



<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;

<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;

<!ENTITY % ISOnum  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent">  %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent">  %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> %UVAsupp;
]>


<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of Visitors</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors meeting</title>
                <author n="110">
                    <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription and uva-dl-tei markup (TEI P4 with local customizations)</resp> 
                    <name>University of Virginia Library</name> </respStmt>
                <biblScope type="date">
                    <date value="2000-01-11">January  11, 2000</date>
                </biblScope>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date value="2008">2008</date>
                <availability status ="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the  University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>                   
                </availability>
                <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20000111</idno>
            <idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:497595</idno>
</publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-BoardOfVisitorsMinutes</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Minutes of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">BOV minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">University of Virginia Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors meeting</title>
                        <author n="110">
                            <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                            <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                        </author>
                        <biblScope type="date">
                            <date value="2000-01-11">January  11, 2000</date>
                        </biblScope>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Public minutes</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent n="300">?? pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                        <date value="2009">2009</date>
                        <availability status="public">
                            <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                                University of Virginia</p>
                            <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                        </availability>
                        <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20000111</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note n="500">
                            <p n="500|a">The official minutes contain salary information.  Access to minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia Freedom of  Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary of the Board.  Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia.  These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="524">
                            <p n="524|a">Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="520">
                            <p n="520|a">Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is the legal owner and operator of the institution.  Recorded in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            &projectDesc;
            <editorialDecl>
                &editorial_correction;
                &editorial_normalization;
                &editorial_hyphenation;
                &editorial_quotation;
                &editorial_stdVals;
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="AAT">
                    <bibl>Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language n="008" id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <term n="610">University of Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="AAT">
                    <term n="655">Minutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="uva-form">
                    <term>serial volume</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
<text id="d1">  
<body id="d2">
<div1 type="roll-call" id="d3">
    <pb n="5751"/>
    <head>TENTATIVE MINUTES  &#x2014;<lb/>
SUBJECT TO THE APPROVAL<lb/>
BY THE BOARD OF VISITORS<lb/>
<date value="2000-01-11">January 11, 2000</date></head>

<p>
The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia
met, in Open Session, at 11:00 a.m., Tuesday, <date value="2000-01-11">January 11,
2000</date>, in the Dining Conference Rooms at the University
Hospital; <name>William H. Goodwin, Jr.</name>, as Chair of the Finance
Committee, presided. <name type="present">John P. Ackerly, III, Rector, Charles
M. Caravati, Jr., M.D., William G. Crutchfield, Jr.,
Terence P. Ross, and Ms. Elizabeth A. Twohy participated in
person. T. Keister Greer, Timothy B. Robertson, Albert H.
Small, Henry L. Valentine, II, Walter F. Walker, Benjamin
P.A. Warthen, James C. Wheat, III, and Joseph E. Wolfe</name>
participated by telephone.</p>
<p>
Also present at the meeting were <name type="present">Leonard W. Sandridge,
Jr., Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., Paul J. Forch, Ms. Alice W.
Handy, and Ms. Jeanne Flippo Bailes. John T. Casteen, III
and Benton Burroughs</name> participated by telephone.</p>
    
<p><name>Mr. Goodwin</name> explained the purpose of the meeting: the
University has investments in various venture capital
partnerships. These investments are now worth over $300m
with a cost basis of about $10m. The University wishes to
enter into a swap agreement with an investment bank to
protect some of these gains. Thirteen stocks, which
account for some $260m, have been identified in this
category. The University is required to post collateral
with the bank in the amount of 25&percnt; of the value of the
stocks.</p>
<p>
As this arrangement could constitute borrowing or a
pledge of securities or other assets held by the Endowment,
it must be approved by two-thirds of the Board and then by
the Governor.</p>
<p>
    <name>Mr. Goodwin</name> told the Board he would give a more
detailed briefing in Executive Session at the Board meeting
on January 22<hi rend="super">nd</hi>.</p>

 <pb n="5752"/>
 <p>
On motion, the Board approved the following
resolution, which will be communicated to the Governor.</p>
<p>The following motion was adopted:</p>

<p>WHEREAS: It is in the best interest of the University
to provide for its officers to execute and deliver
contracts, agreements and other documentation which relate
to its endowment involving selling shares short, option
contracts, and/or swap agreements; and</p>
<p>Such contracts and agreements may constitute a
borrowing and/or pledge of securities, assets and rights
held by the endowment as authorized by Virginia Code <reg orig="23-|30.01">2330.01</reg>
with at least a two-thirds vote of the Board of
Visitors and approval of the Governor.</p>
<p>RESOLVED, subject to the approval of the Governor, the
Board of Visitors hereby approves the University entering
into a swap agreement with an investment banking firm or
financial institution in order to protect a portion of the
endowment fund against market correction, provided that
such agreement is executed within thirty calendar days of
approval by the Governor and the term of the swap agreement
may not exceed a term of more than one year and shall not
affect more than thirteen stocks held within the
University's venture capital portfolio, and including
without limitation, the pledging of endowment assets,
securities or rights, and executing such contracts and
related documentation in connection therewith as may be
advisable or necessary. The Treasurer of the University of
Virginia, or such other University officer as the Board of
Visitors may direct, is authorized to execute and deliver
such swap agreement, related contracts and documents as
necessary or advisable, provided such agreement and related
documents shall not constitute a pledge of the full faith
and credit of the Commonwealth, the University or the
Governor of Virginia. Any such agreements executed by the
University Treasurer, or such other authorized officer,
shall be reported to the Board of Visitors. The University
administration shall forthwith seek the approval of the
Governor of Virginia so as to protect the significant gains
in the new technology stocks held in the University's
endowment.</p>
<p>The Secretary took the roll. Fourteen of the sixteen
voting Members of the Board participated in the vote; all
fourteen voted to approve the resolution.</p>
        
<p>On motion, the meeting was adjourned at 11:20 a.m.</p>
<ornament type="line"/>
<p>There are attached, for the record, copies of the
letter sent to the Governor on January 11<hi rend="super">th</hi> transmitting the
resolution approved by the Board, together with the
Governor's letter of January 12<hi rend="super">th</hi> approving the swap
agreement.
</p>
    </div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
