<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> 
%dlps-teiHeader;

<!ENTITY % ISOnum  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent">  %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent">  %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> 
%UVAsupp;
]>


<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of 
Visitors</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors 
meeting</title>
                <author n="110">
                    <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription and uva-dl-tei markup (TEI P4 with local 
customizations)</resp> 
                    <name>University of Virginia Library</name> </respStmt>
                <biblScope type="date">
                    <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                </biblScope>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date value="2009">2009</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the  
University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>                   
                </availability>
                <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20060728_eac</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Minutes of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">BOV minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">University of Virginia Board of Visitors 
minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of 
Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors 
meeting</title>
                        <author n="110">
                            <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                            <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                        </author>
                        <biblScope type="date">
                            <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                        </biblScope>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Public minutes</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent n="300">?? pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <idno n="090" type="UVa call number">Accession# RG-1/1/</idno>
                        <idno type="UVa Title Control Number">a2846310</idno>  
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note n="500">
                            <p n="500|a">The official minutes contain salary information.  Access to 
minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia 
Freedom of  Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the 
Secretary of the Board.  Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct 
a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia.  
These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="524">
                            <p n="524|a">Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special 
Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="520">
                            <p n="520|a">Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is 
the legal owner and operator of the institution.  Recorded in the minutes are appointments and 
other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to 
the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            &projectDesc;
            <editorialDecl>
                &editorial_correction;
                &editorial_normalization;
                &editorial_hyphenation;
                &editorial_quotation;
                &editorial_stdVals;
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="AAT">
                    <bibl>Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language n="008" id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <term n="610">University of Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="AAT">
                    <term n="655">Minutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="uva-form">
                    <term>serial volume</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body id="d1">
            <div1 type="report" id="d2">
            <head>EXTERNAL AFFAIRS COMMITTEE</head>
                <div2 type="statement" id="d3">
                    <head>GOALS FOR 2006-07</head>
                    <p>The External Affairs Committee will have five major objectives for the Universitys 2006-07 fiscal 
                    year. These goals are: </p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent">
                            1. Successfully launch public phase of $3 billion Capital Campaign with $1.1 billion and 
                            generate $400 million in new commitments during fiscal year 2007. </item><lb/>
                        <item rend="indent">                            
                        2. Increase annual philanthropic cash flow by 10% to $240 million. </item><lb/>
                        <item rend="indent">                            
                        3. Implement changes relating to University-wide foundations as per BOV recommendations. </item><lb/>
                        <item rend="indent">                            
                            4. Continue to reinforce constituent engagement both regionally and University-wide so as to 
                            enhance relationships, create awareness and build support among alumni, parents and 
                            friends of the University. </item><lb/>
                        <item rend="indent">                            
                            5. Improve University-wide communications with the establishment of a centralized marketing 
                            effort, a branding initiative and a crisis management plan. </item><lb/>
                    </list>
                    <p>Attached are tactical details and sub-set objectives.</p>
             
                </div2>
                <div2 type="statement" id="d4">
                    <pb n="2"/>
                    <head>Tactical Objectives </head>
                    <div3 type="section" id="d5">
                        <head>Fund-raising: University Development and University-related Foundations </head>
                        <list>
                            <item rend="indent">
                                1. Provide leadership and oversight in assessing the strengths and weaknesses of the Universitys 
                                overall fund-raising operation (<date value="2007-06-30">06/30/07</date>) </item>
                               
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Lead an institution-wide effort to assess the efficacy and sustainability of current fund-
                                        raising operations relative to serving the foundation and the University. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Provide guidance in determining those peer institutions against which the University should 
                                        benchmark its current philanthropic efforts. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Support the exploration of alternative modelsin structure, in governance and in funding
                                        that potentially provide more viable long-term support for the Universitys ambitious fund-
                                        raising goals. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Provide counsel to select and implement a sustainable funding mechanism for the centrally-
                                        based development operation. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Lead efforts to insure support and ownership by all interested partiesDeans, Foundations 
                                        heads, senior administrators, donors, gift officers, and other constituencies. </item>
                                
                           
                            <item rend="indent"> 
                                2. Continue to provide leadership and oversight of efforts to reach the campaign goal of $3 billion </item><lb/>
                              
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                    Support efforts to generate at least $400 million in new campaign commitments during FY-07. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Support strategies toward the goal of increasing new future support commitments by 10% 
                                        (~$18 million in FY-07). </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Hold all University gift officers responsible for compliance with standardized performance-
                                        based management tools that improve discipline and coordination. In year two of this 
                                        process, increased attention will be given to: (a) tracking of proposals, both planned and 
                                        active, and (b) evaluating and assessing the appropriateness of individual school and unit 
                                        contact goals. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Motivate ever-increasing integration of University Developments fund-raising efforts with 
                                        that of the Schools and units. Utilize the Deans Development Forum to foster and nurture 
                                        cross-University collaboration, particularly around emerging University priorities. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Evaluate and approve plans and strategies related to emerging University fund-raising 
                                        priorities (ie, Science and Technology, the Shannon Center, the Institute on Aging). </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Focus efforts of President Casteen on the direct solicitation of, or approval of solicitation 
                                        strategies for, all principal gift prospects at $5M and above. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Monitor and evaluate compliance with all mechanisms and policies designed to improve 
                                        prospect management, particularly new efforts to better qualify, cultivate, and coordinate 
                                        prospects at the $1M+ level. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Formally declare, and participate in the public campaign kick-off weekend 
                                        (<date value="2006-09-28">September 28</date> - <date value="2006-10-01">October 1, 2006</date>). </item>
                     
                        <pb n="3"/>
                        
                                     <item rend="indent">
                                           Launch the public phase of the capital campaign with at least $1.1 billion in campaign 
                                           commitments. </item>
                                      <item rend="indent">
                                           Guide and support planning and implementation of regional kickoffs, helping to maintain 
                                           focus and visibility through participation where appropriate. </item>
                                                         
                            <item rend="indent">
                                3. Select, support, and assess the progress of those fund-raising initiatives determined to directly or 
                                indirectly influence the Universitys national ranking and reputation.</item>
                             
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                        Support efforts to assess and insure the continued alignment of campaign goals with the 
                                        Universitys six- and ten-year plans, as determined by the Special Committee on Planning. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                    Encourage increased giving participation by alumni, parents, and friends through evaluation 
                                        of the work plan and recommendations of the Annual Giving Advisory Board Task Force, 
                                        studying best-in-class annual giving practices and programs (Task force created and 
                                        approved by President-<date value="2005-06-30">06/30/05</date>. Report findings and recommendations to President and 
                                        BOV no later than 01/07. </item>
                                    <item rend="indent">
                                    Increase philanthropic cash flow by 10%, to a total of $240 million per annum. </item>
                               </list>
                    </div3>
                    <div3 type="section" id="d6">
                        <head>Constituent Engagement</head>
                        <list>
                            <item rend="indent">
                                1. Provide assistance and oversight toward the goal of enhancing relationships, creating awareness, 
                                and building support among alumni, parents, and friends in the life of the University. </item><lb/>
                            <item rend="indent">    
                                2. Promote the value of constituent engagement internally, among the deans and other institutional 
                                leaders. Maximizing our long-term return on investment will require continued, loyal, and 
                                visible support. </item><lb/>
                            <item rend="indent">                                
                                3. Assist with strategic planning efforts around two prioritiesregional engagement efforts and 
                                campus partnershipsas efforts to staff this division continue in FY-07. </item><lb/>
                            <item rend="indent">
                                4. Support efforts toward a stronger partnership between the University
                                and the Alumni Association, through joint strategic planning and performance benchmarks. </item><lb/>
                        </list>
                    </div3>
                    <div3 type="section" id="d7">
                        <head>Public Affairs </head>
                        <list>
                            <item rend="indent">
                                1. Support and guide the creation of a model Public Affairs organization (currently in progress); 
                                assist as appropriate in the establishment of the academic divisions first centralized 
                                marketing department. </item><lb/>
                            <item rend="indent">                                
                                2. Assess the recommendations of McCann-Erickson regarding the Universitys key messages; 
                                guide implementation of the Universitys branding initiative. </item><lb/>
                        </list>
                        <pb n="4"/>
                        <list>
                            <item rend="indent">
                                3. Provide input and oversight into the development of a crisis management plan, including the 
                                creation of a SWAT team to implement the plan as needed.</item><lb/> 
                        </list>
                    </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>



