<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> 
%dlps-teiHeader;

<!ENTITY % ISOnum  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent">  %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent">  %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> 
%UVAsupp;
]>


<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of 
Visitors</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors 
meeting</title>
                <author n="110">
                    <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription and uva-dl-tei markup (TEI P4 with local 
customizations)</resp> 
                    <name>University of Virginia Library</name> </respStmt>
                <biblScope type="date">
                    <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                </biblScope>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">24</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date value="2009">2009</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the  
University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>                   
                </availability>
                <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20060728_scop</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Minutes of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">BOV minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">University of Virginia Board of Visitors 
minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of 
Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors 
meeting</title>
                        <author n="110">
                            <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                            <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                        </author>
                        <biblScope type="date">
                            <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                        </biblScope>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Public minutes</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent n="300">?? pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <idno n="090" type="UVa call number">Accession# RG-1/1/</idno>
                        <idno type="UVa Title Control Number">a2846310</idno>  
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note n="500">
                            <p n="500|a">The official minutes contain salary information.  Access to 
minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the procedures of the Virginia 
Freedom of  Information Act (Code of Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the 
Secretary of the Board.  Researchers interested in obtaining access to these records should direct 
a request in writing to the Office of the Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia.  
These public minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no restrictions.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="524">
                            <p n="524|a">Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special 
Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="520">
                            <p n="520|a">Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body which is 
the legal owner and operator of the institution.  Recorded in the minutes are appointments and 
other personnel decisions concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities, gifts to 
the university, and all other board actions, decisions and resolutions.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            &projectDesc;
            <editorialDecl>
                &editorial_correction;
                &editorial_normalization;
                &editorial_hyphenation;
                &editorial_quotation;
                &editorial_stdVals;
            </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="AAT">
                    <bibl>Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language n="008" id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <term n="610">University of Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="AAT">
                    <term n="655">Minutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="uva-form">
                    <term>serial volume</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body id="d1">
   <div1 type="report" id="d2">
    <pb n="Page 1 of 4"/>
    <head>UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA BOARD OF VISITORS <lb/>SPECIAL COMMITTEE ON PLANNING </head>
    <div2 type="contents" id="d3">
     <head>2005-2006 GOALS STATUS REPORT</head>
     
      <p><hi rend="bold">
          1. Complete six-year revenue/expense/academic plan for submission to the state as required by 
          the Restructuring legislation prior to October 1; extend the plan to cover a ten-year period 
          (including all fund sources) in support of the institutional objectives and ranking goals that 
          will be established by the Board.</hi></p>
       <list>
        <item rend="indent">
           The Full Board approved the six-year plan on <date value="2005-09-24">September 24, 2005</date>.</item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
           The Special Committee on Planning reviewed a preliminary ten-year financial plan at its 
           February and June 2006 meetings. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
           The preliminary ten-year financial plan was developed by including all University resources 
          and applying at least the same level of sophistication as used in the development of the six-year 
          plan. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
           The preliminary ten-year financial plan includes the necessary financial resources over the 
          ten-year period to ensure that we are on track to meet Board commitments related to Access 
          UVa, research enhancement, compensation, diversity, maintenance of facilities, international 
          programs, alumni engagement, and the student information system. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
           The preliminary ten-year financial plan will be refined throughout the fall and winter and 
           finalized in conjunction with the academic plan in February 2007. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
        Goal ongoing. </item><lb/>
       </list>
 
      <p><hi rend="bold">
       2. Reconsider and propose policies, based on existing policies and assumptions, to ensure that 
       they are up-to-date and appropriate in support of the ten-year plan.</hi></p>
       <list>
        <item rend="indent">
         The Finance Committee discussed a review of the 20-25 most significant financial policies 
        and recommended preparation of new policies as appropriate. This work included identification and 
        examination of each policys purpose, its adequacy to sustain the intended purpose, and the 
        need for revision. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
        It was determined that the Board of Visitors recently examined and validated several policies 
       (compensation/salaries, research, tuition, enrollment, deferred maintenance, Access UVa, and 
       self-sufficiency agreements for professional schools) which did not require further review. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
        At its April 2006 meeting, the Finance Committee approved revisions to the debt policy, the 
       interest rate risk management policy, and approved new policies for operating, maintenance, 
       replacement and renewal reserves. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
        The Full Board heard a report on the issue of graduate student fellowships and funding at its 
        June 2006 meeting. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
        The Full Board will continue its policy review by examining the funding of central 
        development activities and the policy on University-related foundations during 2006-07. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
        Goal completed. </item><lb/>
       </list>
     
      <p><hi rend="bold">
         3. Review existing Board commitments and priorities related to compensation, research, 
         deferred maintenance, diversity, alumni engagement and financial aid and assess the impact 
         of these commitments on the University's ten-year plan and infrastructure requirements. </hi></p>
       <list>
        <item rend="indent">
          The preliminary ten-year financial plan includes the necessary financial resources over the 
         ten-year period to ensure that we are on track to meet Board commitments related to Access UVa, 
         research enhancement, compensation, diversity, maintenance of facilities, international 
         programs, alumni engagement, and the student information system.</item>
       </list>
       <p rend="left">
     Source: Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer <lb/>
     Date: <date value="2006-07-20">July 20, 2006</date></p>
     <pb n="Page 2 of 4"/>
    
       <list>
        <item rend="indent">
           The preliminary academic plan, which will be presented to the Full Board at its Retreat, 
           contains initiatives that may serve as strategic advantages for the University in the future. These 
           initiatives will require resources beyond those identified in the preliminary ten-year financial 
           plan or in the current Capital Campaign goal. The Special Committee on Planning and 
           University administrators have begun to identify alternative financial strategies to support these initiatives. 
           These alternative financial strategies were discussed on a preliminary basis by the Committee at 
           its May and June meetings. The work of the Special Committee on Planning will continue to 
           focus on this preliminary assessment of financial options that may be available to fund these 
           initiatives. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">Goal completed.</item>
       </list>
 
      <p><hi rend="bold">
           4. Determine appropriate aspirational position for the University; develop measures to assess 
           whether we are making progress toward attainment of institutional objectives.<lb/> 
           <hi rend="italic">Aspirational Position: </hi></hi></p>
       <list>
        <item rend="indent">
            The Special Committee heard the Top 15 (<hi rend="italic">US News</hi>) gap analysis at the February 2006 
           meeting, which outlined what resources are needed based on the information available to us 
           from the <hi rend="italic">U.S. News and World Report</hi> data, the Universitys preliminary ten-year financial plan and 
           known priorities to achieve a Top 15 status within ten years.</item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
            The Special Committee on Planning also heard information on research rankings and the 
           results of an overall external analysis in which rankings were analyzed in an effort to understand how 
           to improve in key evaluation categories. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
            At its April 2006 meeting, the Special Committee on Planning discussed the financial realities 
           of meeting the top 15 goal  that it may be nearly impossible to raise enough money to close the 
           gap. The Committee concluded that the University should proceed by protecting our <hi rend="italic">US News 
           and World Report</hi> ranking through targeting specific areas identified by gap analysis. At the 
           Retreat, the Board will hear a rankings improvement plan, designed to help guide the University 
           through a long-term strategy to realize its aspirations. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
            At the April meeting, the Special Committee on Planning concluded that the University will 
           only excel by taking aggressive steps to strategically position itself relative to its peers in certain 
           areas, while also protecting <hi rend="italic">US News</hi> ranking. At the Retreat, the Board will focus on the 
           preliminary academic plan and identification of major initiatives, or big ideas on which the 
           University can focus its resources and effort to obtain national and global preeminence. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">Goal completed. </item>
       </list>
   
        <p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Performance Measures:</hi></hi></p>
       <list>
        <item rend="indent">
         The Special Committee on Planning reviewed the proposed performance measures at the 
        February, April, and June 2006 meetings. A set of performance measures which address critical 
        areas of academic quality, financial and physical resources, diversity, and the Medical Center 
        will be presented at the Retreat. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
         The performance measures will be further refined in 2006-07 as the academic plan is 
         finalized. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">
         The Board will continue to receive updates on the implementation of Restructuring, including 
        the performance metrics associated with each state goal, and each of the six core functional 
        areas. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent">Goal ongoing. </item><lb/>
       </list>

     <p>
      Source: Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer <lb/>
      Date: <date value="2006-07-20">July 20, 2006 </date></p>
   
    </div2>
    <div2 type="section" id="d4">
        <pb n="Page 3 of 4"/>
     <head>UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA BOARD OF VISITORS<lb/> 
       SPECIAL COMMITTEE ON PLANNING <lb/>
       2006-2007 GOALS </head>
     <p>
        The focus of this period will be to conclude the planning process with Board of Visitors 
        input, having fully developed strategic alternatives, identified the proper support for 
        programs, and aligned the priorities reflected in the Capital Campaign with those in the 
        academic plan. By February 2007, we will present a final ten-year academic and financial 
        plan, having identified funds for the initiatives included therein. </p>
     <list>
      <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
          1.	Complete ten-year academic and financial plan in support of the institutional objectives 
          and ranking goals established by the Board. Work to further define the academic plan 
          with appropriate faculty and administrative committees.</hi></item><lb/>
      <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">          
          2. Retain a consultant to continue the examination of the Universitys strengths, weaknesses, 
          opportunities and threats. </hi></item><lb/>
      <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">          
          3. Propose and select major initiatives, or big ideas to strategically position and further 
          strengthen the University based on an in-depth assessment of existing strengths, 
          opportunities and threats, as well as known strategies of appropriate elite universities. 
          Explore viable financing alternatives to identify funds to support these major initiatives. 
      </hi></item><lb/>
      <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">          
       4. Ensure the academic plan and the capital campaign case statement are complementary. </hi></item><lb/>
      <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">          
          5. Refine performance measures to assess whether we are making progress toward attainment 
          of institutional objectives. </hi></item>
     </list>
  
     <p>
        Source: Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer <lb/>
        Date: <date value="2006-07-20">July 20, 2006</date></p>
   
    </div2>
    <div2 type="section" id="d5">
        <pb n="Page 4 of 4"/>
     <head>UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA BOARD OF VISITORS <lb/>
     SPECIAL COMMITTEE ON PLANNING <lb/>
     2006-2007 WORK PLAN </head>
   
      <p><hi rend="bold">     
          1. Complete ten-year academic and financial plan in support of the institutional objectives and 
          ranking goals established by the Board. Work to further define the academic plan with 
          appropriate faculty and administrative committees. </hi></p>
       <list>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           Fall 2006:</hi> Provost will work with appropriate faculty and administrative committees to further 
          define the preliminary academic plan. The results of this effort will be reported to the Special 
          Committee on Planning at its November meeting. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           February 2007:</hi> Executive Vice President and Provost to present a final ten-year academic 
           and financial plan, having identified funds for the initiatives included therein. </item><lb/>
       </list>
 
      <p><hi rend="bold">
          2. Retain a consultant to continue the examination of the Universitys strengths, weaknesses, 
          opportunities and threats.</hi></p>
       <list>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
          Summer 2006:</hi> Consultant to be retained. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           August 2006:</hi> Consultant to meet with the Chair of the Special Committee on Planning. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           November/December 2006:</hi> Results of the situation analysis to be presented to the Special 
           Committee on Planning, depending on availability. </item><lb/>
       </list>
  
      <p><hi rend="bold">
          3. Propose and select major initiatives, or big ideas to strategically position and further 
          strengthen the University based on an in-depth assessment of existing strengths, 
          opportunities and threats, as well as known strategies of appropriate elite universities. 
          Explore viable financing alternatives to identify funds to support these major initiatives.</hi></p>
       <list>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           Summer 2006:</hi> Provost to present preliminary identification of major initiatives to the Board 
           of  Visitors at its Retreat. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           Fall 2006:</hi> Conduct situation analysis; use results to inform criteria for selection. Discuss 
          criteria setting with Special Committee on Planning at the November or December 2006 
          meetings, based on availability of situation analysis results. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           November 2006:</hi> Review strategies of appropriate elite universities with Special Committee 
           on  Planning. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           December 2006:</hi> Review financing alternatives to fund major initiatives with Special 
           Committee on Planning. </item><lb/>
         <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           January 2007:</hi> Special Committee on Planning to use criteria to decide on major initiatives to 
           include in final academic plan. </item><lb/>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           February 2007:</hi> Present final major initiatives and financial alternatives incorporated in final 
           ten-year academic and financial plans. </item><lb/>
       </list>
 
      <p><hi rend="bold">
      4. Ensure the academic plan and the capital campaign case statement are complementary. </hi></p>
       <list>
        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           Fall - Winter 2007:</hi> Revisit the capital campaign case statement as academic plan is refined 
           and finalized to ensure goals are congruous. </item><lb/>
       </list>
  
        <p><hi rend="bold">          
          5. Refine performance measures to assess whether we are making progress toward attainment 
          of institutional objectives.</hi></p>
         <list>
          <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           Fall - Winter 2007:</hi> Incorporate additional metrics necessary to measure the efficiency and 
           effectiveness of meeting the goals and objectives outlined in the final academic plan. </item><lb/>
          <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
           January 2007:</hi> Report to the full Board the specific performance measures the Board is 
          required to monitor associated with the Governors twelve goals and each of the six core 
          functional areas. </item><lb/>
         </list>

     <p>
          Source: Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer <lb/>
          Date: <date value="2006-07-20">July 20, 2006</date></p>
    </div2>
   </div1>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI.2>



