<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> 
%dlps-teiHeader;

<!ENTITY % ISOnum  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent">  %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent">  %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> 
%UVAsupp;
]>


<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of
                    Visitors</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors
                    meeting</title>
                <author n="110">
                    <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription and uva-dl-tei markup (TEI P4 with
                        local customizations)</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <biblScope type="date">
                    <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                </biblScope>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">34</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date value="2009">2009</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20060728_fc</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Minutes of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">BOV minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">University of Virginia Board of Visitors
                            minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of
                            Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors
                            meeting</title>
                        <author n="110">
                            <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                            <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                        </author>
                        <biblScope type="date">
                            <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                        </biblScope>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Public minutes</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent n="300">?? pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <idno n="090" type="UVa call number">Accession# RG-1/1/</idno>
                        <idno type="UVa Title Control Number">a2846310</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note n="500">
                            <p n="500|a">The official minutes contain salary information. Access to
                                minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the
                                procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of
                                Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary
                                of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these
                                records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the
                                Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public
                                minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no
                                restrictions.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="524">
                            <p n="524|a">Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special
                                Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="520">
                            <p n="520|a">Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body
                                which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded
                                in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions
                                concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities,
                                gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and
                                resolutions.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc> &projectDesc; <editorialDecl> &editorial_correction;
                &editorial_normalization; &editorial_hyphenation; &editorial_quotation;
                &editorial_stdVals; </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="AAT">
                    <bibl>Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language n="008" id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <list>
                        <item>University of Virginia::Board of Visitors</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <term n="610">University of Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="AAT">
                    <term n="655">Minutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="uva-form">
                    <term>serial volume</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2011-06-23">June 23, 2011</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name id="lsc6v">Lorrie Chisholm, University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Minor corrections to student markup.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body id="d1">
            <div1 type="report" id="d2">
                <pb n="Page 1 of 5"/>
                <head>FINANCE COMMITTEE</head>
                <div2 type="contents" id="d3">
                    <head>2005-2006 GOALS/WORKPLAN STATUS REPORT</head>

                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold"> 1. Provide relevant financial data and support to the
                            Special Committee on Planning to facilitate the necessary policy
                            decisions regarding fundamental University operations and priorities in
                            order to complete a detailed ten-year financial plan. </hi>
                    </p>

                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent">The Full Board approved the management agreement,
                            six-year plan, and policies. </item>

                        <item rend="indent">Special Committee on Planning reviewed a preliminary
                            ten-year financial plan, preliminary situation analysis, gap analysis,
                            performance measures and external analysis. </item>

                        <item rend="indent">The Full Board discussed the issue of funding central
                            Development. </item>

                        <item rend="indent"> The Full Board approved the 2006-2007 operating budget
                            which reflects the changes and resources necessary to comply with the
                            management agreement. </item>

                        <item rend="indent">Management Agreement effective <date value="2006-07-01"
                                >July 1, 2006</date>.</item>

                        <item rend="indent">Goal ongoing.</item>
                        <lb/>
                    </list>

                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold"> 2. Fulfill Restructuring requirements at the maximum level
                            to enable the University to take full advantage of the enabling
                            legislation.</hi>
                    </p>

                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"> The Full Board approved the management agreement,
                            six-year plan, and policies.</item>

                        <item rend="indent">The Full Board approved tuition and fees for 2006-2007. </item>

                        <item rend="indent">Management agreement effective <date value="2006-07-01"
                                >>July 1, 2006</date>.</item>

                        <item rend="indent">Goal completed. </item>

                    </list>

                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold"> 3. Establish a debt policy that preserves the Universitys
                            Aaa bond rating, with special attention to accelerating the development
                            of research facilities. </hi>
                    </p>

                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"> The Finance Committee thoroughly evaluated existing
                            debt policy, and approved revisions to both the debt policy and the
                            interest rate risk management policy. </item>

                        <item rend="indent">Goal completed. </item>
                    </list>

                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold"> 4. Ensure the Universitys benefits plan is cost-effective
                            and competitive with best-in-class institutions of higher education.
                        </hi></p>

                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"> The Finance Committee received its annual report on the
                            UVa Health Plan, including an external assessment of the Universitys
                            benefits plan which benchmarked it against other plans. The UVa plan
                            compared very favorably. </item>

                        <item rend="indent">Goal completed.</item>

                    </list>

                    <p>
                        <hi rend="bold"> 5. Develop appropriate policies to establish operating,
                            maintenance, replacement, and renewal reserves. </hi>
                    </p>

                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"> The Finance Committee thoroughly evaluated different
                            categories of reserves at the University and approved revisions to the
                            capital and operating reserve policies based on that review. </item>

                        <item rend="indent"> The Executive Vice President will work in 2006-2007 to
                            ensure appropriate procedures are in place such that reserves are
                            established and maintained consistent with the Finance Committees
                            evaluation. </item>

                        <item rend="indent">Goal completed. </item>

                    </list>

                    <p> Source: Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating
                        Officer<lb/> Date: <date value="2006-07-17">July 17, 2006 </date></p>

                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" id="d4">
                    <pb n="Page 2 of 5 "/>
                    <head>2006-2007 GOALS</head>

                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 1. Explore viable financing alternatives to identify funds
                            to support key initiatives that may serve as strategic advantages for
                            the University consistent with the ten-year plan. Finalize ten-year
                            financial plan as ten-year academic plan is refined. </hi></p>
                    <p>In the coming months, the Board of Visitors will review the preliminary
                        academic plan, which will contain initiatives that may serve as strategic
                        advantages for the University in the future. These initiatives, which will
                        continue to emerge over the next several months, will most likely require
                        resources beyond those identified in the preliminary ten-year financial plan
                        or in the current Capital Campaign goal. Accordingly, the Special Committee
                        on Planning and the administration have begun a preliminary analysis to
                        identify alternative financial strategies to support these initiatives. The
                        Special Committee on Planning is seeking the advice of the Finance Committee
                        to assess alternative financial options that may be available to fund these
                        initiatives. </p>

                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 2. Implement processes to comply with responsibilities in
                            the Management Agreement in the six core functional areas (Capital
                            Projects, Leases, Information Technology, Procurement, Human Resources,
                            and Financial Administration). Continue efforts to educate the
                            University community about Restructuring. </hi></p>
                    <p> Our long-term success depends on our ability to a) manage our operations
                        under policies established by the Board of Visitors, b) rely on tuition and
                        private support as stable revenue streams, and c) position ourselves to act
                        quickly, efficiently, and effectively as an organization, free of
                        unnecessary limitations imposed by the state. Over almost two decades, we
                        have seen our status evolve from a traditional governmental agency to a
                        major research university with substantial responsibilities and authority to
                        manage our affairs. We have gained many operational benefits since
                        1995-1996, when codified autonomy was established for the Medical Center. On
                        April 6, 2005, the Restructuring legislation was passed, advancing our
                        position as we aspire to become a top-ranked institution of higher
                        education. </p>

                    <p>We have focused our efforts this past year to implement the restructuring
                        initiative by meeting the specific requirements of the Act, which provides a
                        broad framework to enable us to redefine our relationship with the
                        Commonwealth in a manner befitting our established credibility and
                        integrity. The Full Board has approved the management agreement, six-year
                        plan, and policies, as well as tuition and fees for 2006-2007. The
                        management agreement became effective <date value="2006-07-01">July 1,
                            2006</date>. </p>

                    <p>In 2006-2007, in order to continue with the effective implementation of the
                        restructuring initiative, the University must facilitate processes to assist
                        the six core functional areas (Capital Projects, Leases, Information
                        Technology, Procurement, Human Resources, and Financial Administration) in
                        complying with responsibilities in the management agreement in their
                        respective areas. Of particular importance will be the responsibility of the
                        Finance Committee to monitor the development of the new Human Resources
                        system to accommodate University staff.</p>

                    <p> Source: Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer
                        <lb/> Date: <date value="2006-07-17">July 17, 2006</date></p>
                    <pb n="Page 3 of 5"/>

                    <p> The Finance Committee will provide oversight to a) an ongoing program of
                        education for faculty and staff related to the functioning and purposes of
                        restructuring; b) the development of management reports that will
                        demonstrate compliance with and achievement of the expectations associated
                        with restructuring; and c) strategies for keeping legislative staff and
                        legislators informed about the results of restructuring for the purpose of
                        building trust and confidence in the work done at UVa. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 3. Explore funding options for development activities to
                            free up Rector and Visitors unrestricted endowment funds. Ensure the
                            foundations compliance with the policy on University-related
                            foundations. </hi></p>
                    <p>The assessment of the funding of development operations is a key element of,
                        and closely related to, the charge given to the External Affairs Committee
                        by the Rector to examine the relationship between the University and its
                        related foundations. The Finance Committee could assist the External Affairs
                        Committee in the assessment of the need and identification of resources to
                        fund adequately development activities for the next several years. Resource
                        requirements have reached a level such that unrestricted endowment income
                        can no longer solely support development activities. The Finance Committee
                        will continue to discuss and share with the Full Board the available options
                        to address the funding requirements through alternative sources. </p>
                    <p> The trend in recent years is for gifts, including endowment gifts, to be
                        deposited with university-affiliated foundations instead of with the Rector
                        and Visitors. The proliferation of foundations has created inefficiencies in
                        the form of excessive overhead expenses. In the longer run, there is also
                        the potential for different foundations to manage endowments to different
                        policies (including investment and spending policies) but more critically,
                        to develop their own funding priorities, instead of supporting
                        university-wide strategic directions. </p>
                    <p> In support of work being conducted by the External Affairs Committee, the
                        Finance Committee, the External Affairs Committee, and indeed the Full Board
                        will continue to discuss these topics in more depth in order to free up
                        Rector and Visitors unrestricted endowment funds, examine compliance with
                        the Universitys policy on University-related foundations and identify ways
                        to ensure consistent and supportive practices among University-related
                        foundations. Also in conjunction with the External Affairs Committee, we are
                        prepared to include a review of the current system of financial oversight of
                        foundations and to propose revisions necessary to achieve the level of
                        oversight of University-related foundations that the Board of Visitors
                        expects. </p>

                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 4. Create a funding model for research, paying particular
                            attention to unique research needs related to animal care and restricted
                            research. </hi></p>
                    <p> The Finance Committee will examine options for funding research in the
                        humanities and social sciences, as well as the hard sciences - at the
                        University. The work will encompass what is required to provide flexible
                        space on a cost-effective basis for research, addressing graduate student
                        funding needs and providing an appropriate research infrastructure,
                        including compliance. In assessing these issues, the Committee will focus on
                        providing the right incentives to further the institutions overall research
                        goals in fields which provide special opportunities for sponsored funding
                        and growth. This effort is justified in part to meet the Governors goals for
                        research accomplishments and economic development in the management
                        agreements. </p>

                    <p>Source: Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer
                        <lb/> Date: <date value="2006-07-17">July 17, 2006</date></p>
                    <pb n="Page 4 of 5"/>

                    <p> Special emphasis will be placed on understanding the unique funding issues
                        associated with the need for animal care facilities. The University has
                        barely kept up with the needs for this kind of space and has seldom had any
                        capacity beyond immediate needs. If it is possible to provide space for
                        research and animals ahead of immediate demands, the University will create
                        a market advantage that will improve its competitiveness in this area of
                        academic work.</p>
                    <p> Recently it has become clear that the University must examine whether it
                        will conduct restricted research an area that is growing as the emphasis on
                        homeland security grows. What is even more noteworthy is the fact that some
                        research is migrating to the restricted category, when it would not have
                        been previously considered as such, especially in Engineering. The conduct
                        of restricted research comes with unique facility needs and requirements.
                        The Finance Committee will examine the fiscal implications of providing this
                        type of space. </p>

                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 5. Develop a financial plan to support the emphasis of the
                            Educational Policy and the Student Affairs and Athletics Committees on
                            improving the undergraduate experience, in particular the quality of
                            undergraduate advising. </hi></p>
                    <p> Several Board of Visitors committees have emphasized the important role of
                        student advising, especially at the undergraduate level. The Finance
                        Committee intends to understand the financial implications of improved
                        advising in order to be ready to respond to the fiscal impact assessments in
                        this area. To a large extent this may be a function of the resources
                        routinely provided to a school or department for teaching and research.
                        However, there may be ways the University can truly distinguish itself among
                        its peers with appropriate collaborative planning. This goal will require
                        those staffing the Finance Committee to be fully cognizant and involved in
                        the work of other committees. </p>

                    <p> Source: Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating
                        Officer<lb/> Date: <date value="2006-07-17">July 17, 2006 </date></p>

                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" id="d7">
                    <pb n="Page 5 of 5"/>
                    <head>2006-2007 WORKPLAN</head>


                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 1. Explore viable financing alternatives to identify funds
                            to support key initiatives that may serve as strategic advantages for
                            the University consistent with the ten-year plan. Finalize the ten-year
                            financial plan as ten-year academic plan is refined. </hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> July 2006:</hi> Full Board to discuss
                            preliminary academic plan and strategic advantages.</item>

                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> Fall 2006:</hi> Full Board to discuss
                            academic plan and strategic advantages, after review with faculty and
                            key constituents. </item>

                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> Fall and Winter 2006:</hi> Finance
                            Committee to continue identification of financing alternatives. </item>

                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> January 2007:</hi> Finance Committee to
                            decide on recommended financing alternatives. </item>

                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> February 2007:</hi> Provost and
                            Executive Vice President to present final academic plan and strategic
                            advantages, along with ten-year financial plan and financing
                            alternatives proposal to the Full Board.</item>

                    </list>

                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 2. Implement processes to comply with responsibilities in
                            the Management Agreement in the six core functional areas (Capital
                            Projects, Leases, Information Technology, Procurement, Human Resources,
                            and Financial Administration). Continue efforts to educate the
                            University community about Restructuring. </hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> Fall 2006:</hi> Develop quarterly
                            reporting templates for internal and external purposes. </item>

                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> January 2007:</hi> Report to the full
                            Board on the specific performance measures the Board is required to
                            monitor associated with the Governors twelve goals. </item>

                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> June 2007:</hi> Report on restructuring
                            implementation progress in each of the six areas and unit- specific and
                            institution-wide restructuring education efforts. </item>

                    </list>

                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 3. Explore funding options for development activities to
                            free up Rector and Visitors unrestricted endowment funds. Ensure the
                            foundations compliance with the policy on University-related
                            foundations.</hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> July 2006:</hi> Full Board to discuss
                            issue at Board of Visitors Retreat.</item>

                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> January 2007:</hi> Present an
                            assessment of foundation compliance monitoring. </item>

                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> April 2007:</hi> Provide plan for
                            consideration in University budget for 2007-2008. </item>

                    </list>

                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 4. Create a funding model for research, paying particular
                            attention to unique research needs related to animal care and restricted
                            research. </hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> January 2007:</hi> Present a
                            preliminary report on funding alternatives and strategies.</item>

                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> June 2007:</hi> Prepare a final report
                            for inclusion in 2007-2008 budget. </item>

                    </list>

                    <p><hi rend="bold"> 5. Develop a financial plan to support the emphasis of the
                            Educational Policy and the Student Affairs and Athletics Committees on
                            improving the undergraduate experience, in particular the quality of
                            undergraduate advising. </hi></p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold"> April 2007:</hi> Present financial plan
                            (or as needed).</item>

                    </list>

                    <p> Source: Office of the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer
                        <lb/> Date: <date value="2006-07-17">July 17, 2006</date></p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
