<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> 
%dlps-teiHeader;

<!ENTITY % ISOnum  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent">  %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent">  %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> 
%UVAsupp;
]>


<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of Visitors</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors meeting</title>
                <author n="110">
                    <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription and uva-dl-tei markup (TEI P4 with
                        local customizations)</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <biblScope type="date">
                    <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                </biblScope>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">25</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date value="2009">2009</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20060728_bgc</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Minutes of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">BOV minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">University of Virginia Board of Visitors
                            minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of
                            Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors
                            meeting</title>
                        <author n="110">
                            <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                            <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                        </author>
                        <biblScope type="date">
                            <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                        </biblScope>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Public minutes</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent n="300">?? pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <idno n="090" type="UVa call number">Accession# RG-1/1/</idno>
                        <idno type="UVa Title Control Number">a2846310</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note n="500">
                            <p n="500|a">The official minutes contain salary information. Access to
                                minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the
                                procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of
                                Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary
                                of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these
                                records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the
                                Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public
                                minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no
                                restrictions.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="524">
                            <p n="524|a">Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special
                                Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="520">
                            <p n="520|a">Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body
                                which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded
                                in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions
                                concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities,
                                gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and
                                resolutions.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc> &projectDesc; <editorialDecl> &editorial_correction;
                &editorial_normalization; &editorial_hyphenation; &editorial_quotation;
                &editorial_stdVals; </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="AAT">
                    <bibl>Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language n="008" id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <term n="610">University of Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="AAT">
                    <term n="655">Minutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="uva-form">
                    <term>serial volume</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body id="d1"> 
            <div1 type="report" id="d2">
                <pb n="Page 1 of 4"/>
                <head>Buildings and Grounds Committee<lb/>
                2006-07 Goals and Work Plan</head>
                <div2 type="section" id="d3">
                    <head>GOALS</head>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d4">
                        <head rend="left">1. Historic asset management</head>
                        <p>Currently UVa has one of nations most eminent collections
                            of historic buildings and landscapes, and it is the only UNESCO designated World
                            Heritage Site campus in the United States. A historic resources plan has been developed
                            to ensure that the Academical Village receives preservation treatment which conforms to
                            the highest international standards. The recently completed Historic Preservation
                            Framework Plan has been disseminated recently, and will help to inform decision-making
                            as work is proposed on the post-Jefferson buildings on Grounds.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="underline">Planned Results:</hi> The
                            completed Historic Preservation Framework Plan has been submitted to the Department of
                            Historic Resources (DHR) for review and eventual incorporation into a Memorandum of
                            Understanding with DHR that would ensure the States concurrence with its findings. It
                            will continue to help to inform decision-making as work is proposed on the
                            post-Jefferson buildings on Grounds. Based on the knowledge learned from our first tax
                            credit application (Varsity Hall), we plan to seek approval for historic tax credits to
                            defray a noteable percentage (+/- 20%) of the costs for the renewal of the Rugby Faculty
                            Apartments and other appropriate historic projects. In addition, we will continue to
                            develop Historic Structure Reports on the various components of the Academical Village,
                            including the Rotunda and Hotel A.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d5">
                        <head rend="left">2. Environmental sustainability</head>
                        <p>Given Jeffersons
                            intention that UVa's buildings would serve a didactic, as well as a practical, role in
                            every day life, it would seem appropriate that design of our current buildings do the
                            same in terms of demonstrating principles of environmental sustainability. While many
                            other leading universities have been very active in regard to "green building", we have
                            made only modest efforts to date. Our initial efforts have been directed toward
                            developing a pragmatic set of design guidelines tailored to the UVa context and its
                            natural climatic setting; and identification of best management practices as they relate
                            to the university-at-large.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="underline">Planned Results:</hi> We will see significant progress in the
                            area of environmental sustainability. Based on our experience with incorporating LEED
                            equivalency criteria into selected projects this year, we will focus on ways to
                            integrate all LEED criteria into the design of all major new buildings. </p>
                        <p>We are also
                            underway with a sustainability assessment of existing University efforts in all
                            operational areas, so that we can promote awareness and encourage the coordination among
                            sustainability program efforts at the University, ranging from water quality to
                            recycling. The data collection phase of the assessment will take place this summer, with
                            the summary report due in September 06. This will lead to the development of a
                            collaborative network of committed staff, students and faculty already involved in
                            sustainable practices.</p>
                        
                    </div3>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d6">
                        <pb n="Page 2 of 4"/>
                        <head rend="left">3. Land use: work plan, data analysis &amp; enhanced process</head>
                        <p>
                        Though UVa owns more than 5,000 acres beyond its Central Grounds, we
                        have only just begun efforts to assess comprehensively the natural systems, current
                        uses, land use constraints, etc., with the long-term goal of more strategic management
                        of existing lands and the acquisition process through a collaborative approach of the
                        Office of the Architect and the University of Virginia Foundation. This in turn will
                        provide for better decision making, stewardship, and future flexibility in the
                        institutions land use and planning. </p>
                        <p>
                        <hi rend="underline">Planned Results:</hi> Much of the preliminary support
                        work required for the Grounds Plan has been completed and we are well positioned to
                        develop a full draft of the UVa Grounds Plan in 2007. We have retained a biodiversity
                        consultant to conduct an analysis of UVa natural systems, and plan to work with
                        specialty consultants for other systems components of the Grounds Plan including
                        transportation and circulation infrastructure. As the multiple components of the Grounds
                        Plan are developed, we will synthesize them through an iterative process to develop
                        several Grounds Plans alternatives. Development of the draft Grounds Plan is a major and
                        significant focus of our land use team in 06-07.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d7">
                        <head rend="left">4. Process Improvement (new goal for 2006-2007)</head>
                        <p>
                        We are initiating a new goal for 2006-2007 with an interdepartmental Process
                        Improvement emphasis. Within this goal are three new, discrete tasks: implementation of
                        a Grounds Improvement fund; implementation of a collaborative peer review / value
                        management practice into the building design process; and standardization of the cost
                        estimate templates for all new buildings.</p>
                        <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Grounds Improvement Fund:</hi> With its colonnades,
                        gardens and overall landscape, the Lawn served as the focus of community life in
                        Jeffersons Academical Village. The larger University landscape provides the connective
                        tissue that links individual areas and facilities, providing opportunities for
                        circulation, community gatherings, events and recreation. As such, the quality of the
                        outdoor environment reflects the overall vitality of the institution. Currently there is
                        no consistent source of funding for improvements to the landscape infrastructure of the
                        University other than the 6-year capital program, which is almost exclusively focused on
                        building construction and renovation. Implementation of the Grounds Improvement Fund
                        will provide a mechanism to ensure that this community infrastructure system will be
                        (re)developed as necessary to improve its appearance, functionality, and safety and to
                        promote conservation in both land use and resources utilization.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Value Management / Cost Control:</hi>
                            With spiraling construction costs, we have recognized a need to refine the
                            Value Management program and to develop a prototype process for developing and
                            implementing improved cost models. Our goal is to partner with Facilities Management to
                            better incorporate value management into the design process, through a systematic and
                            collaborative peer review at both schematic and design development stages.</p>
                        <pb n="Page 3 of 4"/>
                        <p>Results: <lb/>
                        <hi rend="italic">Grounds Improvement Fund:</hi> A defined percentage contribution applied to the
                        total construction cost for all approved capital projects will provide the funding to
                        support a University-wide program that corresponds to a typical municipal public works
                        program, including upgrades to paths, bus and bicycle facilities, outdoor spaces,
                        lighting, signs, site furnishings, and public art.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Value Management Process:</hi> A
                        collaborative workshop process involving members and outside peer reviewers will develop
                        innovative, cost and quality conscious options for managing budget and schedule as well
                        as improving each of our major capital projects.</p>
                        <p><hi rend="italic">Cost Estimating Templates:</hi> By
                        standardizing the reports for each cost consultant on every major project, we will not
                        only be more capable of making strong managerial decisions for current work, but also
                        more able to refine our project-type benchmarking information for planning future
                        development.</p>
                    </div3>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d8">
                        <head rend="left">5. Safety &amp; Security (new goal for 2006-2007)</head>
                        <p>The most important
                            assets of the University are its students, faculty and staff; its facilities and
                            grounds; and its information. These assets are at risk from both natural and man- made
                            disasters. The University must endeavor to discover and to assess its vulnerabilities,
                            to protect its assets with prevention measures, to develop a plan of action to follow if
                            an event does occur, and to ensure resiliency of the organization in the aftermath of
                            such an event. The physical environment plays an enormous role in the development of a
                            comprehensive security plan.</p>
                        <p>
                            <hi rend="underline">Results:</hi> A detailed assessment of current issues and
                            settings will lead to the development of a set of security guidelines to direct the
                            design of all new major building and landscape projects.</p>
                       
                    </div3>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" id="d9">
                    <head>WORK PLAN </head>
                    <pb n="Page 4 of 4"/>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d10">
                        <head rend="left">1. Historic asset management</head>
                            <list>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">January 2007</hi>: Approval of first tax credit application
                                (Varsity Hall); completed outline for second application (Rugby Faculty Apts).</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">June 2007</hi>: Completion of restoration study, 
                                    design drawings and specifications, and cost
                                    study for Pavilion X, Lawn Rooms and adjacent Colonnades.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">April 2007</hi>: Completion of
                                    Historic Structure Report for Rotunda </item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">June 2007</hi>: Draft agreement with Thomas Jefferson
                                    Foundation regarding a joint building conservation institute and related conservation
                                    facility completed.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">December 2007</hi>: Completion of Historic Structure Report for Hotel A.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">December 2007</hi>: Construction of alleyway and pavilion courtyard paving and lighting
                                prototype area complete.</item>
                            </list></div3>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d11">
                        <head rend="left">2. Environmental sustainability</head>
                            <list>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">December 2006</hi>: Completion of
                                    LEED certification criteria checklist and cost benefit analysis with users incorporated
                                    into design phase of all major new buildings.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">June 2007</hi>: Web-based system for regular
                                    communication and information among sustainability proponents established.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">October 2007</hi>:
                                Completion of inventory of existing University sustainability program efforts.</item><lb/>
                            </list>
                    </div3>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d12">
                        <head rend="left">3. Land use: Work plan, data analysis and enhanced process</head>
                            <list>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">October 2006</hi>: Completion of
                                    consultant study analysis of UVa natural systems.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">December 2006</hi>: With Institutional
                                    Planning and Provosts Office, completion of analysis of programming projections (supply
                                    and demand ratio of space needs); analysis needed to develop Grounds Plan carrying
                                    capacity options.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
                                    April 2007</hi>: Bicycle and pedestrian plans developed in coordination
                                    with City and County staff. </item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">June 2007</hi>: Draft UVa Transportation Management Plan
                                    developed with Parking &amp; Transportation.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">August 2007</hi>: Development of draft Grounds
                                    Plan report and appropriate constituent groups engaged in review process.</item><lb/>
                            </list></div3>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d13">
                        <head rend="left">4. Process Improvement</head>
                            <list>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">December 2006</hi>: Completion of prototype testing and analyses of revised and
                                    improved Value Management Program for all new building designs in concert with
                                    Facilities Management.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">February 2007</hi>: Completion of standardized cost estimating format
                                    for all new projects in concert with Facilities Management.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">March 2007</hi>: Approved
                                    surcharge system for funding infrastructure and grounds improvement projects.</item><lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">July 2007</hi>:
                                Completed draft design guidelines for the Health System.</item>
                            </list>
                    </div3>
                    <div3 type="statement" id="d14">
                        <head rend="left">5. Safety &amp; Security</head>
                            <list>
                                <item rend="indent"><hi rend="bold">
                                    July 2007</hi>: Security component incorporated into building and landscape guidelines for
                                    academic and Health System. </item><lb/>
                            </list>
                        </div3>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
