<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;

<!ENTITY % ISOnum  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent">  %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent">  %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> %UVAsupp;

<!ENTITY % xref 'INCLUDE'>
<!ATTLIST xref url CDATA #IMPLIED>
]>


<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of Visitors</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors meeting</title>
                <author n="110">
                    <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription and uva-dl-tei markup (TEI P4 with
                        local customizations)</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <biblScope type="date">
                    <date value="2005-09-24">September 24, 2005</date>
                </biblScope>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">20</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date value="2009">2009</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20050924</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Minutes of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">BOV minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">University of Virginia Board of Visitors
                            minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of
                            Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors
                            meeting</title>
                        <author n="110">
                            <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                            <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                        </author>
                        <biblScope type="date">
                            <date value="2005-09-24">September 24, 2005</date>
                        </biblScope>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Public minutes</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent n="300">?? pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <idno n="090" type="UVa call number">Accession# RG-1/1/</idno>
                        <idno type="UVa Title Control Number">a2846310</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note n="500">
                            <p n="500|a">The official minutes contain salary information. Access to
                                minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the
                                procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of
                                Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary
                                of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these
                                records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the
                                Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public
                                minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no
                                restrictions.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="524">
                            <p n="524|a">Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special
                                Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="520">
                            <p n="520|a">Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body
                                which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded
                                in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions
                                concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities,
                                gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and
                                resolutions.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc> &projectDesc; <editorialDecl> &editorial_correction;
                &editorial_normalization; &editorial_hyphenation; &editorial_quotation;
                &editorial_stdVals; </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="AAT">
                    <bibl>Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language n="008" id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <term n="610">University of Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="AAT">
                    <term n="655">Minutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="uva-form">
                    <term>serial volume</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2011-06-10">June 10, 2011</date>
<respStmt>
<name id="lsc6v">Lorrie Chisholm, University of Virginia Library</name>
<resp>corrector</resp>
</respStmt>
<item>Minor corrections to student markup.</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">
            <div1 type="contents" id="d3">
                <head type="main"> RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED BY THE BOARD OF VISITORS </head>
                <head type="sub">SEPTEMBER 24, 2005 </head>
                <p>
                    <table cols="2" rows="3">
                        <row>
                            <cell/>
                            <cell role="label">PAGE</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Approval of the Six-Year Institutional Plan Pursuant<lb/> to the
                                Restructured Higher Education Financial and Administrative <lb/>
                                Operations Act </cell>
                            <cell>7032 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Approval of the Management Agreement Pursuant to <lb/> Subchapter
                                3 of the Restructured Higher Education<lb/> Financial and
                                Administrative Operations Act </cell>
                            <cell>7033 </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
               
            </div1>
            <div1 type="roll-call" id="d4">
                <pb n="7030"/>
                <head type="main">TENTATIVE MINUTES<lb/> SUBJECT TO THE <lb/> APPROVAL OF THE <lb/> BOARD OF
                    VISITORS </head>
                <head type="sub">
                    <date value="2005-09-24">September 24, 2005</date>
                </head>
              <p> The Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia met, in Open
                    Session, at 12:00 noon, Saturday, <date value="2005-09-24">September 24,
                    2005</date>, in the President’s Conference Room at Madison Hall; <name>Thomas F.
                        Farrell, II, Rector presided. Alan A. Diamonstein, Ms. Susan Y. Dorsey, Ms.
                        Georgia Willis Fauber, G. Slaughter Fitz-Hugh, Jr., Ms. Glynn D. Key,
                        Vincent J. Mastracco, Jr., Lewis F. Payne, Gordon F. Rainey, Jr., Warren M.
                        Thompson, and Ms. Catherine S. Neale </name> were present. </p>
              <p><name>Don R. Pippin</name> participated by telephone. </p>
              <p>Present as well were <name>John T. Casteen, III, Leonard W.
                        Sandridge, Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr., Paul J. Forch, Gene D. Block, R.
                        Edward Howell, Ms. Colette Sheehy, and Ms. Jeanne Flippo Bailes</name>. </p>
              <p>The Rector asked <name>Mr. Sandridge</name>, Executive Vice
                    President and Chief Operating Officer, to present the Agenda. <name>Mr.
                        Sandridge </name> reminded the Board of the task at hand: a discussion of
                  the Six- Year Plans that must be submitted to the State by October 1<hi rend="super">st</hi>. He asked
                        <name>Ms. Sheehy</name>, Vice President for Management and Budget, to
                    describe the two plans, one for the Academic Division and the Medical Center
                    combined, and the other for The University of Virginia’s College at Wise. Both
                    plans are divided into four parts: narrative; response to goals set by the
                    state; revenue and spending plan; and enrollment plan. </p>
              <p>In response to the State’s goals, the Plan for the Academic
                    Division would fully implement AccessUVa, continue the newly instituted College
                    Guide Program to provide advising to high school students and increase
                    enrollment by 1500 students over ten years. The University will agree, among
                    other responses to the State’s goals, to introduce and “expand availability of
                    new degree programs in high need areas,” to maintain a “continuous assessment”
                    of academic programs, to maintain our high graduation rate, to expand the Arts
                    &amp; Sciences advising fellows program, and to implement articulation
                    agreements with all 23 community 
                  <pb n="7031"/> 
                  colleges. As for research goals,
                    the University would construct new facilities, hire “national academy” caliber
                    faculty, and work to attain research expenditures of $307million by 2012.</p>
              <p><name>Ms. Sheehy</name> next outlined several proposed revenue and
                    spending plans. </p>
              <p>As for the Medical Center, its strategic direction reflects the
                    goals of the Medical Center Operating Board, agreed upon this past summer. It
                    aims to continue to deliver superior medical care, while operating
                    competitively, and to meet the needs of both the aging and growing population in
                    the region. Its growth, however, is dependent on increasing the number of
                    patient beds. The Medical Center’s projected operating margin is 5% over this
                    six year period. </p>
              <p>Responding both to the State’s goals and to the needs of Southwest
                    Virginia, The University of Virginia’s College at Wise wants, among other
                    things, to increase access and affordability, broaden its range of academic
                    offerings, establish an Office of Economic Development and improve student
                    retention. <name>Ms. Sheehy</name> noted that on July 19<hi rend="super">th</hi>, the State Council approved Wise
                    enrollment targets – previously approved by the Board – to add 215 students over
                    seven years. </p>
                <p><name>Mr. Sandridge</name> pointed out that the Management Agreements, required
                    by the legislation approved by the General Assembly at the last Session, are
                    still under negotiation with Richmond. According to the established schedule,
                    the Governor will have approved the management agreements in time to include
                    them with his budget recommendations to the General Assembly in December. If the
                    General Assembly approves them in the next Session, they will go into effect on
                    <date value="2006-07-01">July 1, 2006</date>. </p>
              <p>After discussion of the details of the proposed Six Year Plans, the
                    Board adopted the following resolution approving them: </p>
               
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d5">
                <pb n="7032"/>
                <head type="main">APPROVAL OF THE SIX-YEAR INSTITUTIONAL PLAN PURSUANT TO THE RESTRUCTURED
                    HIGHER EDUCATION FINANCIAL AND ADMINISTRATIVE OPERATIONS ACT </head>
             
                    <p>WHEREAS, the 2005 General Assembly passed HB 2866 and SB 1327 known as the
                        Restructured Higher Education Financial and Administrative Operations Act,
                        as amended by the Governor; and </p>
                   
                    <p>WHEREAS, on <date value="2005-06-11">June 11, 2005</date>, the Board of
                        Visitors of the University of Virginia passed a resolution committing to the
                        Governor and to the General Assembly that it will meet the goals as set
                        forth in the Act, in addition to such other responsibilities as prescribed
                        by law as they pertain to the University of Virginia, the Medical Center,
                        and the College at Wise; and </p>
                   
                    <p>WHEREAS, § 23-9.2:3.02 of the Act requires governing boards of the public
                        institutions of higher education to develop and adopt biennially a six-year
                        plan and submit that plan to the State Council, the Governor, and the
                        respective chairs of the House Committee on Appropriations and the Senate
                        Committee on Finance no later than October 1st of each odd-numbered year; </p>
                  
                    <p>RESOLVED, the Board of Visitors approves the six-year plans of the
                        University’s Academic Division, the Medical Center, and the College at Wise;
                        and </p>
                  
                    <p>RESOLVED FURTHER, the President is authorized to transmit the six-year
                        plans to the State Council, the Governor, and the respective chairs of the
                        House Committee on Appropriations and the Senate Committee on Finance. </p>
                   
                    <ornament type="characters">- - - - - - - - - - </ornament>
                    
                    <p>There was further discussion of the proposed Management Agreement, and the
                        Board adopted the following resolution approving the Agreement so far, and
                        authorizing the administration of the University to continue negotiations
                        and to finalize the Agreement before November 15<hi rend="super">th</hi>: </p>
                
               
            </div1>
            <div1 type="resolution" id="d6">
                <pb n="7033"/>
                <head type="main">APPROVAL OF THE MANAGEMENT AGREEMENT PURSUANT TO SUBCHAPTER 3 OF THE
                    RESTRUCTURED HIGHER EDUCATION FINANCIAL AND ADMINISTRATIVE OPERATIONS ACT </head>
             
                    <p> WHEREAS, the Restructured Higher Education Financial and Administrative
                        Operations Act includes a provision titled Subchapter 3, Alternative
                        Authority for Covered Institutions (23-38.91 <hi rend="italic">et seq</hi>.), which sets out the
                        requirements for a public university or college of the Commonwealth to gain
                        the greatest degree of authority over financial and administrative
                        operations, subject to certain accountability, audit and reporting measures
                        specified by the General Assembly of Virginia; </p>
                   
                    <p>WHEREAS, on <date value="2005-06-11">June 11, 2005</date> the Board of
                        Visitors passed a resolution stating that the University is qualified to be,
                        and should be, governed by the authorizations and requirements set forth in
                        Subchapter 3 and as may otherwise be prescribed by applicable law; and</p>
                   
                    <p>WHEREAS, in that same resolution the Board of Visitors of the University
                        attests to the ability of the institution to manage successfully its
                        administrative and financial operations without jeopardizing its financial
                        integrity and stability; and accordingly authorized the University President
                        and the Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer to enter into
                        negotiations with the Governor to develop a management agreement with the
                        Commonwealth as provided for in the Act that will grant the greatest degree
                        of financial and managerial autonomy to the University as provided in
                        Subchapter 3, </p>
                   
                    <p>RESOLVED, the Board of Visitors approves the management agreement
                        negotiated by the University for the benefit of the Academic Division, the
                        Medical Center, and the College at Wise; and </p>
                   
                    <p>RESOLVED FURTHER, the Board of Visitors authorizes the President and the
                        Executive Vice President and Chief Operating Officer, with the concurrence
                        of the Rector, to continue negotiations and to finalize the management
                        agreement prior to <date value="2005-11-15">November 15, 2005</date>. </p>
                  
                
                <ornament type="characters">- - - - - - - - - - </ornament>
               
                <pb n="7034"/>
              <p>On motion, the meeting was adjourned at 12:50 p.m. </p>
                <signed>Respectfully submitted, <lb/>Alexander G. Gilliam, Jr.<lb/>Secretary, Board
                    Visitors,<lb/>University of Virginia</signed>
                <trailer>AGG:lah These minutes have been posted to the University of Virginia’s
                    Board of Visitors website. <xref
                        url="http://www.virginia.edu/bov/publicminutes.html"
                        >http://www.virginia.edu/bov/publicminutes.html</xref>
                </trailer>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
