<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">

<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> 
%dlps-teiHeader;

<!ENTITY % ISOnum  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent">  %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub  SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent">  %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % UVAsupp SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/uva-supp.ent"> 
%UVAsupp;
]>


<TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of Visitors</title>
                <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors meeting</title>
                <author n="110">
                    <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                    <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                </author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of electronic transcription and uva-dl-tei markup (TEI P4 with
                        local customizations)</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                <biblScope type="date">
                    <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                </biblScope>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">24</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <date value="2009">2009</date>
                <availability status="public">
                    <p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2008 by the Rector and Visitors of the
                        University of Virginia</p>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                </availability>
                <idno type="DLPS ID">bov_20060728_saac</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
            </seriesStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title n="245|a" type="main">Board of Visitors minutes</title>
                        <title type="sort">board of visitors minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Minutes of the Board of Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">BOV minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">University of Virginia Board of Visitors
                            minutes</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of meeting of the Board of
                            Visitors</title>
                        <title n="246" type="alternate">Public minutes of the Board of Visitors
                            meeting</title>
                        <author n="110">
                            <name n="110|a" type="corporate">University of Virginia</name>
                            <name n="110|b" type="sub-unit">Board of Visitors</name>
                        </author>
                        <biblScope type="date">
                            <date value="2006-07-28">July 28, 2006</date>
                        </biblScope>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Public minutes</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent n="300">?? pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <idno n="090" type="UVa call number">Accession# RG-1/1/</idno>
                        <idno type="UVa Title Control Number">a2846310</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note n="500">
                            <p n="500|a">The official minutes contain salary information. Access to
                                minutes containing salary information will be granted only under the
                                procedures of the Virginia Freedom of Information Act (Code of
                                Virginia-2.1-340 ff.) or if permission is granted by the Secretary
                                of the Board. Researchers interested in obtaining access to these
                                records should direct a request in writing to the Office of the
                                Legal Adviser, Madison Hall, University of Virginia. These public
                                minutes have had salary information deleted and bear no
                                restrictions.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="524">
                            <p n="524|a">Board of Visitors' minutes, Accession # RG-1/1/, Special
                                Collections Dept., University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                        </note>
                        <note n="520">
                            <p n="520|a">Minutes of meetings of the university's governing body
                                which is the legal owner and operator of the institution. Recorded
                                in the minutes are appointments and other personnel decisions
                                concerning faculty, decisions about construction of facilities,
                                gifts to the university, and all other board actions, decisions and
                                resolutions.</p>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc> &projectDesc; <editorialDecl> &editorial_correction;
                &editorial_normalization; &editorial_hyphenation; &editorial_quotation;
                &editorial_stdVals; </editorialDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy id="LCSH">
                    <bibl>Library of Congress Subject Headings</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="AAT">
                    <bibl>Art &amp; Architecture Thesaurus</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy id="uva-form">
                    <bibl>UVa Library Form Categories</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language n="008" id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="LCSH">
                    <term n="610">University of Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="AAT">
                    <term n="655">Minutes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="uva-form">
                    <term>serial volume</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body id="d1">
            <div1 type="report" id="d2">
                <pb n="1"/>
                <head>STUDENT AFFAIRS AND ATHLETICS COMMITTEE<lb/> 2006-2007 GOALS</head>
               
                    <p> 1. Sustain the core value of self-governance in the context
                        of continued growth and the changing student needs </p>
                        <p> The success of a community depends on its members
                            commitment to personal responsibility and accountability.
                            Self-governance entails collaborating with students to support their
                            ownership in the creation, modification and implementation of policies
                            and practices that define the community in which they live, while
                            ensuring that basic institutional responsibilities of safety, legality
                            and fiscal soundness are not compromised. Student Affairs strives to
                            maintain a balance between letting students take risks and learn from
                            their success and failures, and direct involvement on issues that demand
                            institutional oversight. The Universitys Judiciary and Honor Committees,
                            Residence Life program and Student Council exemplify self- governance at
                            UVa. Student Affairs works closely with students -- individually and
                            collectively -- to manage opportunities and challenges which surface
                            from this model, as well as with parents who can both support and
                            question this approach. This model should enrich students during their
                            tenure at the University, and upon graduation help instill a sense of
                            community membership, personal responsibility and civic engagement that
                            will assist them in their lives as educated citizens and leaders. </p>
                        <p> The Universitys projected enrollment growth, coupled with
                            changing needs and demands of students, are factors that need to be
                            addressed proactively in order to uphold this core value. Discussions
                            this year will focus on securing and maintaining the resources needed to
                            support this model, on strategies to work effectively with parents in
                            supporting the Universitys approach in this regard, and on developing
                            the appropriate metrics to measure the impact of self-governance and
                            involvement beyond a students time at the University. </p>

                    <p> 2. Strengthen residential programs for first years and
                        upper class students, particularly transfers. </p>
                        <p> For the past two years, Student Affairs has been working
                            with the Provost and the Vice President for Finance to define how the
                            University supports the student experience through residence life.
                            Elements being addressed in this planning process include: determining
                            current and future demands for housing; defining the goals of specific
                            residential life experiences (e.g., first-year housing, residential
                            colleges, language houses); and affirming program objectives by student
                            populations (i.e., first-year, transfer, and other upper class
                            students). In April 2005 the Board confirmed its support for the
                            first-year residential program and preliminary plans to move forward
                            with changes to the Alderman Residences. We will continue to discuss how
                            we support the academic experience of first years through residence
                            life, as well as our residential program objectives for upper class
                            students. In particular, we will work on establishing a new arts
                            residential college and a new residential program specifically for
                            transfer students. </p>

                <p>Student Affairs and Athletics</p>
                <pb n="2"/>
                
                    <p> 3. Promote student involvement through appropriate
                        strategies, programs and allocations of resources </p>
                        <p> Student Affairs works to promote an environment in which
                            students feel safe, welcomed and supported so that they may fully
                            realize their academic pursuits and other opportunities that define the
                            student experience. Outreach and dissemination of information about
                            services, resources and opportunities are critical to ensure that
                            students know about the support thats available to them, and to engage
                            them in community life. Student Affairs strives to provide physical
                            spaces and programs that establish meaningful connections between
                            academics and life outside the classroom; that promote interactions
                            between students and faculty, or between individuals and groups that
                            might not otherwise collaborate; that foster a sense of community and
                            involvement in University life; and that purposefully immerse students
                            in experiences that expose them to different perspectives and provide
                            them with an opportunity to learn. </p>
                        <p> Student Affairs will be updating the Board on several
                            initiatives this year including the implementation of a first-year
                            multicultural and diversity education program that incorporates
                            structured workshops, efforts to promote general safety and security on
                            Grounds (e.g., physical safety, on-line safety); and strategies to
                            complement efforts in the College of Arts and Sciences to improve
                            undergraduate advising. </p>
            
                <div2 type="section" id="d3">
                    <head>Student Affairs Work Plan:</head>
                    <p>Sustain the core value of self-governance in the context of continued growth
                        and the changing student needs. </p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"> September 2006: Student Council presents its goals for
                            the year. Vice President provides overview of critical student life
                            issues. </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> September 2006-April 2007: develop data collection and
                            tracking mechanism for student involvement at UVA to serve as baseline
                            for future analysis of level and effects of student engagement. </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> October 2006: Analysis of Honor faculty complete;
                            planning underway to incorporate results into future effort. </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> September 2006-May 2007: collect data on parent
                            interactions. </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> February 2007: Honor and UJC present their major
                            initiatives. </item>
                        <lb/>
                    </list>
                    <p>Strengthen residential programs for first-years and upper class students,
                        particularly transfers. </p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"> August December 2006: Finalize assessment of student
                            and resident staff experiences, and develop plan to address any
                            challenges in the program.</item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> November 2006: Residential plan for transfer students
                            complete for implementation in 2007-08. </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> August 2006 February 2007: Assessment of residential
                            college model complete </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> April 2007: Present major initiatives related to
                            residence life. </item>
                        <lb/>
                    </list>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <p rend="left">Student Affairs and Athletics</p>
                    <pb n="3"/>
                    <p>Promote student involvement through appropriate strategies, programs and
                        allocations of resources </p>
                    <list>
                        <item rend="indent"> August December 2006: Complete analysis and outline
                            proposed changes appropriate to major orientation initiatives for new
                            students (e.g., summer orientation). Goal would be to implement changes
                            by summer 2007. </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> August 2006-May 2007: Track and analyze data collected
                            and response to incidents reported via on-line incident reporting
                            system. </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> February 2007: Update on key safety initiatives </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> April 2007: Update on Diversity residential program for
                            firstyears (during spring to cover changes intended for spring 07
                            changes) </item>
                        <lb/>
                        <item rend="indent"> May 2007: Outline initiatives between Student Affairs
                            and the college of Arts and Sciences aimed at strengthening advising
                            (e.g., University Career Services, Residence Life) </item>
                        <lb/>
                    </list>
                </div2>
                <div2 type="section" id="d4">
                    <head>Athletics Goals and Work Plan:</head>
                  
                        <p> 1. Create a system of measurement and enhance the
                            academic success rates for student- athletes.</p>
                            <list>
                                <item rend="indent"> Complete the search for the Assistant Director
                                    for Football Academic Support and create a support structure for
                                    incoming and continuing football student-athletes that will
                                    allow for assessment of academic strengths and weaknesses. Based
                                    on each assessment, a specific academic success plan will be
                                    developed, implemented and monitored on an ongoing basis. The
                                    Department has developed the proper personnel infrastructure
                                    over the last 18 months to support this effort. </item>
                                <lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"> The Academic Affairs unit will develop a
                                    semester by semester summary report that will provide
                                    information relative to individual and team academic progress
                                    (successes and failures). </item>
                                <lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"> The Department will conduct a search, in
                                    conjunction with the Registrar's office, to add a dedicated
                                    position in which monitoring and certifying continuing
                                    eligibility of all student- athletes would take place. </item>
                              </list>
                      
                        <p>2. Establish a nationally competitive athletics
                            programs.</p>
                            <list>
                                <item rend="indent"> Win multiple national championships and
                                    continue to climb the ladder in the Director's Cup standings. </item>
                                <lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"> Place as many teams in NCAA championship
                                    competition as possible and have those teams advance in their
                                    championships' respective brackets. </item>
                                <lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"> Recruit the best possible student-athletes in
                                    support of championship efforts. </item>
                                <lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"> With each coaching vacancy, hire a high
                                    performing coach that will thrive in an environment with an
                                    expectation of winning national championships within a highly
                                    competitive academic environment. </item>
                         </list>

                    <p>Student Affairs and Athletics </p>
                    <pb n="4"/>
                        <list>
                                <item rend="indent"> Continue to hold head coaches accountable for
                                    the sustained success in the academic and athletic performances
                                    of their teams. </item>
                      </list>
                        <p> 3. Eliminate the structural deficiency in the
                            Department of Athletics' operating budget. </p>
                            <list>
                                <item rend="indent"> The Senior Staff in Athletics will analyze
                                    carefully the unit-by-unit trends in allocations and
                                    expenditures to determine the cause of the structural
                                    deficiency. </item>
                                <lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"> The Senior Staff will assess the efficiencies
                                    (cost benefit analysis) in the use of current resources. </item>
                                <lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"> The Senior Staff will pursue options for
                                    maximizing or generating new revenue streams. </item>
                                <lb/>
                                <item rend="indent"> All unit supervisors will operate with
                                    operating budgets held constant in fiscal 2006-07 </item>
                                <lb/>
                            </list>
                    <p rend="left">Student Affairs and Athletics</p>
                </div2>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
