<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0137 SYSTEM "000001107_0137" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0138 SYSTEM "000001107_0138" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0139 SYSTEM "000001107_0139" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0140 SYSTEM "000001107_0140" NDATA uvaHighRes>

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19150718">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-07-18">July 18th 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19150718</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>4 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
        		<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0137"/>
        		<head>Jim to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-07-18">July 18th 1915</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline><date value="1915-07-18">July 18th 1915</date></dateline>
        		</opener>
        		
            <p>
            I have just received your letter of the
            15th telling me about Carb’s leaving and
            Rockwell’s saunter with you.  I envy them
            so much seeing you, but I do not envy Carb
            for he is leaving, and in leaving loses the 
            chance for continuing in the finest work it
            will ever be his fortune to see again.
            </p><p>
            I’ll bet your Frenchman just over from
            America is going to be a spy for the government.
            Isn’t that so?  That makes two now.  You ought 
            to have some good inside information about the 
            enemy.
            </p><p>
            The only good news I have is that Ambulance
            No. 1 is to be sent to the town below us
            and No 3, that is there, brought up.  The
            Medicine Chef complained it was too dangerous and 
            asked to be moved back.  Incidentally he waited
            until he got his Croix de Guerre before he asked
            for the move.  The darned old slobs.  I’m glad
            the change has been made.  Another advantage
            lies in the fact that No. 3 is new at the
            front and we can get them to hustle from
            the start as we’re older around here than
            they are.  I sent a letter in by Barclay who
            is leaving for America so I guess you have
            it by now.  It seems years since I’ve heard
            any news of Paul.  I’m anxious to hear what
            his plans are, for I am making application for
            a leave in September to go in and see
            you all and while I know you will be at
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0138" n="[p.2]"/>
            
            the same old post I’m not sure of Paul.
            My friend Betty Baldwin, I am sorry to hear,
            is going to leave for a two months’ trip
            to the States, and will be away when I
            get to Paris.  She’s a peach.  I wish you
            knew her.  Do you know Miss <unclear>Lines [sp?]</unclear> at the
            Ambulance?  She’s a friend of hers.
            </p><p>
            There is very little new up here.
            We are now mostly interested in what’s
            going on in other secteurs and on the 
            other fronts.  I am not at all alarmed 
            about the Russian retreat.  Belloc claims
            the capture of Warsaw would be a great
            blow, but from studying the railroad
            facilities that would be left I cannot
            see where the enemy would find himself
            in any better position, save that the city
            would allow quarters for a great number
            of troops.  So long as they keep their
            troops over there well and good.  It 
            will give us more time to accumulate
            ammunition, and keep the Germans from
            making another drive.  By Christmas the
            Dardanelles will be opened.  By spring
            Russia’s new armies will be trained, supplied,
            and equipped with a compliment [sic] of artillery
            and weakened Germany can be crushed into
            a heap from which she can never
            straighten out.  We French will be the ones
            that will administer the final touch, as is
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0139" n="[p.3]"/>
            
            fitting and proper, for France from the
            first to the last has fought the 
            whole war.  I’m glad to note that
            Americans are beginning to realize it.
            A letter I have just received is typical
            of those I have been getting of late.
            It goes on to say “We hear the British
            are holding but twenty five miles of front.
            Is that possible?  If so it is disgusting.
            The more I think about it the more I
            am convinced that the French are the
            wonderful, noble, people of this war.  They
            are so admirable; they do not prate about
            it, but even give most of the credit
            to others.”  When you consider that the war
            has been going double shift now for about
            a year, lacking but a few days now, it
            is surprising that people in America are
            just waking up to the truth..  They’re a
            soulless bunch those Yankees anyway.
            Well I believe America will play a good
            part in the long run.  Up until two months
            ago she was supplying on one twentieth of
            one percent of the ammunition used by the
            Allies.  Now she is increasing a hundred percent 
            on geometrical progression every month.  ['We' lined through] They are
            taking ['our' lined through] their ordinance officers and putting them
            in charge of ['our' lined through] their ammunition usines.
            Ah that will be a sweet time when
            we have great quantities of shells to fire
                        
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0140" n="[p.4]"/>
            
            with out ceasing.  To hear the continuous
            sharp departs and the roll of dull
            roars as they boom off in the Boches
            trenches.  As a crapoulland [sic] gunner said to
            me once “I tell you, you would laugh to
            see it.  I shoot my torpille .  She goes
            turning slowly over and over through the air
            and then drops right in the trench.  Oh
            you see em [sic] go up.  Legs and arms and
            heads.  Rifles, helmets and sacks.  All go 
            up at once. Once I saw a whole Boche
            go up.  Perfectly good Boche.  Only one leg
            missing.  He went up.  Way up thirty meters."
            Yes, and I would laugh, damn em [sic],
            and the more mangled they are the
            better I’d like it. I would take keen
            delight in a string of German ears.  They
            cut the throats of some of our comrades
            the other day and stuck their heads
            up over the trench on bayonets.  Les salauds.
            </p>
        		
        		<closer>
            <salute>Well, good night and keep well, and
            don’t flirt.</salute>
            
            <signed>Jim</signed>
            
            <seg type="postscript">
            You can leave off “Conducteur” on the address.
            It takes up room and serves no purpose,
            for there’s only one man with my name
            in Secteur Postal 84 and American Section.
            </seg>
        			</closer>
            
            <!-- [With this letter is an envelope addressed to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin, 148 bis Rue de Longchamps, Paris.]
            
            File: McConnell/Jul18'15 -->
            
            <!-- Image file for envelope mentioned is missing from image set 000001107 - MSS -->
            
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>