<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0095 SYSTEM "000001107_0095" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0096 SYSTEM "000001107_0096" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0097 SYSTEM "000001107_0097" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0098 SYSTEM "000001107_0098" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0099 SYSTEM "000001107_0099" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0100 SYSTEM "000001107_0100" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0101 SYSTEM "000001107_0101" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0102 SYSTEM "000001107_0102" NDATA uvaHighRes>

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19150607">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-06-07">June 7th 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19150607</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>6 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
        		<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0095"/>
        		<head>Jim to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-06-07">June 7th 1915</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline><date value="1915-06-07">June 7th 1915</date></dateline>
        		</opener>
        		
            <p>
            I have just received your letter
            inclosing [sic] the clipping, ^ re Pont a Mousson and many
            thanks.  I have too heard from Paul
            and he has given me the new of Kiffin.
            My friend Thierry-Delauoue who used to
            get letters from the Vicomte du Peloux
            with news for me of Rockwell, got
            his in a recent bombardment and
            it fell to me to evacuate him.
            </p><p>
            So old Russia has returned to the
            attack has he?  I should think you
            ought to be able to get him to go to
            war and then he might get killed and
            your troubles would be over.  He’s certainly
            a persistent individual.
            </p><p>
            I got into Nancy yesterday for the first
            time I’ve been at the front.  I had a whole
            hour and as I was with an officer who
            insisted on taking me around in a sea going <unclear>[???]</unclear>
            hack and pointing out the sights I had a
            very good tour of the place.  It was a 
            glorious day and I enjoyed it all immensely.
            The Place d’Alliance is a perfect little
            gem.  The gardens, where we sat down to
            have a drink&mdash; I would have you know that
            for a month now I have touched but lemonade
            and other soft thirst killers&mdash;were beautiful.
            It was Sunday and everyone was out
            strolling around.  True there was something
            strange about the scene; the noticeable
            absence of men from twenty to forty, but
            but [sic] never for a moment could one realize
            that the greatest war in history was being
            fought twenty eight kilometers distant.  Returning
            to our quarters was very interesting following 
            the peace and quiet of Nancy.  I took an
            artillery captain back with me and as it
            was his first time at our part of the
            front the details of approach to the line
            were called to new attention by his questions.
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0096" n="[p.2]"/>
            
            and comments.  At five fifteen we left  the 
            beautiful city in the quiet of its Sunday
            rest and at six we were in front of
            artillery that was in action.  After we
            had followed the road for a few kilometers
            the captain called attention to an observation
            balloon, sharply outlined against the deep blue
            sky.  Then we went thru [sic] villages where
            great crowds of soldiers were gathered.  As
            we passed others one could notice the
            difference in the appearance of the men.  Those
            in the towns farther back were cleaner and
            looked fresh; as we went on one could
            notice boots and coats still covered with 
            the dirt of the trenches and then
            we arrived at a town where the fronts
            of some buildings were torn by eclats.
            We rolled on and suddenly came to a 
            stretch of road on which the Germans can
            look and frequently shell.  The captain covered
            his gold galons with a map he was
            looking at.  We then entered a town where
            I began to meet friends.  They greeted us
            and some wanted a ride.  Then we came to
            our town and its wrecks of buildings.  We 
            turned out towards the trenches; past
            cantonments where great numbers of soldiers
            I knew where resting.  They would wave, and
            in the most advanced one a man ran up,
            stopped me, and gave me a ring he’d been
            making for me out of a piece of shell.  “Why
            you know everyone here don’t you?” said the
            officer.  We had been hearing distant firing
            but now it became clear and sharp and
            we looked for wires that having been
            cut by shells might be too low to pass
            under.  Up we went.  There were no soldiers 
            to be seen now and ahead we heard 
            heavy firing.  We rounded a bend and came
            upon a battery firing across the road just in
                       
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0097" n="[p.3]"/>
            
            front of us.  Of course we could go no further
            of course and so our dapper little captain
            with the usual profuse thanks dismounted 
            and disappeared in the woods behind to
            circle the artillery.  I couldn’t quite get it
            thru [sic] my head that only three quarters of
            an hour before we had slipped out of a
            peaceful city.  The changes are rapid.  Even
            with the people.  The officer chap was quite
            stiff and formal when we started from 
            Nancy and he reminded me strongly of your
            Paris fighting men.  As we neared the front
            he began to get more chummy and when he
            got out of the car in front of the guns
            he was calling me “mon vieux” and wishing
            “Bonne chance” and various other friendly farewells.
            </p><p>
            This letter has been written in sections.
            Every time I get started along comes a 
            call and I have to up and away, and its
            an hour or more before I can get back to
            finish it up.
            </p><p>
            By the way Miss <unclear>Fuller [sp?]</unclear> is not coming
            over.  She lost her nerve, or at least
            gives it as an excuse, that the liners
            are being sunk, and she’s loath to die
            or take a chance on it at the present.
            </p><p>
            I had a man in my car just now
            that had come within the zone of effect of
            an asphyxiating, or however you spell it, shell.  he
            suffered in his breathing and &mdash;Next day
            </p><p>
            At this moment one of the doctors came up to
            ask me where he could get ahold [sic] of Salisbury.
            I was stationed for the day on call at Ambulance
            ['m' lined through] 1 and was writing this letter in the court-
            yard.  The doctor had just sat down next to me
            when we heard the tearing roar of a great
            shell overhead.  It hit a house a hundred
            yards from us with a deafening explosion.  We
            bent down to avoid the eclats.  I asked the
            doctor what message I could carry to Salisbury.
            Instead of replying he got up and said “Come in 
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0098" n="[p.4]"/>
            
            with me.”  We entered the long corridor.  A few seconds,
            not more than three I estimate, afterwards, I 
            saw a small group of brancardiers, in the
            next entrance to the corridor from us, crouch
            swiftly down.  They had heard the whistle.  Immediately
            the air became crushing.  I was bent over.  There
            was an overpowering detonation and it became
            dark.  Glass, wood and plaster pelted and fell on
            me.  I remember wondering what was coming down
            next and then I heard terrible shrieks above
            the din of falling debris.  I tried to look down
            the corridor thru [sic] the dense smoke and saw
            a man waving his arms and yelling crazily
            totter towards me.  He grabbed my shoulder and
            moaned.  You have heard a child cry after some
            shock.  It was like that but this was a man
            and it made it seem worse.  The clouds of smoke
            and dust cleared and twenty yards from me I
            saw one of the brancardiers on the floor.  A
            stream of red blood was feeling its way thru [sic]
            the coating of dust on the floor.  An eclat had 
            passed through his chest.  He had been killed 
            instantly.  Others were wounded.  I went
            out and saw the great hole where the
            “marmite” had struck twenty five yards
            from where I was standing.  The eclats had wrecked
            the front of the building.  If it had been 
            ten feet nearer it would have hit the 
            corridor  wall and bagged the whole bunch of 
            us.  I heard another coming and fell flat
            on my face as we do to avoid them.  It
            passed over.  The men began hurrying towards
            the cave.  I had never yet taken to any but
            when I saw an officer with the Medaille Militaire
            scurry down I figured it would be all right
            and joined the basement crowd.  First I went
            back to get this letter that I had placed on
            a chair in the corridor when I entered and
            found it all covered with glass and stones
            and plaster.  I’ve cleaned it up as well as
            I can.  The rough edges come from cramming it
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0099" n="[p.5]"/>
            
            in my pocket.  I’m sorry.  Shells began coming
            over at regular intervals.  When it was time
            to go back to the caserne  I waited until a 
            shell went off and then made a dash for it.
            Got to the main street and was tangled up
            in broken telephone lines.  I got them off
            and hit it up across the Place.  Two of our
            fellows who were looking out from a sand
            bag shelter there said I just got away
            in time to miss two.  After supper we
            went down to see the shells that were
            being aimed at the bridge.  They came from
            such a long distance that one couldn’t hear the
            guns.  We could hear them go overhead.  See
            a couple of columns of water hurtle a hundred
            feet into the air and then the twin crashes.
            The shells came in pairs.  Then we’d run for
            a wall in order to dodge the eclats.  After
            that there would be a scramble for them.
            </p><p>
            There were a great many killed yesterday and
            several wounded.  60 casualties in all.
            </p><p>
            We evacuated all the hospitals in Pont a Mousson
            last night and it was eleven before we finished.
            It was pretty working then for we could see
            a part of the town burning from the bombard-
            ment and shrapnel bursting over to keep people
            from putting it out.  I stayed on call at
            the caserne and read your sweet letter of
            May 27th that came only last night.  I had only
            a lantern for the bombardment broke our gas
            system as it had  the electric before.  Do
            you really mean to tell me you would
            care especially if I were killed and that
            it would relieve you in anyway to get
            news of me frequently?  I wish I could believe
            it.  I naturally do not care especially about
            getting killed but if I do I hope its up 
            on service at the postes back of the trenches
            and not in town during bombardments.  I
            dislike the idea.  Up at Clos Blois 
            Montanville  where we’re under fire its quite
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0100" n="[p.6]"/>
            
            interesting and enjoyable.  Its part of the
            game and in the fight.  I’m going up
            there now in an hour for an attack is
            in progress, and the wounded will be coming
            down from the trenches then.  Shells are 
            singing overhead and explosions are
            shaking my room but that doesn’t bother
            us for its only our artillery shooting and
            the Germans shooting back at the
            batteries.  Its a fearful din tho.  [sic]
            </p><p>
            I got a nice call down yesterday but I
            was mad and didn’t give a rap about rules.
            A few of the fat, good for nothing doctors
            at Amb 1 asked me to take them to 
            Montanville to see Poincaire who had come
            up.  That was all right but after they had
            finished their visit instead of going back
            they went into a popote and proceeded to
            tank up.  I had to wait.  In an hour
            they came out singing Tipperary and
            feeling fine.  I thought it would be fun
            to scare them and ran them down the
            outside road on which the Germans
            can look and over which they fire shrapnel.
            They discovered where they were too late
            to take another road, and the singing
            ceased.  Just my luck.  The Boches didn’t
            pay any attention to the load of officers
            even tho [sic] they did to one that Lovell
            was running towards Dieulouard  the
            other day and banged a shell over at
            them.  I got a call by the Docs
            all right but when the Medicine Divisionaire
            found out about the joy ride, they
            came in for theirs all right.  One of
            the fat ones was wounded slightly next
            to me in the bombardment that followed.
            </p><p>
            I’m sending this letter into Paris by a
            refugee to be mailed to you from there.
            </p>
        		
        		<closer>
            <salute>Affectionately</salute>
            
            <signed>Jim.</signed>
        		</closer>
        		
            
            <!-- [The envelope with this letter is addressed to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin, 38 Rue Pauquet, Paris.  '28 Rue Pauquet is lined through and '148 bis Rue de Longchamp' added.]
            
            File: McConnell/June7'15 -->
        		
        		<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0101"/>
        		<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0102"/>
            
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>