<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19170423"><!-- CHECK DATE OF THIS LETTER IN IMAGE FILE.  DATE IN LETTER DOES NOT CORRESPOND W/ THE FILENAME APR2315.txt. -->
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to  Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1917-04-23">April 23rd 1917</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19170423</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>8 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
        		<head>Jim to  Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1917-04-23">April 23rd 1917</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline><date value="1917-04-23">April 23rd 1917</date></dateline>
        		</opener>
        		
            <p>
            I’m very well pleased with our new post.  Its a most delightful town where we have our base, and we’re 
            welcomed with open arms.  I’m glad we’re in a place where we can do really useful work.  I had a job 
            yesterday that took me 44 kilometers into a place forte.  We’re under strict military rule here; have to give 
            the pass word and all of the frills.  The Germans take a chance at our town now and then.  Night before 
            last they turned loose a few <unclear>obus [?]</unclear> trying to reach the station.  Two little children playing in the street were 
            killed.  We went down to see the damage.  A large crowd of soldiers gathered around 
            
            <pb n="[p.2]"/>
            
            but no one seemed to be disturbed by the fact that we were in the direct line of a battery that had fired a few 
            minutes before.  Late that evening I went to the spot again and picked up part of the shell.  Up above I could 
            hear the breast deep sobs of  the young mother crying over the poor little mangled bodies of her only 
            children.  It was very pitiful.  Yesterday morning light shells came in.  A woman was killed in her bed about 
            400 yards from us.  The peculiar part about a bombardment to me is that one can hear the firing
            
            <pb n="[p.3]"/>
            
            of the cannons long before the shell arrives.  There is a faint “boom” away off; then a “zipp - zipp, zipp, 
            zipp”, as one tearing parchment, and suddenly an ear - splitting crash.  After a few of them one doesn’t 
            mind the racket or pay any attention to the shells.  Guns are firing all the time but its the cause of no more 
            excitement than an automobile in Paris.
            </p><p>
            I’m writing this letter from our advance point where we work in shifts of thirty six hours.  We’re in a 
            town that is under practically continuous bombardment
            
            <pb n="[p.4]"/>
            
            but things are going on all the same.  There are good shops, and tho [sic] holes are thru [sic] most of them, 
            business is flourishing.  To get here from our base we pass for a kilometer along a road that is under 
            bombardment.  Its quite thrilling.  One car hits it up across the shell marked area.  When the dust has settled 
            the next car turns on full speed and whizzes along the entertaining stretch.  We get our wounded about 200 
            yds from the trenches.  The enemy’s trenches are but fourteen hundred yards from our town and they could 
            <unclear>pot [?]</unclear> us
            
            <pb n="[p.5]"/>
            
            with rifles if they wished to.  
            </p><p>
            At our base are some German prisoners and you should see the looks they give us, thinking us English.  
            Their uniform is wonderful.  It can hardly be seen, so well does it blend in with all surroundings.
            </p><p>
            To night I’m sleeping in our advance post and they tell me that we’re to have an unusually fierce 
            bombardment.  We have beds here tho [sic] just as at our base.  At the latter place one of our men and I 
            share a large bed in the home of two very nice old souls where we are billited [sic].  They are quite friendly 
            towards 
            
            <pb n="[p.6]"/>
            
            me and can’t do too much for us.  When I left this morning they expressed all sorts of hopes that I’d get 
            back.
            </p><p>
            This morning at our advance place a fellow came into see us who looked as if he’d just stepped off 
            Broadway.  He wore an American fedora; tan shoes, an English rain coat and his trousers that were turned 
            up were perfectly pressed.  I couldn’t understand what the man was doing out here at the front.  He 
            explained to us that he had left New York a year and a half ago to do engineering work at a large factory 
            
            <pb n="[p.7]"/>
            
            near us.  He was going home for a vacation when the war broke out.  Then he decided to stick to his post 
            and so here he is just as American as ever.  He was overjoyed to see us, and told us all about the time the 
            Germans were here and many other interesting experiences.  He’s coming around to night to see us again.
            </p><p>
            All the French officers I’ve met are perfect “corkers”.  They’re the nicest men I’ve ever met.  About half 
            speak English very well.  So do about an eighth of the soldiers.  Its remarkable.
            
            <pb n="[p.8]"/>
            
            I’ve all sorts of interesting things to tell you when I see you again that I can’t write about.  I hope I shall 
            hear from you soon.
            </p><p>
            How’s old Rockwell getting along?  I’m afraid I can’t get in to his wedding for we’re not allowed to 
            leave here.  Even our supply cars have to stop at a point very much in the rear of our place.
            </p>
        		
        		<closer>
            <signed>Jim.</signed>
        		</closer>
        		
            
            <!-- [With this letter is an envelope addressed to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin, 28 Rue Pauquet, Paris.] -->
            
            
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>