<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19150525">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to M. Kiffin Rockwell <date value="1915-05-25">May 25th, 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">8</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19150525</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>2 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer transcription.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
            <head>Jim to M. Kiffin Rockwell <date value="1915-05-25">May 25th, 1915</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline><date value="1915-05-25">May 25th, 1915</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>Dear Paul:</salute>
        		</opener>
        		
            <p>
            One of our men is leaving for Paris to
            morrow and I’m sending this note in by him
            to be mailed from there.
            </p>
        		<p>
            I hope things are coming along fine
            for you now and that you’ve gotten back 
            your usual cheerfulness.  Cheer up, mon vieux,
            for Italy marches and that will mean a
            few more dead enemies.  Speaking of that
            reminds me.  I went up to the first line
            trenches the other day, a line that had, with
            two others, been taken from the Boches, to
            see the burying of the dead.  The fire had
            been so hot that no one could go out to
            get the bodies and they were in a bad
            state.  I won’t go into the gruesome, or
            however you spell it, details of the burying of
            decaying French and German dead behind the
            lines, for I haven’t time to do it justice.
            out  front
            There were a few bodies remaining ^ and we
            were looking for those.  On our way back
            from the first line, and just as our boyau
            merged into the second, we smelt two corpses
            and were told they were about half way out 
            between the second and first line.  The young
            lieutenant with me pulled down some sand bags
            and wriggled out on his stomach.  I followed
            but forgot to keep low and zing a bullet
            went by.  I stayed down after that.  One of
            the bodies, both of which were German, proved
            to be an officer.  He was a fearful mess.
            His face was no longer a face but a black
            ball of putrid flesh out of which and over
            crawled swarms of magots [sic].  Teeth shown
            out of a bloated mouth giving a grinning 
            look to the thing.  The officer called a 
            couple of brancardiers out to him.  They examined 
            the body for identification and then the lieutenant
            ordered him dragged to a marmite hole near by.
            They pulled him by his boots and his head
                        
            <pb n="[p.2]"/>
            
            came off.  Then he broke in the middle, and 
            they had to start all over again.  After
            three crawling trips he was collected and
            duly interred.  The other corpse was more
            reasonable and remained intact during the
            haul.
        		</p>
        		<p>
            When the lieutenant and I had returned
            to the burying ground near the edge of
            that murdered part of nature known as
            Le Quart en Reserve we sat down and talked.
            Pretty soon a marmite came snarling thru [sic]
            the shattered, desolate woods and the officer
            rolled over on his stomach his arms
            protecting his head.  Pow [sic], and the eclats
            went over us.  The third was damn close
            and had I not been following the lieutenant’s 
            method of dodging I’d have gotten mine, for
            a large, robust and very speedy chunk 
            sang over my dome by a two foot miss
            and sunk in the edge of an excavation.
        		</p>
        		<p>
            Things have been very quiet “around these parts”
            of late.  Zora Lee Fry has gone to visit
            her uncle out on Route No. 3, and the 
            crops look good.
        		</p>
        		<p>
            Paris is sending us a big Hotchkiss
            car for sitting cases and that will help
            a lot.  By the way some officers around
            here tell us we’re going to get mentioned
            in the order of the day.  Some class
            if that comes off.  People are beating
            it out of town and as a result I
            have a most wonderful billet.  The Chief
            and I have a whole apartment along with
            a garden to ourselves.  I’m living up
            here all the time now.
        		</p>
        		
        		<closer>
            <salute>My best</salute>
        			
            <signed>Jim</signed>
        		</closer>
        		
            <!-- [The above letter is addressed to M. Kiffin Rockwell, Hospital No. 101 (Salle Pasteur), Reimes,
            	Ille et Vilaine.  The envelope includes the notation, "Pour Paul".
            
            File: McConnell/My25'15R -->
            
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>