<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19150708b">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to Mon. Paul Rockwell <date value="1915-07-08">July 8th 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19150708b</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>4 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
        		<head>Jim to Mon. Paul Rockwell <date value="1915-07-08">July 8th 1915</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline><date value="1915-07-08">July 8th 1915</date></dateline>
        			
        		<salute>	
            Dear Paul:
        		</salute></opener>
        		
        		<p>
            We have all been very very busy
            during the past ten days and in the last
            few days its been a continuous go.  As it stands
            now I haven’t slept for a couple of days and
            am now waiting another call this night.  If you’ve
            been following the papers you will know why.
            The roar has kept up day and night.  In spite
            of the rush we managed to pull off a regular
            old 4th of July fest.  Captain Watt and Noel, 
            the Aviators, were guests and what with
            our Frenchmen in various sorts of uniforms
            our board had a many colored appearance.
            Things were done up in style.  Someone had
            even scared up a piano.  We found wine
            and champagne glasses in the caserne and
            from the nearest city we had brought paper
            napkins.  An architect in the outfit had
            make special menues [sic] decorated with our flag.
            It was a classy affair but somewhat halting
            in that calls kept coming in and we
            were forced to be continually going out.
            Each man did some “stunt” and I remember
            how well Gunga Din sounded, recited as it
            was, when the artillery was roaring outside.  We
            had all the 4th of July noise one could wish
            for and illuminating rockets afforded a quota
            of fireworks.  The Boches evidently didn’t think
            we had done it up brown for they gave us
            a short bombardment later in the evening.
                        
            <pb n="[p.2]"/>
            
            The wounds are frightful these days and
            a good many die before we get them to
            the surgeons.  The only consolation lies in
            the fact that the Boches are getting it
            just as badly.  The damn swine are using
            gas and as an extra barbarism they throw
            petrol jets on the choking soldiers.
            </p><p>
            It seems that its the Army of the 
            Crown Prince operating against us here.  I
            didn’t know that before.  It also turns
            out that the Germans, as we have found
            out from prisoners, know an American section
            is doing the sanitary work for the French
            in this secteur.  Of course they see our
            cars, but I didn’t know before that they
            knew that we were an American section.  As
            a matter of fact its quite mixed, with
            English, French, a Hollander and ourselves.
            The latest addition is R. J. Cunningham the 
            famous African lion hunter.  He’s a fine,
            old fellow but got poisoned and has 
            been evacuated for awhile.
            </p><p>
            Marcelle Guerin tells me you and your
            brother are going to dine Chez elle and 
            that possibly she’ll get Mlle. Du Bouchet to
            fill in.  Seems years since you and I
            were there and you were late getting back
            to the Ambulance.  Remember?  It was the
            night before I left.  The outfit looks very
            much changed since it pulled out of
                        
            <pb n="[p.3]"/>
            
            the yard that morning with flags flying.
            Flags! Oh hell.  They were pulled off
            long ago.  I’ve gone thru [sic] one car and
            for the past month have been driving
            a new one.  The few cars that were
            detached from the fizzle of a tent section
            and assigned to do our evacuation
            below the zone have been a lot of bother.
            Four of the men have quit, two cars have
            been smashed driving at night and they’ve
            gone on the bum generally.  The outfit
            wasn’t much good to start with naturally,
            but there are two or three good men
            and as soon as they are tried out we
            may take them on.  A good deal of
            responsibility has been given us &mdash; Not even
            any French automobile section is located as
            close as we are, &mdash; and we have to be very
            careful who we accept.  There are three
            fellows in the gang now that I wish could
            be got rid of.
            </p><p>
            At last things seem to have quieted
            down here, but believe me the whole works
            has been raising some intense little action.
            The Boches on the hill at the end of our
            street whose trenches are but 1,400 yards
            off got fresh the other night.  Its just a 
            salient that comes in there, unimportant,
            and as they haven’t been doing anything, nor
            indulging in any great amount of shooting down with
                        
            <pb n="[p.4]"/>
            
            rifles they’ve been let alone.  Why they got
            so tame that sometimes their sentinels
            would stand up clear cut against
            the sky.  Well sir, the night of the
            fifth about 9 P.M. you should have
            heard the howl they let loose and
            down they started for town.  We couldn’t
            see very well but it certainly wasn’t very 
            far down before they got it.  The report
            of rifles and sing of the mitrailleuses blended
            into one continuous whirring clatter and
            in ten minutes it was over.  They got
            badly shot up.  That’s an awful crust on
            their part but I guess they won’t try it
            again.
            </p><p>
            Doesn’t the American action in regard
            to the war make you tired?  Its 
            Mexico all over again.  Sort of a make-a-
            bluff-and-if-its-called-try-another,
            diplomacy.
            </p><p>
            You never run across Betty Baldwin
            of 11 Bis Bvd Debessert do you?  I hear
            from her now and then.  Damn nice of 
            the kid to write.
            </p><p>
            Excuse the dullness of this letter
            but my brain won’t work at all now.
            </p><p>
            How are things going with you?
            Have you received the two letters I sent
            in by the staff car some time ago?
            </p>
        		
        		<closer>
            <signed>Jim.</signed>
        		</closer>
        		
            
            <!-- [The envelope with this letter is addressed to Mon. Paul Rockwell, Hotel Beauvau, 24 Rue de Miromesnil, Paris.] -->

        	</div1>
        	</body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>