<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0127 SYSTEM "000001107_0127" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0128 SYSTEM "000001107_0128" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0129 SYSTEM "000001107_0129" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0130 SYSTEM "000001107_0130" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0131 SYSTEM "000001107_0131" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0132 SYSTEM "000001107_0132" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0133 SYSTEM "000001107_0133" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0134 SYSTEM "000001107_0134" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0135 SYSTEM "000001107_0135" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0136 SYSTEM "000001107_0136" NDATA uvaHighRes>

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19150708">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-07-08">July 8th 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19150708</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>8 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
        		<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0127"/>
        		<head>Jim to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-07-08">July 8th 1915</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline><date value="1915-07-08">July 8th 1915</date></dateline>
        		</opener>
        		
            <p>
            I have just come in from night
            duty and found your very delightful
            letter in the bureau where I reported
            before going for coffee.  I put your letter
            in my pocket and went over to my
            room, washed up a bit, and sat
            down to read it.  I had intended
            going to bed for it was hard work
            all day yesterday, and all night, but
            somehow your letter, the touch it
            brought me of yourself, has rested
            me and now I want to write you
            instead of resting.  Its wonderful
            how much content and happiness your
            letters bring me &mdash; all except those parts
            where I find how hard and disagreeable
            some phases of your work are.  Still
            even those recitals add a great deal
            for they give a bigger meaning to the rest
            of the letter.  I’m awfully sorry you’ve
            got such a rotten patient on your
            hands and I hope to goodness something,
            it doesn’t matter very much what, will
            relieve you of the task.  In this
            work everyone concerned, the patient,
            nurse, or doctor, or anyone concerned, [concerned scratched out] have
            to work in harmony or the task becomes
            very, very hard.  Of course I do not get
            the disagreeable, long drawn out trials
            that fall to your lot &mdash; your dear, fine
                        
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0128" n="[p.2]"/>
            
            girl, but I deal with certain phases
            that are sufficient to give me an
            understanding of how hard it must be.
            My trouble is with the brancardiers
            and doctors, not the wounded.  The 
            wounded and his regimental infermeries
            and we conductors are on one side.  The
            hospital outfit on the other.  Its so
            bitterly discouraging sometimes.  Take for
            instance last night.  Everyone is tired,
            and cross.  If you have been following 
            the papers you will know why.  For
            two weeks its been that way.  Well
            as I say we’re tired and that doesn’t 
            help matters, but good heavens others
            have less right to be worn out and
            they should do their part.  There is
            heavy firing going on.  It will be some time
            before the wounded are brought down.  Maybe
            half and hour, and one lies down in the 
            telephone room up there back of the trenches
            hoping for a few minutes sleep before
            another call.  Its cold now for the
            windows were blown out of the place
            three days ago, and it takes a little
            while to doze off.  There is a faint 
            ring and looking up from the stretcher
            one is lying on one sees the weary 
            telephonist in the dim light of his
            candle plug in the connection.  Then &mdash;
                        
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0129" n="[p.3]"/>
            
            “Monsier Americain, un plesse’ urgent a c -”
            You get up and go out to the car and
            whirr [sic]up a long hill to a place in
            the woods.  The poor, hard worked men at 
            the poste de secours are waiting.  In the
            light of the illuminating rockets you
            see a much bandaged figure on a stretcher
            and between the reports of artillery you
            get instructions to go carefully but
            swiftly.  That’s hard, that two kilometers
            down into town and you figure on every
            little bump or hole.  Sometimes there’s a
            new shell hole and you hit it.  The
            poor fellow shrieks and you would
            give anything to have avoided the bump.
            We get so that we know the easiest way
            to take all turns and what sides of the
            road are smoothest, but every second is
            a strain as we nurse the car down
            to the Ambulance where the man will
            be operated on and evacuated the next
            morning.  The cobblestone streets are the
            hardest proposition and then comes the
            hospital.  You stop and go to the back 
            of the car.  The wounded man is groaning
            softly.  You hurry into the bureau to
            wake up the attendant.  “Un couch’
            garment bless”<unclear>[.]</unclear>  The man slowly gets up
            mumbling about the toughness of the
            war and slowly ambles back into the
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0130" n="[p.4]"/>
            
            building.  Minutes pass.  You go out to
            the car and try and explain the
            delay to the wounded man.  One brancardier
            comes out.  When will the other come,
            you wonder.  He’s careless about that 
            and wants to know if there are
            many more wounded.  Finally you lose
            all patience.  I know I do and think
            of the other brancardier still sleeping.
            Finally he comes out.  The man is
            taken into the operating room and
            examined in a superficial way.  They
            wake up a surgeon.  He takes his
            time and after a short look turns
            away saying its no use trying to
            operate and goes back to bed.  The
            man is carried to a side of the
            room and the brancardiers go out.  Oh,
            that hurts so after you have tried so
            hard to get the poor fellow down as
            easily as possible and hoped you could
            save his life.  To have that indifference
            shown is very aggravating.  You go up
            again after using up all your matches
            trying to pick out a brancard that
            isn’t too bloody or broken and find
            a load waiting.  Three couches and two
            assis.  Down the hill you go again and
            then there’s the same fight to wake
            up the hospital.  (I am taking parts
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0131" n="[p.5]"/>
            
            from last night’s work for its fresh
            in my memory and typical of other
            nights)  I took the two assis in
            with me while I went to rout out
            the brancardiers.  In the corner of the
            room the poor fellow I had brought before
            was making hideous noises.  He seemed
            pitiful [sic] dying there all alone, and
            when I lit a match the two assis
            looked at him in a shocked sort of
            way.  I went out to my couches.  There 
            was a long delay getting the men out.
            One was a trepan case and I said
            I’d take him down eight kilometers
            where a young doctor in a second
            evacuation hospital would take care of
            him all right.  “Oh we do all that here”
            said a brancardier and disappeared with
            the jolting stretcher.  They didn’t return
            for a long time.  The remaining man
            and I passed the time cussing the
            gang out.  “Here we go and get all shot
            to pieces and then they treat us like
            cochons” he said.  When the brancardiers
            came out he handed them a bit of his 
            mind “Remember you’re not the only one,”
            they said and that got me furious.
            “You g - d - bunch of embusques.  You
            sit around here all day and raise - h - 
            when a wounded man is the cause of some
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0132" n="[p.6]"/>
            
            work, just as if you blamed him for
            it.  I hope to heavens you all get
            sent up and get a taste of it yourself.”
            I said all that in English but from
            the tone and the word embusques they
            got my meaning perfectly and for
            the rest of the night things went
            better.	
            </p><p>
            It is disheartening you know.  When
            you come down from all the hellish
            surroundings of the fight with a 
            man who has sacrificed himself, right
            under your eyes as it were.  You feel
            as if a whole lot was due when you
            get to the peace and comparative quiet
            of the town, and then when the
            poor fellow is treated as if he were
            a burden it nearly makes you cry.
            Oh I know how it is.  There are
            thousand and thousands and its
            impossible to give much attention, but
            it could be very much different at
            a certain ambulance I know of.  I’m
            accustomed to all the suffering myself
            and a bit hardened but I try to 
            give every wounded man the best I
            can do in the circumstances.  Of the
            fifty two I brought down last night
            I didn’t forget a bump on any trip
            and watched just as carefully each time.
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0133" n="[p.7]"/>
            
            Anyone, of course, would do that and so
            its but natural that one expects
            people in other departments to at
            least try and do their best.
            </p><p>
            I suppose I sound very gloomy.  Forgive
            me for getting off on all that
            strain.  You’ve got enough disagreeable
            things to bother about.  I guess I’m
            just cross and sleepy.  Next time I
            won’t write until I’m in a better
            humor.
            </p><p>
            We had a regular 4th of July celebration.
            The noise was all free and there was
            plenty of it, and as an extra the
            Boches gave us a little bombardment.
            We had a regular banquet with various
            sorts of wine glasses we found in the
            caserne; flowers in projectile vases,
            paper napkins, flags and various sorts
            of liquid refreshment.  A chef from New York,
            who is with the troops, prepared the
            meal for us.  Captain Wall the aviator
            and Noel as well were guests.  In the 
            lamp light the varied collection of uniforms
            was quite effective.  It seemed queer
            to be dining in that way 1,400 yards
            from the German trenches.  Calls kept
            coming in and we left in turn.
            One of the fellows recited Gunga Din
            and during it we heard the roar
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0134" n="[p.8]"/>
            
            of artillery and saw the flashes of 
            guns.  It was quite realistic.  We all
            did various stunts and the evening
            was a great success.
            </p><p>
            I told you didn’t I that some of
            the tent section cars have been detached
            and now do our evacuation to points
            below the fighting zone.  They can’t
            come any nearer than our old base 
            and we run on down with a 
            fatherly air, to put wounded in the
            hospital there.  It must make them
            furious.  They’re funny to watch.  Yesterday
            in passing thru [sic] the old base some of
            us were in time to get there as
            some shells landed and the new crowd
            was just as excited as could be.  They
            were like a crowd of kids.  “Oh Gee we’re in
            the war” stuff &mdash; and they’re still talking
            about it I guess.
            </p><p>
            I like Lovell better every day.  He’s
            a real man all the way through.  His
            nerve is fine.  He says he’ll stick it
            out.  He and our chief are the best 
            we have.  There are three lemons in the
            outfit.
            </p><p>
            I’ll write soon again.  You’re a peach
            to write me at such length as you did.
            </p>
        		
        		<closer>
            <salute>Affectionately</salute>
            
            <signed>Jim.</signed>
        		</closer>
        		
            <!-- [With this letter is an envelope addressed to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin, 148 bis Rue de Longchamps, Paris.] -->
				
				<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0135"/>
        		<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0136"/>
				
        	</div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
