<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19150624">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to M. Paul Rockwell <date value="1915-06-24">June 24th 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">17</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19150624</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>8 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
        		<head>Jim to M. Paul Rockwell <date value="1915-06-24">June 24th 1915</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline><date value="1915-06-24">June 24th 1915</date></dateline>
        			
            <salute>Dear Paul:</salute>
        		</opener>
        		
            <p>
            Eh, mon brave, where’s that long
            letter you were going to write, promised in
            the last I have received from you which
            was written four days after your return from 
            Reimes [sic]?  Does the line “Am expecting Jeanne
            to Paris today” explain why I haven’t had the
            pleasure?  Indirectly I have heard that
            you’re still up and doing from Marcelle G.
            and the Vicomte.  You probably know he 
            sent me a letter.  I was quite floored with
            the compliment of getting such a delightful
            personal letter from him.  It was fine
            of him to write to me.  I tried to send
            an answer that would give him an idea
            of how much I appreciated his letter, but
            I’m afraid it sounded quite stiff and
            artificial, for I felt I had to be sort of
            formal.
            </p><p>
            The staff car is expected out to day and
            I shall send this letter in to be mailed from
            Paris.  There isn’t much news.  There has
            been no fighting going on here at all ^of late.  Some
            days we handle fifty wounded only, tho [sic] there
            will be spells [‘when’ scratched out] during an hour or
            two &mdash; when the crapouillot and grenade work
            has been lively, and there will be a lot of
            rush work.  Last night a great many were
            wounded by a short but fierce bombardment
            of the trenches by 210 s. Bad head wounds too,
                        
            <pb n="[p.2]"/>
            
            for out of eleven operations ten died, as the
            doctors told us this morning.  One fellow
            died in my car before I could get him to
            the hospital.
            </p><p>
            We are to be given the work of
            the adjacent division as well as the one
            we are now attached to and when that
            service starts we will go on beyond Auberge
            St. <unclear>Pierre [sp?]</unclear>, our last point of call at present,
            to Feyen <unclear>Hage [sp?]</unclear>, <unclear>Leiney [sp?]</unclear> and <unclear>Flirey [sp?]</unclear>.  On that
            road the Germans have a nice trick of
            dropping four shells at once, forming a square
            so to speak, and it would be quite delightful,
            to say the least, to be in the Center.  They’ve
            left us alone in Pont a Mousson itself for
            over four days now.
            </p><p>
            Captain Watts, the Australian aviator in
            the French service, and Noel, the famous
            military flier, ran down from their base
            near Toul to lunch with us this noon.
            Both of them have done wonders in this war.
            Its rather queer to meet men on the
            ground who you have watched being
            fired on in the air.  Do you know what
            secteur Thaw is working in?  I hear
            he’s quartered at Nancy but don’t know
            what he covers.  I forgot to ask.
            </p><p>
            There is to be a week more of nothing
            doing and then, depending somewhat on
            the result of the northern movement, we
            are to have one hell of a an attack in this
                        
            <pb n="[p.3]"/>
            
            place.  Watts expects to come down and
            rest with us after the work is
            over.  You ought to hear him on
            England.  He has no patience at all
            with the way they’re doing.  Too 
            many shirkers in the small crowd they 
            have out.  A Lord something or other he
            knows in England is yelling his lungs
            out about fellows recruiting, saying his
            son is fighting for “King &amp; Country”, but
            Watts ran into said K &amp; C fighter in Paris
            running some swank automobile supply
            system.
            </p><p>
            By the way, please advise me about
            the kind of stuff you think might sell.
            I mean give me a line on the material
            to look for; treatment, length, etc. and
            I’ll cook up a couple of samples from 
            the brand of copy one gets here and
            you can tell me whether I’m right or 
            wrong.  I have just finished a 7,000
            word article on the American section here
            that I know would be of interest in
            the States but its for the Ambulance
            Authorities who asked me to write it 
            up for them.  Its to be taken to
            the censor and then sent, God knows 
            where.  Your Sydney Adamson route sounds
            fine.  If it was so rotten he would
            be ashamed of putting his name au dessous
            we could fake another.  I might not
                        
            <pb n="[p.4]"/>
            
            be able to send in anything worth
            while, but then there’s no use ^not trying.
            You and Adamson &amp; I could figure out
            a whack up providing the stuff sells.
            </p><p>
            In a letter from Arthur Page, editor of 
            World’s Work, he tells me that even Arno
            Dosch (Fleurot’s) stuff is now hard to sell &mdash;
            that people now pass by unnoticed things
            that a year ago thrilled them to the 
            core and that now they are wondering
            what’s coming next and not interested in
            what’s gone before.  Too bad about em, 
            isn’t it?  I haven’t sent Page anything
            from out here yet.
            </p><p>
            When Walls and Noel were here, (You note I
            have continued the letter from the other day)
            Salisbury, our boss, and a couple of other fellows
            took them up to the trenches.  Noel said
            he knew the way perfectly from his aerial observations.
            Well they got on up to the Quart en Reserve
            and then got lost and wandered off into a
            section where artillery has practically levelled [sic]
            the ground.  They were finally wandering
            around in an abandoned area 200 meters from
            the Germans.  They knew they were exposed
            but not until later did they find out how
            close they were.  Well the nuts stood up
            there and had an argument.  Watts with
            glaring Captain’s galons and several gold
            wings on him began giving Noel hell
            for leading them the wrong way.  They
                        
            <pb n="[p.5]"/>
            
            argued out there for a long time.  No one
            can understand why the crowd wasn’t
            shot.  Three looked like English and two
            were French officers.  Finally they crawled
            back, tho [sic] what was left of the 
            trenches didn’t afford but six inches or
            less of cover and eventually got into the
            boyau running to the 1st line which is
            but 17 meters from the Boches.  A shell
            had just landed there and they had to
            crawl over some dead bodies.  I know
            the place, Le Col de Cygne, I was up
            there a few weeks ago but with an
            officer and didn’t get lost.  We took the
            fliers back to their grounds near Toul
            and they began telling about their visit
            to the trenches with all the excitement
            we would manifest should we recount
            a flight in one of their machines.  I’m
            going to try for a ride with Noel
            and hope to get it.  Watts has been
            hit 56 times &mdash; that is his machine
            has.  You know its fortunate in the 
            extreme that we are placed as we are.
            We get an intimate knowledge of all
            phases and it makes it all very interesting.
            We really see more of the details of the
            whole business than lots of French officers.
            Keep that observation under your hat please.
            Its only because we’ve make good tho [sic] that
            they let us have the cinch we enjoy.
                        
            <pb n="[p.6]"/>
            
            Last night I was on duty back at Dieulouard
            where every ten days one has a turn, and
            ran across some fellows I know from an
            Algerian battery in Bois le Pretre.  We formed
            up a concert.  We sat around a long
            table in the garden of some popote and
            beat time while the Algerians chanted.
            There was an Arab there that was a 
            wonder on the old two toned songs.  That
            language sounds as if one were trying to
            open an old rusty lock and it was
            breaking.  Felt at home tho [sic] for the rest
            were as rotten in French as I am.
            It had rained during the day, washing
            the air, and the light of the full
            moon was glorious.  Finally a girl, the
            prettiest I’ve seen out this way, slipped
            onto the scene.  I don’t know where she
            came from, but she looked strangely
            out of place in her fluffy white dress,
            flower bordered apron and tiny pumps,
            in the middle of our Algerian aggregation.
            Finally we got accustomed to her and
            I felt as if we were in northern Africa
            and she some fair houri.  One of
            the men borrowed her shawl, produced
            a couple of handkerchiefs in place of
            veils and to the accompaniment of chanting
            and measured beats proceeded to execute
            a danse de ventre.  It was great.  One
            of the fellows got marvelous cymbal
                        
            <pb n="[p.7]"/>
            
            effects out of a beer bottle with a 
            swinging cap and a door for a 
            sounding board.  This morning
            a fellow named Smith, who was on
            duty with me, and I motored the 
            crowd back to their battery.  Well
            we’re running a war de luxe if
            nothing else.  Very few of the
            fellows in the Artillery ever seem
            to get hurt.  When they do its
            an event.  Everyone stops your car
            on the way down and takes a 
            look at the gunner.
            </p><p>
            Yes, old boy, I reckon you’re
            right when you see no immediate
            ending to the war, and as far as
            Italy is concerned I don’t think she
            helps much.  You see she want Trieste
            and Trente [sic].  Austria couldn’t just
            quietly hand the section over to her
            and so Italy goes to war about it.
            Austria being in the position of heads I
            win &amp; tails you lose puts up a fake
            fight to hold her honor and lets
            Italy take what she wants with as
            little a loss as possible.  I am very
            much afraid that having occupied
            the area in question Italy will
            proceed to quit.  To do on I
            understand she wants, as a reward
            Tunisia.  Hell of a nerve, when you consider
                        
            <pb n="[p.8]"/>
            
            France made Italy what she is to day.
            The whole show seems up into
            France and Russia against Germany and
            Austria - Hungary with the aid of
            England’s sea power to help our Allies.
            The rest counts off.  Japan of course counts for 
            nothing and Serbia, Belgium &amp; Montenegro
            are more than balanced by Turkey.  When
            you figure the thing out in light of
            preparations;  the comparative strength of
            each, and what should have been 
            accomplished, why France and Russia 
            have beaten the devil out of 
            Germany and Austria.  Grand Meme
            c’est dure cette sale guerre.  And a few
            other oft repeated formulas such as 
            “Quand ^serait [sp?]  fini, cette guerre?” &amp; “Qui j’aimerais bien
            de voir la fin, c’est longue, c’est dure.”
            </p>
        		
        		<closer>
            <salute>Hope to hear from you soon
            old legionaire [sic].</salute>
            
            <signed>Jim</signed>
            
            <seg type="postscript">
            Mc Connell, James<lb/>
            S.S.Americaine.Y.<lb/>
            Secteur Postal 84          
            </seg>
        		</closer>
        		
            <!-- [The envelope with this letter is addressed to M. Paul Rockwell, Chez M. le Vicomte du Peloux, 15 Avenue Malakoff, Paris.] --> 
            
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>