<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19150716">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to Mon. Paul Rockwell <date value="1915-07-16">July 16th 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19150716</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>4 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
        		<head>Jim to Mon. Paul Rockwell <date value="1915-07-16">July 16th 1915</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline>Friday. <date value="1915-07-16">July 16th 1915</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>
            Dear Paul:
            </salute></opener>
        		
        		<p>
            Got your postal a couple of days
            ago but have looked in vain for the
            letter.  Guess you’re quite occupied with
            Jeanne &amp; Kiffin.  Hope things are going
            well anyway.
            </p><p>
            One of our fellows is leaving
            to morrow for the States and I’m sending
            in this letter by him.  By the way why
            don’t you put your Sun man onto the
            fact so a New York reporter at the dock
            can get some copy from him when he
            lands.  He will sail on the French line
            in about a week.  He’s well supplied
            with pictures and has been in the
            service for nine months.  His name is
            Leif Barclay.  The publicity you gave me has
            the notoriety for Lydia Pinkum’s Pink Pills
            looking like the announcement of a chamber-
            maids wedding.  It branched out from
            New York papers until it got to the obscure
            recesses of Moore County, North Carolina.  They
            went em [sic] all one better and I’m sure
            that when I return there will be a
            welcoming committee composed of the
            leading citizens in high hats, the fire
            department in red shirts and little girls
            in white dresses waving palm leaves.
            </p><p>
            By the way I have some good news.
            Remember my telling you I was asked to
                        
            <pb n="[p.2]"/>
            
            write a sketch of the life of this section
            and that I turned in 7,000 words?  Well
            our inspector, Mr. Andrew liked it so well
            that he has been reading it all over 
            Paris.  He was up here last night and
            told me that he read it to a group
            in which Mr. &amp; Mrs<unclear>[.]</unclear> Bacon (Ex Ambassador
            outfit) and a couple of other high brows.
            Result:  Mrs. Bacon, who is returning to
            America to get more money for the hospital
            is going to take the screed with her; get
            Teddy Roosevelt to write a preface and
            have it run in Scribners or Metropolitan.
            Andrew, who at one time was Assistant Sec’y
            of the Treasury is a side kick of
            Teddy’s and has also written  to
            the Colonel.  Some class if it frames
            up along the lines they’ve cooked
            up, eh [sic] what, old pal?
            </p><p>
            The enemy has been active of late in our
            secteur and we’ve all been working very
            hard.  They haven’t been able to do anything
            since their success the night of July 4th.
            In that attack, preceded by a ten days shelling,
            they took back all we had gained since
            the month of January in the area known as
            the Quart en Reserve.  About two kilometers
            at a certain point.  We had to move
            our artillery back.  They got to within 300
            meters of a battery of 220 s.  Of course a
            number of 75 s in the woods fell into
            their hands as well as 1,000 prisoners.
                        
            <pb n="[p.3]"/>
            
            Don’t let on I told you this.  Might get
            back and get me into trouble.  We are
            now retaking the lost ground daily, tho [sic]
            it isn’t figured by trenches any more.  There
            are no trenches left - just upheaved
            earth and bits of murdered nature.  Seems
            hard to realize the damn swine are so
            close, but they are mighty near at
            some points.  A little over a month ago I
            was in the first line at Le Col de Cygne
            and now that’s Boche.  Oh well we’ll
            shove em [sic] back.  On les ora.  This
            small attack business means nothing
            but part of a process: the wearing down
            and killing of Germans.  The big events
            will have to wait until next spring
            when Russia is supplied and has her
            new Armies ready and England can lend
            a hand.  The Russian retreats now are
            all in our favor.  The Germans are being
            worn down.  I wouldn’t be surprised to
            have them meet with a disaster similar
            to that experienced by Napoleon this winter.
            Anyway it keeps them from making any big 
            drives our way.
            </p><p>
            I’m anxious to hear all about you and
            your plans for I want to request a six
            day leave within the next two months
            and of course when I take the rest 
            will depend on your schedule.
                        
            <pb n="[p.4]"/>  
            
            I have been given to understand that we
            will be allowed a leave.  Each taking his
            turn in Paris.  The soldiers here are
            getting six days clear.  That is a full
            six at home.  I’ve got two friends going
            all the way to Algeria.  The time taken in
            traveling doesn’t count against them.
            </p><p>
            Nearly all the infantry here now is
            Colonial.  Most of the men came from
            the Midi and it takes a man with a 
            better knowledge of French then I have to
            understand them.  Being for Bien and
            all that sort of patois.  A number are
            seeing their first time at the front.  They
            aren’t on to grenades and things and get
            hurt using them.  Last night I brought
            down a man who had blown his hand
            off with one and I also transported four 
            of his mates who had been wounded
            by the same grenade.
            </p><p>
            Haven’t heard from Marcelle Guerin in a long
            time.  Hope she’s well.  How’s your brother
            now?  Wish him luck for me.
            </p><p>
            Well old “Compin” here’s how, and
            hoping to hear from you soon.
            </p>
        		
        		<closer>
            <salute>Yours</salute>
            
            <signed>Jim</signed>
            
            <seg type="postscript">
            S.S. Americanine, Y.<lb/>
            Secteru Postal 84
            </seg>
        		</closer>
        		
            <!-- [With this letter is an envelope addressed to Mon. Paul Rockwell, Hotel Beauvau, 24 Rue de Mironesnil, Paris.] -->
            
        	</div1>
        	</body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>