<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0017 SYSTEM "000001107_0017" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0018 SYSTEM "000001107_0018" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0019 SYSTEM "000001107_0019" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0020 SYSTEM "000001107_0020" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0021 SYSTEM "000001107_0021" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0022 SYSTEM "000001107_0022" NDATA uvaHighRes>

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC191504nd">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to  Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-04">Apr 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">9</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC191504nd</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>4 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        		<div1 type="letter">
        			<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0017"/>
        			<head>Jim to  Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-04">Apr 1915</date></head>
        			
        		<opener>	
            <dateline><date value="1915-04">Apr 1915</date></dateline>
        		</opener>
        			
            <p>
            We have just received orders to proceed to Pont a Mousson to morrow at nine.  We will arrive  there 
            probably at noon.  It is at the front and our letters will be held for several days, so I am taking this 
            opportunity of writing.
            </p>
        		<p>
            Our squad is most fortunate.  It is the first to go to the front.  This morning our roll was called and we 
            were asked for an address to notify in case we we [sic] were wounded or killed.  It really promises to be 
            interesting and worth while work and I am very glad.
        		</p>
        		<p>
            The fact that I am on this squad, a squad whose members were chosen carefully, should convince you 
            that your fear of my breaking loose is ungrounded.  I liked you for telling me frankly not to kick over the 
            traces and to watch myself, but honestly I never fall down on a job.  Why after our squad was complete, 
            three men were ordered dropped, and I still remained, so you see my record isn’t so rotten.
        		</p>
        		<p>
            We’ve had the most wonderful trip imaginable.
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0018" n="[p.2]"/>
            
            After threading our way across Paris, and jolting along the rough cobblestone streets of the outskirts, we 
            found ourselves traveling along a perfect road through the most charming country.  You know how pleasing 
            it is; the exquisite coloring that is on every hand; the great stretches of undulating ground divided into the 
            angular patch work fields, that are in themselves delightful gardens; the quaint, artistic groups of houses that 
            cluster along the ribbon like road, and the light green streams that delineate the curving valleys.  Never have 
            I felt that life was so pretty or the world so good.  I am aware now of what is meant by “La Belle France” as 
            I never was before.  Why I wouldn’t trade one of the vistas I saw our second day out, as we followed the 
            Marne, for the whole of Paris.  Somehow I associated all of it with you much more than I do Paris.  It would 
            have seemed much more natural to meet you out there than to encounter you in Paris.  Its all so free, and 
            beautiful and sweet that it seems as if that should comprise your surroundings rather that the artificial 
            atmosphere of the city.
        		</p>
        		<p>
            We passed through many places where fighting had taken place.  At noon we had reached La Ferte 
            Gaucher where the battle
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0019" n="[p.3]"/>
            
            that drove the Germans back commenced.  A little further on we passed numerous graves.  Some were quite 
            elaborate and had permanent crosses and wreathes on them.  These were along the road and sheltered many 
            soldiers, while others out in the fields were marked with a rude cross only, save when the poor fellow’s kepi 
            had been placed on the top.  The fields are being cultivated now and the furrows run almost to the little spot 
            of ground in which the cross is placed.  Beyond we went through little villages where a number of houses 
            had been levelled [sic] by shell fire, and some had burnt.
        		</p>
        		<p>
            Our first night out we stopped at St. Dizier where the population turned out and crowded around our 
            cars.  I’d have you know that I’m getting on so well in French that I was able to answer 
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0020" n="[p.4]"/>
            
            all their questions and had a group all of my own.  Curtin had another of course.
        		</p>
        		<p>	
            This place is quite dead.  All the fine hotels have been turned into hospitals and only soldiers are about.  
            A very quaint place down in the village and most interesting.  The air here is great and gives one really too 
            great an appetite for satisfying on the army rations.  We’re under military rule now.  Have to salute, be in at 
            eight, and obey all kinds of rules.  Our Captain here is a fine fellow.  Hope the next one’s the same.
        		</p>
        		<p>	
            You’ll write me won’t you?  And soon for I’m terribly anxious to hear from you.  I’ll send you word 
            from our new post as soon as possible.
        		</p>
        			
        		<closer>	
            <signed>Jim</signed>
            
            <seg type="postscript">
            Address American Ambulance Corps
            Nancy squad
            </seg>
        		</closer>
        			
            <!-- [With this letter is an envelope addressed to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin, 28 Rue Pauquet, Paris.] -->
            
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0021"/>
            <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0022"/>
            		
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>