<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19150729">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to M. Paul Rockwell <date value="1915-07-29">July 29th 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">10</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19150729</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>4 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
        		<head>Jim to M. Paul Rockwell <date value="1915-07-29">July 29th 1915</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline><date value="1915-07-29">July 29th 1915</date></dateline>
            
            <salute>
            Dear Paul:
            </salute></opener>
        		
        		<p>
            Got your card and am looking
            forward to your letter.
            </p><p>
            One of our men is returning to
            the States, his three months being up,
            and I’m sending in this letter by
            him.  In fact two or three additional
            are going, and two new ones are coming
            out from Paris.  One is [‘Lawrence’ scratched out] Waldo Pierce,
            the nut that started for Europe with 
            John Reed on a cattle ship and not
            liking the cattle ship jumped overboard
            when outside of Boston light and
            broke a swimming record.
            </p><p>
            The night of the 22nd we caught
            it for fair here in town.  One man was
            killed and two wounded.  Nine others had
            the damndest [sic] luck I’ve ever heard of.
            They were having a bit of a party in
            one fellow’s quarters which were in a
            house located at the juncture of two
            streets.  It was the logical target
            of the whole town but hadn’t been
            touched.  We had had two bombardments
            during the day but they hadn’t come
            within 100 yards of our caserne, or the
            house in question which is quite near
            by.  At 8.30 the affair opened up with
            the simultaneous arrival of four high
            speed, high explosive “Marmites”.  The first
                        
            <pb n="[p.2]"/>
            
            hit right on the nose of a small earth
            retaining wall in front of the house.
            It blew the nine to the floor with
            a lot of debris to boot.  The other
            shells hit close by.  They made a
            jump for the cave and just as
            they got in a shell hit the house
            and blew it to pieces inside.  Nothing
            remains intact.  The coats the fellows
            left behind are in shreds.  The 
            first shell had killed one of the
            section, the nicest Frenchman in the 
            lot, as he was passing the house
            on the way to the caserne.  I,
            fortunately, had passed a few minutes
            before.  Another French member with him
            was badly wounded.  The fellows in
            the cave heard the cries and went 
            up to help.  A mother and her
            daughter were lying clasped in each
            others arms, dead, alongside of our man.
            Soon after a shell hit just at the
            edge of the pavement and cellar and
            blew the cave to bits.  Three escapes
            for the nine of them is mighty
            fortunate I think.  One was cut a
            bit from the first shell.  The wounded
            French fellow looked fearfully when he
            came running into the caserne.  An 
            eclat had gone thru [sic] his cheeks, cutting
                        
            <pb n="[p.3]"/>
            
            his tongue and another got his left
            arm.  It has only half its bones
            left and may have to be cut off.
            I got my car and took him to the 
            Ambulance.  He couldn’t speak and I
            didn’t know at the time the other
            fellow was dead.  Then at the Ambulance
            they gave me a wounded civil to take
            all the way to Nancy.  When I got back
            things were pretty bad.  They had
            been banging Marmites all around, and
            on the caserne.  The crowd was in
            the cave and safe, but wondering
            what was coming next.  I feel mighty
            sorry about Maignot.  He was a fine fellow.
            </p><p>
            The Medecine Divisionaire has removed the
            last Ambulance from Pont a Mousson
            now and now we have to evacuate
            all the way to Dieulouard at night.
            We hope to get a sort of Poste de
            Secours started so as to obviate that
            night trip.  Its almost impossible to
            make without lights.  The French lieutenant
            in charge during Salisbury’s absence had us
            move our bureau from the caserne, whose
            range had been found.  The next night,
            the quartier where the new bureau was
            located was shelled with 210 s. short.
            Salisbury got back to day.  He’s located
            a fine place for the bureau.  Its
                        
            <pb n="[p.4]"/>
            
            in the part of town nearest to Montauville [Montreuil ?],
            where the postes de secours start in,
            and makes it much better all around.
            Its a regular mansion with generous grounds and fixed
            for fare -you - well inside.  Can’t believe its true, its
            all so damned fine.  Lieutenant Kullman, our French
            lieutenant has beat it ^for Dieulouard, and so I pinched his room
            at Salisbury’s invitation.  Feel like a General of 1870
            in the splendor of a commandeered chateau.  I would
            feel as if I were going it a bit too strong were
            it not for the fact that we’re only a few hundred
            lines from the Germans and so if we can make our-
            selves comfortable why not.  My bed’s got one of those
            canopy’s [sketch of canopy with round top] like that over it.  Some swank &mdash;
            and a bath room &mdash; and old housekeeper
            to arrange things.
            </p><p>
            The picture of you and myself came out in
            the N.Y.Times with a regular speil.  Did
            you see it?  Great class to it, you
            old publicity agent.  Now be sure and let
            me know what’s what after you pass the
            Commission, and as soon as possible, for 
            I want to arrange my “permission”.
            </p><p>
            Got a letter from Marcelle Guerin just 
            now saying she saw you and Kiffin at
            Mlle. Dubouchet’s.
            </p><p>
            Last night Germans tried to pull off a sneak
            out in mass grenade throwing charge.  They were
            cut to pieces and we had only 90 wounded.
            </p>
        		
        		<closer>
            <salute>More Anon</salute>
            
            <signed>Jim</signed>
        		</closer>
        		
            
            <!-- [The envelope with this letter is addressed to M. Paul Rockwell, Hotel Beauvau, 24 Rue de Miromesnil, Paris.] -->          
            
			</div1>
        </body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>