<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0111 SYSTEM "000001107_0111" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0112 SYSTEM "000001107_0112" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0113 SYSTEM "000001107_0113" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0114 SYSTEM "000001107_0114" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0115 SYSTEM "000001107_0115" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0116 SYSTEM "000001107_0116" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0117 SYSTEM "000001107_0117" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0118 SYSTEM "000001107_0118" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0119 SYSTEM "000001107_0119" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0120 SYSTEM "000001107_0120" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0121 SYSTEM "000001107_0121" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000001107_0122 SYSTEM "000001107_0122" NDATA uvaHighRes>

]>

<TEI.2 id="McC19150623">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Jim to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-06-23">June 23rd 1915</date>
                </title>
                <author></author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">McC19150623</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-McConnell-papers</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Papers of James Rogers McConnell [manuscript], 1915-1977 (bulk 1915-1917)</title>
                        <author>McConnell, James R. (James Rogers), 1887-1917.</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>8 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 2104</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">2798594-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a2798594</idno>
                        
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
        	<div1 type="letter">
        		<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0111"/>
        		<head>Jim to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin <date value="1915-06-23">June 23rd 1915</date></head>
        		
        		<opener>
            <dateline><date value="1915-06-23">June 23rd 1915</date></dateline>
        		</opener>
        		
  <p>
     Now, isn’t that just like it?
Would only happen once in a thousand
times, but the letter and the postal
came together.  Our Marichal des logis
went to headquarters today and happened
to get both pieces of mail.  Still
until proved otherwise I think     
     S.S. Americaine Y is better than the
     Secteur Postal 8H
Convoy.  The officers around here seem to think 
so.
</p><p>
     I haven’t heard from Paul in a long
time; don’t know about his flaws, and as for
the wedding that’s in the uncertain future.
Hope it comes off soon, and that I can
get a leave, for I most certainly am
anxious to see you.  Heavens it will be
great to talk to you again and look you 
over.  I always got a lot of pleasure out
of looking you over, you know &mdash; or possibly
you didn’t.  The directions as to how
to reach you are very correct I presume 
but as far as I understand them I
go to the Etoile, walk around six times,
start down for a tram, get off and
walk over to the <unclear>Trocaders [sp?]</unclear> and turn
to my left, then walk back and
turn to my right and end by going
out to Neuilly.  Oh of course I’ll get there
all right.  That’s one sure thing.  What I
am worrying about now is whether
I’ll get in before the war’s over.   
</p><p>

<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0112" n="[p.2]"/>

     We are honored today by a call from
Captain Watts the Australian aviator in
the French Army and Lieu. Noel the famous
flier.  Watts is a wonderful looking
fellow.  He’s stationed right down the
road towards Toul, some twenty
kilometers away, and from that aviation
ground starts for his work over the
trenches.  We can tell him by the 
fact that he flies low and we watch
the Germans firing at him.  Firing at
aeros is a foolish occupation.  Only
about once in five thousand times do
shots come anywheres [sic]near them.
</p><p>
     I told you in my last letter 
about visiting the tent squad and
finding old Doty hanging around there
and as for Suckley I write him off
and on &mdash; just to make him jealous &mdash; 
and hear that he’s doing well.  I
suppose you know they made a
general clean up at the Ambulance
and the among others O’Hagan was
fired for just being O’Hagan and Blair
for being Blair.  Poor rough old Harris, the
horse fellow got it too, but I was sorry
to see him go.  He was all right.
</p><p>
     The staff car, by which I shall
send back this letter is two days
overdue for some reason I can’t understand.

<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0113" n="[p.3]"/>

</p><p>
     Its fortunate that we are to have the
Pierce - Arrow for it will help a great deal.
We are a little short of drivers.  Two
men have been sent back, Curtin had to
return to America and two others didn’t
want to stand the risk and returned
to Paris.  An English fellow named Bushwell,
a pretty, pink cheeked chap, the scion of
some ancient and honorable family is our
last addition.  I don’t know how he’ll 
make out.  In some ways I’m dubious but
hope he’s all right for we have trouble
getting men.  They put up this “Well
you see I’m the only child” spiel, and 
go to the Vosges or Dunkirk.  We’ve got
an excellent crowd now, with the 
exception of one awful lemon whose
presence I can’t understand.  Yes, I miss
Curtin a good deal.  Its a shame he had
to go.  You miss him a lot too, don’t
you now?  D----- it!
</p><p>
     Don’t get a false idea of our town
from the inclosed, [sic] for its a photo of the
worst shot up place in the collection.
Worst appearing, I mean, for of course there
are some houses that are all done for,
nothing left, and others with no insides
for the big shells fall almost straight 
down.
</p><p>
     Did I tell you we are to get the
work of the next section and that we

<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0114" n="[p.4]"/>

will go to Leiney and Flirey and Tey en Haye?
Auberge St. Pierre near the Quart en Reserve of
Le Bois le Pretre is our last point of call
at present.  I never wrote you, did I, about
my trip up to the first line trenches;
to the Col de Cygne; Le Gros Chene where
the rotten dead are buried, etc?  It was
about a month ago.  Oh, yes I did.  I
remember now.
</p><p>
     My  Mlle. Hostess is still
kind to me.  New baskets of cherries appear
unexpectedly in my room, vases of roses,
and now I find ruffles on the bed linen.
That is really too much.  I can’t figure out
the idea.  Modesty compells [sic] me to keep
silent the fact that my room-mate &mdash;I
mean suite-mate doesn’t draw the
attentions.  Which reminds me &mdash; how
is Sergius dear?
</p><p>
     Doesn’t the Nona McAdoo &amp; C. Britton
stuff make you tired?  They should have
stayed at home.
</p><p>
     Are you really standing up under
your work?  I’m quite worried about you
sometimes.  Of course you’re strong &mdash; stronger
by far than a great many &mdash; but you
take things so very seriously and go at 
it so conscientiously that you are apt
to over due [sic] yourself.  I don’t know of anyone
that should be admired more than you
for what you are doing and the way you

<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0115" n="[p.5]"/>

are doing it.  I never will forget your 
observation to the effect that what
makes France great is “Its soil and its
women”  The more I see of the wonder-
fully cultivated fields of France, and 
the more I think of you, the better
I understand the truth of your
statement.  This coming to your country
has done me a wonderful amount of good
and I believe that most of it is due to
the fact that I had you to point out some
of the hidden things to me, some of the
subtle influences obtaining here but which
do not have effect unless one is open to them.
Sometimes, when I think of how distressingly
American you are; when I recall some of
your remarks about being anxious to get 
back to that God forsaken New York I
could ring your charmingly formed neck
but then I remember that you are here
helping “us French” and I forgive you.
</p><p>
     I was on twenty four hours service at 
our former base, Dieulouard, yesterday
evacuating to the train which runs
up to the <unclear>hint [sp?]</unclear> of shell fire a
few kilometers below.  I have usually
dreaded that long day which falls to
each of us every ten days, but
this time I enjoyed it.  We had
sneaked some of our friends down from
an Algerian battery in Le Bois Le Pretre

<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0116" n="[p.6]"/>

so that they could rest at Dieulouard
for a change, and last night they
gave a concert.  We sat in a little
garden around a long table.  It had
rained during the day and cleaned the
air, so that the light of the full
moon was brilliant and glorious.  They
sang weird Arab songs while we
kept beat on the table, and then a
foolish sort of fellow from Paris
regaled us with peculiar pieces “Le Metro”
where one imitates the whistles and
closing of doors, etc.  The crowd had
gradually increased and then suddenly into
our midst glided one of the fairest young
women I’ve seen in a long time.  She was
quite young;   nineteen I would say, and
slim and graceful.  She wore a little
flower bordered apron and tiny pumps.
She was quite foreign to those surroundings,
it seemed, and the presence of the
Arabs and rough soldiers accentuated her
tenderness.  An old sergeant, who stayed at
her house had brought her down to hear
the concert.  He was either very broad
or didn’t know what was coming for
soon after she arrived the Arabs 
executed one of the wildest dances I’ve
seen.  They chanted, and for draperies
they used large handkerchiefs while
the fellow from Paris managed to get

<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0117" n="[p.7]"/>

wonderful cymbal effects out of a 
beer bottle with a swinging cap and
a door for a sounding board.  It 
was late when we started home.  The 
last thing I remember was how beautiful
the girl looked in the moonlight.  She
may be impossible in the day.  I don’t
know.
</p><p>
     This letter was started three
days ago and still the staff car
doesn’t come.  I can’t understand
the delay.  Maybe they are still
laughing at the <unclear>beer [sp?]</unclear> section.  The
last I’ve heard about their flaws
is to the effect that they contemplate
moving near Mortmare to the North
west of us.  If such is the case I
presume we’ll evacuate to some point
where their cars will take the wounded
we have brought them.
</p><p>
     One of our men became very ill
with pluresie [sic], or however you spell it,
and was evacuated to Toul.  Today he
is being sent to the south of France
in spite of the fact that he wants
to go to Paris.  He has to follow the
regular route.  I suppose, therefore that if
I get wounded I won’t have the pleasure
of going to Paris but will end up
at Lyons or someplace down south.

<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0118" n="[p.8]"/>

Outside of not seeing you and Paul
I don’t care tho. [sic]  We would be
taken care of well and treated as
officers, as Ferguson, who is being
operated on at the Ambulance, however,
for up here where instruments are
lacking and what they have are dull
one’s chances are slim.  Night before last
out of eleven cases where an operation
was performed eleven died.  One died in
my car before I could get him to 
the ambulance or their would have
been twelve.  So many poor fellows
die in hospitals; cars, postes de secours, etc,
and there is no way of letting their
families know just how they died.  That
seems a pity for people seem to be
anxious to learn about the last
minutes of their own.  The fellow I had
began yelling about his mother, and lifting
up his head, and cigarettes, all at the 
same time as I locked him in.  When
we reached Bleuod he ceased to make a
noise and must have died then.  The 
other two in with him were so far
gone themselves they couldn’t have minded
it much.
</p>
        		
        		<closer>
             <salute>Affectionately</salute>
             <signed>Jim</signed>
     			</closer>

<!-- [With this letter are an envelope addressed to Mlle. Marcelle Guerin, Salle 69, Ambulance Americainie, 
Neuilly - sur - Seine; and a postcard with a picture entitled “Bombardment de PONT-a-MOUSSON” 
on which is written “After the war our town is going to be a point of call for those visiting the holey places”] -->

<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0121" n="[p.8]"/>
<pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0122" n="[p.8]"/>

        	</div1>
            <div1 type="postcard">
                <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0119"/>
                <figure rend="page"><byline>Bombardement de PONT-&#x00E0;-MOUSSON</byline></figure>
                <div2 type="note">
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000001107_0120"/>
                   <p> After the war our<lb/>
                    town is going to<lb/> 
                    be a point of call<lb/>
                    for those visiting<lb/> 
                    the holey places</p>
                </div2>
                </div1>
        	</body>
    </text>
	</TEI.2>