<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0283 SYSTEM "000000766_0283" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0284 SYSTEM "000000766_0284" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0285 SYSTEM "000000766_0285" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0286 SYSTEM "000000766_0286" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0287 SYSTEM "000000766_0287" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0288 SYSTEM "000000766_0288" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA61i26a SYSTEM "NA61i26a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61i26b SYSTEM "NA61i26b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61i26c SYSTEM "NA61i26c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61i26d SYSTEM "NA61i26d.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61i26e SYSTEM "NA61i26e.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61i26f SYSTEM "NA61i26f.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA61i26">
 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <!-- todo -->
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1861-09-26"
      >26 September 1861</date>
    </title>
    <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>David Seaman</name>
     <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
     <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>ETC</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NA61i26</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
    <date value="2001">2001</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 26 September 1861</title>
      <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>6 pages</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p/>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p> </p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings. </p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1861-09-26">1861-09-26</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>feminine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-02">November 2nd, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">
  <front id="d2">

   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>6 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1861-09-26">26 September 1861</date>

      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p/>
   </div1>
  </front>
  <body id="d4">
   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1861-09-26">26 September
      1861</date></head>
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0283"/>
    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <name type="place">Oil Spring Seminary, </name>
      <date value="1861-09-26">Sept 26, /61</date>
     </dateline>
     <salute>Dear Friend</salute>
    </opener>

    <p>After waiting long and <lb/>
     <unclear>anxiously</unclear> I at last recieved your kind <lb/> letter dated Sept. 16 Indeed I
     was <unclear/>
     <lb/> surprised when I recieved it for I had <lb/> almost <unclear>dispaired</unclear> the hope
     of hearing from <lb/> you again. and having heard since you left <lb/> Camp Dennison I thing
     that you must have <lb/> felt somewhat relieved when you found <lb/> yourself <unclear> down
      the </unclear>. You must <lb/> have felt freed <unclear>to some</unclear> extent. I think that <lb/>
     <hi rend="underline">I</hi> should enjoy a ride on that <unclear/> , with it <lb/> guarded by
     some of the gallant seventh. You spoke <lb/> of your feelings during the fight of <unclear/>
     <lb/> as being indescribable Perhaps they were similar <lb/> to mine when I first heard of the
     fight <lb/> Not knowing who were safe and who were not <lb/>
     <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0284"/> and also hearing that that idolized brother <lb/> had
     passed into the cold hands of death <lb/> you will not wonder that my feelings were <lb/> sad
     and voluntarily turned to Charlie <lb/> wondering if he too had entered that <lb/> narrow void.
     It was then <hi rend="underline">I again</hi> felt <lb/> that strange sensation mingled with
     <lb/> pity that I wrote you of when I first became <lb/> acquainted with you I was then <hi
      rend="underline">I really longed</hi>
     <lb/> to hear from you but did not have the pleasure <lb/> till last eve You wrote of sending a
     letter <lb/> after recieving mine which I did not recieve <lb/> Perhaps I will yet but do not
     think so <lb/> Charlie I wish I could collect my scattered <lb/> thoughts enough to write
     something worthy <lb/> your perusal. but that seems impossible <lb/> I wrote a letter to Hallie
     a few days <lb/> ago including a few lines to you do you <lb/> know whether he recieved it or
     not <lb/>
     <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0285"/> I sincerely hope you did. I read of the <lb/> fight in
     which Col. Lowe fell. Noble man <lb/> he died a cruel yet noble death It seems, when <lb/> I
     realize the privations of. war, cruel for our <lb/> (for our) brave youths to fall on the
     battle <lb/> field with no kind friend to sooth and <lb/> comfort them. But I would not sadden
     your <lb/> thoughts. If you were here would we not have <lb/> a nice <unclear/> ring? We miss
     Hal very much <lb/> when we <unclear/> round the old <unclear/>
     <lb/> while away the hours in music. He would <lb/> never give us any peace till <add
      place="inline" hand="h1">we</add> would play <lb/> and sing with him. Charlie I have a <lb/>
     sweet little friend here in Mecca <lb/> If it were not for her I would be very <lb/> lonesome
     indeed. We are <add hand="h1" place="inline">almost</add> constantly together <lb/> her name is
     Dora Leslie I wish you were <lb/> acquainted with her. She is gentle and <lb/> kind and still
     she is as perfect a piece <lb/>
     <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0286"/> of female vanity as I ever became <lb/> acquainted
     with. [W or Sh]e attends the same <lb/> school <unclear/> the same lesson and <lb/> occupy the
     same seat. In fact some <lb/> have intimated that our friendship <lb/> was more for the sake of
     her brother <lb/> and Hal than for each other <sic>(Ridicalous)</sic>
     <lb/> If Hal knew who told me so he would <lb/> laugh some. I saw Edwin Williams about <lb/>
     two weeks ago. he said when I wrote <lb/> to Hal to send word to Will. Braden <lb/> that he was
     well and would like to <lb/> see him. He wish <unclear/> very much to <lb/> go to war again but
     does not <unclear/>
     <lb/> health will permit him to do <lb/> so. Charlie what a <unclear>quiet</unclear> day this
     is <lb/> This morning it was <unclear/> warm and the <lb/> sun was shining so beautifully
      <unclear>but</unclear>
     <lb/> now <unclear> hardly </unclear>
     <lb/>
     <pb n="5" entity="DSSR_000000766_0287"/> clouds have gathered together and <lb/> completely
     obscured the sun. <unclear/> a slow <lb/> drizzling rain is falling as if nature <lb/> was
     shedding a few silent tears that <lb/> the summer is ended and the cold winter <lb/> is fast
     approaching. When the rain is <lb/> falling in torrents I always turn my <lb/> thoughts to the
     soldiers wondering when <lb/> and how they are I do <unclear/> you if you will <lb/> be obliged
     to camp out this winter <lb/> Charlie you know not how many silent <lb/> petitions have been
     sent to that high <lb/> throne for your safety and darling Hallie's <lb/> I sometimes wonder
     why life is so strange <lb/> and why I am <unclear> to </unclear> this <lb/> dull routine of
     life You may think that I <lb/> have strange feelings indeed I have at <lb/> times I know not
     for what I live. Do <lb/> I do any good in the world? I fear <lb/>
     <pb n="6" entity="DSSR_000000766_0288"/> not But what am I writing My thoughts <lb/> have been
     way down south in Ole Virginny <lb/> with Hal to day more than usual, <lb/> and I scarcely know
     what I write <lb/> Charlie are you <unclear>fasting</unclear> to day Dora <unclear/>
     <lb/> to ask you she says tell him Addie and <lb/> I are <unclear/> on green apples But I <lb/>
     guess you will be tired when you have <lb/> finished this nonsense give my love <lb/> to Hallie
     and Please write soon <lb/> and oblige me <lb/>
    </p>

    <p>Affectionately, Addie <unclear> Case <lb/> I am again </unclear> to tender my thanks <lb/>
     for the sketch of <unclear/> you <lb/> sent me. I prize it very highly </p>
    <closer> Addie </closer>
   </div1>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI.2>
