<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0269 SYSTEM "000000766_0269" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0270 SYSTEM "000000766_0270" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0271 SYSTEM "000000766_0271" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0272 SYSTEM "000000766_0272" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0273 SYSTEM "000000766_0273" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0274 SYSTEM "000000766_0274" NDATA jpg>


<!--<!ENTITY NA61f23a SYSTEM "NA61f23a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61f23b SYSTEM "NA61f23b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61f23c SYSTEM "NA61f23c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61f23d SYSTEM "NA61f23d.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61f23e SYSTEM "NA61f23e.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA61f23f SYSTEM "NA61f23f.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>
<TEI.2 id="NA61f23">
	<teiHeader type="migrated">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date
						value="1861-06-23">1861, June 23</date>.</title>
				<author>Case, Adelaide</author>
				<editor/>
				<respStmt>
					<resp/>
					<name/>
					<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
					<name>Jayme Schwartzberg, Electronic Text Center at the University of Virginia</name>
					<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
					<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
				<idno type="etext">NA61f23</idno>
				<idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
				<availability>
					<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
					<!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
					<p n="copyright"/>
				</availability>
				<date value="2001">2001</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<seriesStmt>
				<title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
				<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
				<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
			</seriesStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note>
					<p>Images have been included of the original source.</p>
				</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblFull>
					<titleStmt>
						<title>Nettleton Civil War Collection: Letter from Adelaide E. Case to
							Charles N. Tenney, 1861, June 23.</title>


						<author>Case, Adelaide</author>
						<editor/>
						<respStmt>
							<resp/>
							<name/>
						</respStmt>
					</titleStmt>
					<editionStmt>
						<p/>
					</editionStmt>
					<extent>unpublished letter</extent>
					<publicationStmt>
						<publisher/>
						<pubPlace/>
						<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr
							Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections,
							Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
					</publicationStmt>
					<seriesStmt>
						<p/>
					</seriesStmt>
					<notesStmt>
						<note/>
					</notesStmt>
				</biblFull>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p> </p>
				<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
					aid in establishing analytical groupings. </p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<p/>
			</refsDecl>

		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<creation>
				<date value="1861-06-23">1861-06-23</date>
			</creation>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="eng">English</language>
			</langUsage>
			<handList>
				<hand id="h1"/>
				<hand id="author"/>
				<hand id="unknown"/>
				<hand id="cataloger"/>
			</handList>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>nonfiction</term>
					<term>prose</term>
					<term>feminine</term>
					<term>American Civil War/Special Collections</term>
				</keywords>
				<keywords>
					<term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>

		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Corrector</resp>
					<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date value="2009-11-02">November 2nd, 2009</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>corrector</resp>
					<name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
					(uva-dl-tei).</item>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text id="d1">
		<body id="d2">

			<div1 type="letter" n="1861-06-23" id="d3">
				<pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0269"/>
				<head>Letter, June 23, 1861, from Adelaide E. Case to Charles Tenney</head>
				<opener>
					<dateline>
						<name type="place">Mecca</name>
						<date value="1861-06-23">June 23<hi rend="super">rd</hi>, /61</date>
					</dateline>
				</opener>

				<salute>Dear Friend</salute>
				<lb/>
				<p>After receiving your very<lb/> welcome letter last evening, I <unclear
						cert="decent">seal</unclear><lb/> myself to comply with your request<lb/> to
					write you. Your letter gave some<lb/> very plea<unclear cert="ok">sant</unclear>
					feelings and again it<lb/>
					<unclear/> some feelings amounting almost<lb/> to pain. because I thought there
					was<lb/> a little <unclear>consider</unclear>able,, of flattery <unclear
						cert="low">min-</unclear><lb/> gled with it. Perhaps if you had<lb/> been in
					the room when I read your<lb/> letter, you might have seen me<lb/> indulge a <hi
						rend="underline">very little</hi> in that<lb/> feminine weakness of
					blushing<lb/> for indeed I was surprised. There is always<lb/> some thing so
					disgusting to <unclear/> flattery<lb/> in any form and especially when it<lb/>
					<pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0270"/> from those that I wish to call by
					the<lb/> endering name of friend that for the<lb/> moment it creates within my
					heart a<lb/> strange sensation that is hard to conquer<lb/> I do not say this as
					a reproof. but that I<lb/> may be understood. you may not have meant<lb/> it for
					flattery but I took it as such,<lb/> so if you value my friendship please
					do<lb/> avoid flattery in every form towards me.<lb/>
				</p>
				<p>Although our acquaintance has been very<lb/> short it has been. to me, very
					pleasant. I shall<lb/> ever rem<add hand="h1" place="inline">em</add>ber with
					feelings of gratitude your<lb/> short visit at our home and I sincerely<lb/>
					hope that <hi rend="underline">sometime</hi> in the future it<lb/> will be
					repeated. Thus it is with life.<lb/> Today we form some agreeable and<orig
						reg="profitable">prof-<lb/> itable</orig> acquaintance that perchance
					tomorrow<lb/> may <unclear cert="ok">sever</unclear> forever. When I think of this<lb/>
					<unclear/> cast a gloom upon my feelings, that is<lb/>
					<pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0271"/> hard to dispel. I have sometimes
					thought<lb/> that I would form no more acquaintances. but<lb/> a desire for
					sympathy obliges me to succumb.<lb/>
				</p>
				<p>As I opened your<del hand="h1" rend="script">your</del> letter, my eye
					rested<lb/> upon the portrait of Col Elsworth. For a short<lb/> time I sat spell
					bound. and gazed with<lb/> admiration. then almost unconsciously I<lb/>
					exclamed.&mdash;Oh! that he should die. and such<lb/> a death. Cousin Jennie
					Case who was with<lb/> me immediately sprang to my side and<lb/> inquired what
					was the matter. thinking only<lb/> of my brother Hallie or Brig. but when I<lb/>
					showed her the portrait, she too was possessed<lb/> with the same feelings. Me
					dear friend<lb/> how shall I ever thank you for that<lb/> portrait. there was <hi
						rend="underline">nothing</hi> that I could<lb/> have wished for more. but
					let us turn<lb/> to something else.<lb/>
				</p>
				<p>You spoke in very glowing<lb/>
					<pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0272"/> terms of my borther. I can but thank
					you<lb/> for in my opinion he merits it all<lb/>
				</p>
				<p>You say that you dare not hope that I<lb/> think more of you than a common
					friend.<lb/> No, I do not. how could you expect me to,<lb/> to be sure there are
					those I have known for years<lb/> that I have no kinder feelings
						for <unclear>them</unclear><lb/> nor as kind as<add hand="h1" place="inline"
						>I have</add> for you and have denied<lb/> them the request that to you I
					granted<lb/> still I wish for no <unclear>nearer</unclear> tie <unclear/>
					outside<lb/> of my home. than a true and warm-<lb/> hearted friends. perhaps you
					will ask me<lb/> why it is if you do I will answer you.<lb/> You also ask if I
					have objections to our<lb/> changing ambrotypes? I most assuredly<lb/> have.
					That was one of the sentences which<lb/> gave me pain. You may think me a<lb/>
					<unclear>queer</unclear> girl&mdash;but I have several reasons<lb/> for
					refusing that request. one is this.<lb/>
					<pb n="5" entity="DSSR_000000766_0273"/> our acquaintance has been very
					short.<lb/> But do not think that I deem that<lb/> a sufficient reason. far from
					it. If you<lb/> had heard the low vulgar expressions I<lb/> once heard uttered
					by a youth while<lb/> gazing at a likeness of a pure minded<lb/> noble girl. you
					would not wonder that<lb/> I then made a vow to never let my<lb/> portrait go
					into the hands of a gentleman<lb/> when he was nothing more than a<lb/> common
					friend. Do not imagine that<lb/> I think you would be guilty of such a<lb/> base
					act. no. never If I did Addie would<lb/> be the wrong one to be writing to you
					now<lb/> But that vow is made and cannot be<lb/> broken. I think that where a
					gantleman<lb/> and lady are engaged, <hi rend="underline">then</hi> they
					should<lb/> change portraits. for then it is a sacred<lb/>
					<pb n="6" entity="DSSR_000000766_0274"/> gift but not till then. Now you
					have<lb/> my reasons in full In your letter you<lb/> spoke of that insurrection.
					and of your being<lb/> the second man in line. It would do no<lb/> good for me
					to praise you. but there was a<lb/> feeling of pride kindled in my bosom<lb/>
					when I read it. You asked if Laura knew<lb/> that you corresponded with me? Yes
					she does<lb/> there are but few things or secrets of mine<lb/> that she does not
					know. she sends her<lb/> respects to you and says tell him to<lb/> always do
					what he knows to be right. Is not<lb/> that godd advice? I understood that the
						7<hi rend="super">th</hi><lb/>
					<unclear/> had left Camp therefore I hardly<lb/> know where to send this. But my
					letter<lb/> is getting some what lengthy so I will<lb/> close with the request
					to write soon (what<lb/> a miserable pen this is) Yours in friendship<lb/>
				</p>
				<closer>
					<signed>Addie <unclear/> Case</signed>
				</closer>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
