<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0091 SYSTEM "000000766_0091" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0092 SYSTEM "000000766_0092" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0093 SYSTEM "000000766_0093" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0094 SYSTEM "000000766_0094" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62b25a SYSTEM "NA62b25a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b25b SYSTEM "NA62b25b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b25c SYSTEM "NA62b25c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b25d SYSTEM "NA62b25d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62b25">

 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-02-25"
      >Feb. 25th, 1862</date></title>

    <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>Kimberly A. Tryka, Virginia Center for Digital History</name>
     <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
     <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>Kimberly A. Tryka, Virginia Center for Digital History</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NA62b25</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                    <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton/</p>-->
                    <p n="copyright"/>
                </availability>
    <date value="2001">2001</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Page images have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, Feb. 25th, 1862</title>


      <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>4 pp.</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p/>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings.</p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>

  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1862-02-25">1862-02-25</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>feminine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Women Writers/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-06">November 6th, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2010-09-30">September 30, 2010</date>
    <respStmt>
     <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">

  <front id="d2">

   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>4 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1862-02-25">Feb. 25th, 1862</date>

      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p> Adelaide writes to Charles from Mecca. The letter is concerned with personal matters
     including her and Charles's health and comments about, and reactions to, information in
     previously exchanged letters. Persons mentioned in the letter include Hal (Hallie), Laurie, and
     Capt. Aspen.</p>
   </div1>

  </front>

  <body id="d4">



   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-02-25">Feb. 25th,
      1862</date></head>
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0091"/>


    <opener>
     <dateline><name type="place">Mecca</name><date value="1862-02-25">Feb. 25th 1862</date>.
     </dateline> My Darling </opener>

    <p> Again has my heart been<lb/> gladdened by one of your "angel visits" <unclear/><lb/>
     <unclear/> how very interesting my letters<lb/> must be. "Angel visits"! indeed, if<lb/> mine
     are such to you, wonder what<lb/> yours are to me. Well dear one, I am<lb/> gratified if they
     interest you for I<lb/> had thought myself incompetent.<lb/>
    </p>
    <p> You seem quite anxious as regards <hi rend="underline">my</hi><lb/> health, Do not be alarmed
     about me<lb/> dearest if I were not enjoying perfect health<lb/> I should inform you. It is
     quite natural<lb/> for me to wish to know the particulars<lb/>
     <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0092"/> about yours, for you ar not situated as<lb/> I am with
     kind friends around you, but<lb/> you are exposed to cold and hunger<lb/> as well as to the
     poisonous atmosphere<lb/> that must necessarily be when <orig reg="thousands">thous-<lb/>
     ands</orig> are breathing the same air. Therefore<lb/> please inform me in every letter
     about<lb/> your health. I trust you have recovered from<lb/> your cold that you spoke of.<lb/>
    </p>
    <p> Dearest "Yes" was the word you wished me to<lb/> say, and I have written it. If the <orig
      reg="talented">tallented</orig><lb/> and the gifted Charles Tenney can love and<lb/> accept of
     Adelaide's love welcome you are to it<lb/> and as regards my miniature, I presume<lb/> you
      have <abbr expan="received">recd</abbr> it <orig reg="before">ere</orig> this as I sent it<lb/>
     by Capt. Aspen. Preserve it my dearling, as<lb/> a sacred gift. There is nothing that I
     could<lb/> give you which could express my love for<lb/> you as fully as does that; and if
     you<lb/> prize it has as hightly as I do yours I wll<lb/> be more than repaid.<lb/>
    </p>
    <p> I am willing dear one to accept of you<lb/> just as you are a soldier and could not<lb/>
     <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0093"/> wish you other than you are. How happy I<lb/> am,
     loved one. If ever a woman enjoys perfect<lb/> happiness it is when<ref target="n1" n="1"
     >1</ref> she loves and knows she<lb/> is loved in return. It seems as if it was<lb/> too much
     happiness to last and that I must<lb/> yet find it all a dream. Darling Adeline will<lb/>
     strive in her poor way to make your life<lb/> happy. Oh, how I love so to dwell on these<lb/>
     dear thoughts, but I must turn to other<lb/> subjects<lb/>
    </p>
    <p> Darling, you did not intend to do me an<lb/> injustice di you when you asked me if I<lb/>
     was jealous of you? Surely you did not.<lb/> No, I am perfectly willing that you should<lb/>
     write to her when and what you please, and<lb/> should love to have you. She enjoys your<lb/>
      letters <hi rend="underline">very</hi> <hi rend="underline">very</hi> much, I thnk I know<lb/>
     the reason of that question. It was about<lb/> my "wry faces" was it not. When Laurie
     wrote<lb/> that little note of hers she told me she was<lb/> going to commence it with "Sister
     Charlie"<lb/> I laughingly told her if she did I would<lb/> not send it with mine hence her on
     "my faces"<lb/> which she wrote about. Thank Fortune that<lb/> ugly "green eyed monster" has no
     influence over<lb/> me. How unhappy I should be if I had<lb/> not confidence enough in one I
     love to allow<lb/> him to correspond with my sister. The idea<lb/>
     <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0094"/> is perfectly ridiculous so please dearest never<lb/>
     again allow such a thought to mar your happiness<lb/> for it certainly must make you
     unhappy.<lb/>
    </p>
    <p> Charlie, dearest, try to suppress your<lb/> ill will towards Col. <unclear/> will you
     not<lb/> at least while you are under his<lb/> authority. Please do. Perhaps Hallie was<lb/> in
     the wrong in writing these letters<lb/> although that seems almost impossible<lb/> but he ought
     to have been more careful<lb/> what he wrote. You will not seek revenge<lb/> for Hal's insults
     will you? He can not<lb/> wish you to. In the letter you wrote to<lb/> Laurie you said "the
      pen <unclear>is</unclear> mightier than<lb/> the sword" Dearest do not strive to prove it<lb/>
     for I fear if you do you will meet with<lb/> powerful opponents. Even if you do write
     under<lb/> a fictitous names are you not fearful of<lb/> your letters being intercepted?<lb/>
    </p>
    <p> Perhaps you will think me writing about that<lb/> which I ought not or which I have no
     interest<lb/> in. If so forgive me and I will do so<lb/> no more. But I have not time to
     write<lb/> . Write often dearest your letters<lb/> are <hi rend="underline">so</hi> welcome </p>





    <closer>
     <salute>meanwhile believe<lb/> me I remain yours forever<lb/></salute>
     <signed> Adelaide </signed>
    </closer>

   </div1>
  </body>

  <back id="d6">
   <div1 type="notes" n="1" id="d7">
    <head>Notes</head>
    <note id="n1" place="end" n="1">
     <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
     <p>This word is partially hidden by an ink blot.</p>
    </note>
   </div1>
  </back>

 </text>

</TEI.2>
