<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0143 SYSTEM "000000766_0143" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0144 SYSTEM "000000766_0144" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0145 SYSTEM "000000766_0145" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0146 SYSTEM "000000766_0146" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62e27a SYSTEM "NA62e27a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62e27b SYSTEM "NA62e27b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62e27c SYSTEM "NA62e27c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62e27d SYSTEM "NA62e27d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>
<TEI.2 id="NA62e27">
 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-05-27"
      >May 27<hi rend="super">th</hi>, 1862</date></title>

    <author>Case, Adelaide</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>Carrera de la Red, Anun. Universidad de Valladolid, Spain</name>
     <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
     <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>Carrera de la Red, Anun. Universidad de Valladolid, Spain</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library </publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NA62e27</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
    <date value="2001">2001 </date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Page images have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, May 27th, 1862</title>

      <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>4 pp.</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p> </p>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center. </p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings. </p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1862-05-27">1862-05-27 </date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>feminine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Women Writers/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-09">November 9th, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text id="d1">
  <front id="d2">
   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>4 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1862-05-27">May 27th,1862</date>

      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p> Writing during the break of one of her morning teaching sessions at Claridon, Addie
     expresses her pride at Charlie's noble achievements. She describes an encounter with Mr.
     Richardson at Mr. Armstrong's, whom she found "insolent." After school, she resumes her
     writing, in which she renews her request for a portrait of Charlie and relates to him her
     punishment of one of the boys for swearing. She made him read the commandment from the Bible
     (Exodus 20:7) against taking the Lord's name in vain, which had the intended effect. </p>
   </div1>
  </front>

  <body id="d4">
   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-05-27">May 27<hi rend="super">th</hi>,
     1862</date></head>
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0143"/>

    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <date value="1862-05-27">May 27<hi rend="super">th</hi><abbr expan="1862">'62</abbr>.
      Noon,</date>
     </dateline>
     <lb/>
     <salute>My darling <name type="recipient">Charlie</name>.<lb/>
     </salute>
    </opener>

    <p> I can not wait till night<lb/> before answering your darling letters. therefore will
     write<lb/> a little this noon, although I am so happy that<lb/> I can hardly contain my self.
     Yes darling you<lb/> have entered manhood. and I trust a bright and<lb/> happy future is
      before <hi rend="underline">us</hi>. Many thoughts I cast toward<lb/> Charlie on the 8<hi
      rend="super">th</hi> of May<seg type="postscript">"</seg> Loving thoughts darling. I<lb/> have
     a stronger claim on you now. have I not. for<lb/> now you are truly a man. But what have
     you<lb/> ever been to me but a true <hi rend="underline">noble</hi> <hi rend="underline"
     >minded</hi> man.<lb/> Yes darling you are right. Many <hi rend="underline">many</hi> sighs
     and<lb/> wishes<q>"that Charley was here"</q> has been wasted not<lb/> only on the morning
     breeze but evening breeze,<lb/> Charlie I must relate a little incident that<lb/> occured last
     friday eve. The soldiers<q>"Mite Society"</q><lb/> of <name type="geographic">Claridon</name>
     met at Mr. Armstrongs, and I<sic corr="was">went</sic><lb/>
     <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0144"/> becoming tired of the noise and gossip in the
     house<lb/> I rose and quickly went out of the room into<lb/> Mr. Leslie's intending to seek
     Dora. She had gone<lb/> out. and I went out in the cooling night air to<lb/> refresh myself. I
     passed on a few rods from the<lb/> house and strew myself down under an apple tree<lb/> with
     the exclamation<q>"I wish Charlie was here"</q><orig reg="immediately">Imme-<lb/>
     diately</orig> this answer came from behind me.<q>"And what<lb/> if Charlie were here,"</q> I
     sprang up with a cry of surprise<lb/> (not mingled with fear) for I did not know but<lb/>
     Charlie had really come. Upon looking round I saw a<lb/> tall form standing there as quietly as
     you please. I<lb/> know not what prompted me but I turned and<lb/>
     <hi rend="underline">flew</hi> into the house. Soon the gentleman came in<lb/> (I knew it was
     the one although I had not seen his<lb/> face) and was introduced as Mr Richardson, Upon<lb/>
     being introduced to me he spoke, and said.<q>"Miss Case<lb/> you did not wait for Charlie to
      come."</q><orig reg=".">,,</orig>
     <q>"No. nor<lb/> will I wait now"</q> I replied and arose, deeply mortified<lb/> and almost
     angry at the mans insolence and left the<lb/> room, I did not again enter the room, until<lb/>
     <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0145"/> Dora came after me and would not return without<lb/>
     me, Mr. R-- did<sic corr="not">not not</sic> notice me again during<lb/> the evening. for which
     I was thankful,, </p>

    <closer> But it is<lb/> time to close school dearest and for three hours.<salute>Addie<lb/> must
      bid you good bye.,,</salute>
    </closer>

   </div1>

   <div1 type="letter" n="2" id="d6">
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, After School <date value="1862-05-27"
      >May 27<hi rend="super">th</hi>, 1862</date></head>

    <opener>
     <dateline>After school.</dateline>
     <lb/>
     <salute>My darling.<seg type="postscript">"</seg></salute>
    </opener>

    <p> school has closed and I have again<lb/> read over your letters of the 9<hi rend="super"
     >th</hi> &amp; 11<hi rend="super">th</hi> Charlie, yours is a<lb/> noble spirit. just such
     as one as I would wish you to<lb/> have. You have<orig reg="suffered">suffured</orig>, dear, I
     know you have, yet with<lb/> me I would have you call on God to bless your<lb/> friends.
     Friends by blood, if nothing more, But darling<lb/> I know these words will but pain you
     therefore will<lb/> change the subject. How aspirant you are dearest. I<lb/> too feel that you
     will win laurels. Laurels that any<lb/> one would be forward to wear.<lb/>
    </p>

    <p> You ask do I ever get tired, and wish those children<lb/> would be quiet? Yes I often get
     tired, but as a general<lb/> thing my scholars are quite orderly. In fact as much<lb/> so as I
     could expect. I have two more scholars this<lb/> week and I can see they have been to<q>"my
      school"</q><lb/> You also ask if I have punished any yet. I have<lb/>
     <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0146"/> one scholar. John. Halderman. I accidentally
     heard<lb/> him swearing one day and called him in. and told<lb/> him he could remain with me
     after school.,, He<orig reg="seemed">seem-<lb/> ed</orig> pleased at the<q>"news"</q> as he
     called it; and remained<lb/> after the scholars had left. I went to my desk, tooke<lb/> out
      my<orig reg="Bible">Beibl</orig> turned to the 20<hi rend="super">th</hi> <abbr expan="Chapter"
      >Chap.</abbr> of Exodus 7<hi rend="super">th</hi> verse<lb/> and asked him to read it to me.
     He did so and burst<lb/> into tears.<q>"Teacher,"</q> said he<q>"I have always been flogged
      for<lb/> swearing but it never hurt me so bad as this punishment<lb/> I will swear no more
      this summer,"</q> Charlie I was not ashamed<lb/> of the tears that fell and mingled with his.
     He afterward<lb/> told me that he expected I would try to whip him and<lb/> he did not intend
     to let me. He is fourteen years of<lb/> age, I think. I have not a better scholar in school
     than he<lb/> has since been. Dont you admire my government?<lb/> How very kind Mr <hi
      rend="underline">s</hi> Ostorm was to you darling. I shall<lb/> ever bless her for that act.
     Hers, must be a noble<lb/> heart, and her son too, is he as good as his mother?<lb/>
    </p>

    <p> You noticed my request in regard to your portrait<lb/> and ask me what size I wish. I am not
     particular<lb/> any size to suit yourself I want a perfect one just as<lb/> me. I quickly
     recognized our native<q>"blue belles"</q> and<q>"Violets"</q><lb/> but they were never the less
     thankfully received because<lb/>
     <sic corr="they">the</sic> were like our own loved flowers, for did not <hi rend="underline"
      >Charlie</hi><lb/> send them to me, and are they not a lovely token of the<lb/> love
      he <unclear reason="corrected">bo**s</unclear> me?<lb/>
    </p>

    <p> I have just read over the letter I wrote you yesterday.<lb/> and this morning. and have some
     scruples about sending<lb/> it. I do not know what caused me to write as I did<lb/> but my
     brain was sadly perplexed and I wrote the<lb/> thoughts that came from my heart. Just so I
     should<lb/> have felt all day had I not <orig reg="received">recieved</orig> your letters
     this<lb/> morning; But darling I must go or I shall lose my<lb/> supper. </p>

    <closer>
     <salute>Write real often darling to your own -</salute>
     <lb/>
     <signed>
      <name type="sender">Addie</name>
     </signed>
     <lb/>
     <seg type="postscript">I may just as well send Dora's love for she would were she here</seg>
     <lb/>
     <signed>
      <name type="sender">Addie</name>
     </signed>
     <lb/>
    </closer>
   </div1>

  </body>


 </text>
</TEI.2>
