<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0071 SYSTEM "000000766_0071" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0072 SYSTEM "000000766_0072" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0073 SYSTEM "000000766_0073" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0074 SYSTEM "000000766_0074" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0075 SYSTEM "000000766_0075" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0076 SYSTEM "000000766_0076" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0077 SYSTEM "000000766_0077" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0078 SYSTEM "000000766_0078" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62b11a SYSTEM "NA62b11a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b11b SYSTEM "NA62b11b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b11c SYSTEM "NA62b11c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b11d SYSTEM "NA62b11d.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b11e SYSTEM "NA62b11e.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b11f SYSTEM "NA62b11f.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b11g SYSTEM "NA62b11g.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b11h SYSTEM "NA62b11h.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62b11">
    <teiHeader type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date
                        value="1862-02-11">February 11th, 1862</date></title>

                <author>Case, Adlaide E.</author>
                <editor/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Linda Lisanti; Nadine Ellero</name>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">19</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="etext">NA62b11</idno>
                <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                    <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton/</p>-->
                    <p n="copyright"/>
                </availability>
                <date value="2001">2001</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Page images have been included from the original source.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, February 11th,
                            1862</title>


                        <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
                        <editor/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>8 pp.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                        <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: UVA Special Collectiions</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </seriesStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p/>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
                <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
                    aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1862-02-11">1862-02-11</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <handList>
                <hand id="h1"/>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>nonfiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>feminine</term>
                    <term>American Civil War/Women Writers/Special Collections</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2009-11-03">November 3rd, 2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
                    (uva-dl-tei).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2010-09-30">September 30, 2010</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">
        <front id="d2">
            <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
                <head>
                    <bibl>
                        <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                        <extent> 8pp.</extent>
                        <date value="1862-02-11">February 2, 1862</date>

                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenny</title>
                    </bibl>
                </head>
                <p>Adelaide writes to Charlie describing her thoughts concerning the frequency of
                    their correspondence, her readiness for marriage, her feelings of affection for
                    him and his being at war(the Battle on the Potomac). </p>
            </div1>

        </front>

        <body id="d4">



            <div1 type="letter" n="1862-02-11" id="d5">
                <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-02-11"
                        >February 11th, 1862</date></head>

                <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0071"/>
                <opener>

                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">Mecca</name>
                        <date value="1862-02-11"> February 11<hi rend="super">th</hi>1862</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                    <salute>Dearest Charlie</salute>
                </opener>


                <p> I guess you will not complain<lb/> because I do not write often enough. for
                    I<lb/> have sent you a letter every<q>"mail day"</q> for a<lb/> good while. But
                    I go upon the principle<lb/> that the oftener I write the oftener I<lb/> recieve
                    and therefore I shall write real often<lb/></p>

                <p>How happy I was last night when I rec'd.<lb/> you darling letters of the 2<hi
                        rend="super">nd</hi> and 3<hi rend="super">rd</hi> I<lb/> recieved two from
                    you friday and did not<lb/> expect to recieve another so soon. I thought<lb/> I
                    should not go to the office last night<lb/> for it was quite muddy but
                    something-I<lb/> can call it nothing but instinct-seemed to<lb/> tell me to go..
                    I went and my heart was<lb/>
                    <unclear>gladdened</unclear>. I am sure I can not tell what<lb/> part of your
                    letters interest me most<lb/> for they are so full of interest that it is<lb/>
                    <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0072"/> difficult finding the most
                    interesting<lb/> part. I was pleased with your<q>"Diary letter"</q><lb/> It is
                    so different from what you generally<lb/> write, but it was Charlie's letter
                    after all.<lb/> I sympathize with you in the loss of Gen. Lander<lb/> but I hope
                    your new Gen will <unclear>
                        <del hand="h1">supply</del>
                    </unclear><del hand="h1">his</del>prove<lb/> himself as worthy as did Gen.
                    Leander. I<lb/> believe Banks and Shields take his place<lb/> do they not? I
                    read in the Cleveland<lb/> Leader that they did but the<q>"Leader"</q>
                    gives<lb/> us so many wrong reports that I can<lb/> not believe any thing that
                    they print<lb/> unless it is authenticated in some<lb/> other direction.
                    Darling, I can not think<lb/> of the battle that <hi rend="underline">must</hi>
                    be fought on the<lb/> Potomac, without a shudder, and my heart<lb/> clings
                    closer to my idol. <hi rend="underline">Would to God</hi><lb/> that that battle
                    would be avoided. Surgeons<lb/> are preparing to go to Washington, from all<lb/>
                    parts of the country.<lb/>
                </p>

                <p>I am <hi rend="underline">so</hi> thankful that you enjoy good<lb/>
                    <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0073"/> health, and I am glad that you are
                    so<lb/> punctual in informing me.<lb/>
                </p>

                <p>Darling, I do not think Hal would wish you<lb/> to <unclear>insure</unclear> your
                    own safety for his<sic corr="sake">sak</sic>.<lb/> Charlie, how
                        your<q>"question"</q> startled me. I can not<lb/> tell you. I had not cast a
                        thought <unclear>to avoid</unclear><lb/> changing my name to the the one you
                    have at<lb/> present. I had been so happy in your love<lb/> that I had thought
                        of<orig reg="nothing">nothink</orig> beyond<lb/> No Charlie, I must maintain
                    the simple<lb/> name of Addie <unclear>Le</unclear> Case until I am someting<lb/>
                    wiser, something better than I now am.<lb/> I have aspirations that <hi
                        rend="underline">must</hi> be reached<lb/> before I bear another name than
                    this<lb/>
                </p>

                <p>I wish to make myself worthy of you<lb/> my darling, before I am wholy
                    yours.<lb/> and your love will strengthen me.<lb/> Be content dearest at
                    present, and<lb/> remember that it is for the best<lb/> for I could never bestow
                    my hand<lb/> upon you now. My heart is already<lb/>
                    <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0074"/> yours and even will be, but my<lb/>
                        hand <hi rend="underline">may</hi> not be for years. It may<lb/> seem a hard
                    request to grant when I ask<lb/> you to not mention this again until I<lb/> do,
                    but you <hi rend="underline">will</hi> grant it will you not<lb/> my own
                        Charlie<unclear>!</unclear> Does it seem a long time<lb/> Charlie? Perhaps
                    it does, but would you not<lb/> rather wait a few years till I have a
                    chance<lb/> to cultivate the gifts God has given me<lb/> than to find but too
                    late that you have<lb/> taken to your heart an unworthy object?<lb/>
                </p>

                <p>Consider this darling, and answer me,<lb/> Hallie too, my own darling brother
                    wishes me<lb/> to become a woman in mind as well as<lb/> in body before I can
                    marry, and could<lb/> I refuse a request from him<unclear>!</unclear> He considers<lb/>
                    <hi rend="underline">you</hi> worthy one of the noblest of women<lb/> and <hi
                        rend="underline">God in Heaven helping me I will<lb/> be that one.</hi> You
                    asked me if father<lb/> knew of our<q>"carrying on"</q> He does not<lb/> He
                    always said that his daughters would<lb/> never recieve his dictation in
                    choosing a<lb/> companion, a queer person is my papa<lb/> He seems to think his
                    children capable of<lb/> choosing for themselves. Perhaps he is right<lb/>
                    <pb n="5" entity="DSSR_000000766_0075"/> Did you ever see a more lovely day
                    than<lb/> this one is. It is so warm and pleasant.<lb/> I can scarcely content
                    remaining in<lb/> the house. Not a cloud is to be seen and<lb/> the sunshine is
                    dashing through the windows<lb/> so brightly it is such a contrast so the<lb/>
                    fire which seems feebly burning but auntie<lb/> says it is burning real good and
                    above<lb/> all the birds - Earth's first and beautiful<lb/> poets are singing so
                    sweetly. I imagine they<lb/> are singing just as sweet songs now as<lb/> birds
                    sang to Adam and Eve when<lb/> were in the garden of Eden before that<lb/> one
                    great sin deprived them forever<del hand="h1">from</del><lb/> of their
                    happiness. How does Gen. Moore<lb/> get along. I shall never forget his call
                    to<lb/> our house and my questions I asked him<lb/> of you. I tried to appear
                    disinterested when<lb/> talking about you, but his honest blue<lb/>
                    <pb n="6" entity="DSSR_000000766_0076"/> eyes which look right into mine<lb/>
                    just as if he knew I was doing<lb/> myself an injustice as well as you.<lb/> He
                    knew that we corresponded with each<lb/> other when he was here. I have a
                    curiosity<lb/> to know whether that<q>"look"</q> is natural with<lb/> him or
                    not.<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>Dear Charlie I have been thinking today<lb/> of the visit which you made at our
                    house<lb/> how sad you must have felt when you saw<lb/> Laurie and I caressing
                    brother and thought<lb/> you too had a sister, but her caresses were<lb/> denied
                    you. If I had then known of your<lb/> sister nothing in the world would
                    have<lb/> separated us to express my joy so warmly<lb/> in your presence. I
                    could not have pursued<lb/> your noble heart so much as my actions<lb/>
                    undoubtedly did. But if you were only here<lb/> would not I supply the place of
                    that absent<lb/> sister. Will you not tell me more about<lb/> her. Does she
                    resemble you? She certainly<lb/>
                    <pb n="7" entity="DSSR_000000766_0077"/> loves you dear one, who could help
                    it.<lb/> I do wish you could get her to write<lb/> to you. The thought just
                    presented<lb/> itself that perhaps this thought would<lb/> not be agreeable to
                    you and<add place="inline" hand="h1">I</add> am now<lb/> doing just what I would
                    not do for<lb/> any thing - praising you. If I am darling<lb/> forgive me. But
                    for fear that I may say<lb/> something which I ought not so I will change<lb/>
                    the subject.<lb/>
                </p>
                <p><unclear>Hallis</unclear> is in Warren yet, he came home<lb/> last friday and
                    stayed over night but<lb/> went away in the morning. How I<lb/> should loved to
                    have had him stay<lb/> over the sabbath but when I urged<lb/> him to stay he
                    looked at me with<lb/> his great black eyes and said "Addie<lb/> can you ask me
                    to stay when you<lb/> know that duty calls me away?"<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>I urged him no more to stay but<lb/> told him to go. What a power my brother<lb/>
                    <pb n="8" entity="DSSR_000000766_0078"/> has over his sister. One
                    reproachful<lb/> look from him will bring the tears<lb/> to my eyes and such a
                    heavy pain will<lb/> gather round my heart that will never<lb/> leave me till I
                    know that I am forgiven<lb/> for the offense that brought that look.<lb/> Just
                    such a power I feel and <hi rend="underline">know </hi><lb/> my Charlie has over
                    me. I can feel it<lb/> when I read your letters and I know<lb/> it is with me in
                    every action.<lb/></p>
                <p>Thus it is with this I truly love<lb/> and the deeper my love is
                    for <unclear>my</unclear> and<lb/> the more strongly do I feel that proven.<lb/></p>
                <p>But what a letter I am writing you<lb/> to day. I sat down and let my
                    strengths<lb/> go just as fast and about as curious<lb/> as that<q>"about"</q>
                    is. But I guess<lb/> you will not find time to read this hurried<lb/>
                    <q>"thing"</q> if I do not cease.<lb/></p>
                <p>Do not fail to write often dearest. If,<lb/> more than two mail days pass with
                    out hearing<lb/> from you the<q>"Blues"</q> get hold of me most<lb/>
                    unmercifully and no relief can I find<lb/> until I receive a letter from
                    you.<lb/></p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>I guess it is unecessary for me to sign<lb/> my name to this for it you
                        do not recognize your Adelaide's writing send it back.<lb/></salute>

                </closer>
            </div1>
        </body>


    </text>
</TEI.2>
