<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0087 SYSTEM "000000766_0087" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0088 SYSTEM "000000766_0088" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0089 SYSTEM "000000766_0089" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0090 SYSTEM "000000766_0090" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62b23a SYSTEM "NA62b23a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b23b SYSTEM "NA62b23b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b23c SYSTEM "NA62b23c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b23d SYSTEM "NA62b23d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62b23">

    <teiHeader type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date
                        value="1862-02-23">February 23rd, 1862</date></title>
                <title n="240"/>

                <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
                <editor/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Sara B. Weber, University of Notre Dame/RBS 23-27 2001</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Sara B. Weber, University of Notre Dame/RBS 23-27 2001</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">18</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="etext">NA62b23</idno>
                <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                    <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton/</p>-->
                    <p n="copyright"/>
                </availability>
                <date value="2001">2001</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Page images have been included from the original source.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, February 23rd,
                            1862</title>


                        <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
                        <editor/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>4 pp.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                        <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr
                            Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections,
                            Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </seriesStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p/>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
                <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
                    aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p/>
            </refsDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1862-02-23">1862-02-23</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <handList>
                <hand id="h1"/>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>nonfiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>feminine</term>
                    <term>American Civil War/Women Writers/Special Collections</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2009-11-06">November 6th, 2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
                    (uva-dl-tei).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2010-09-30">September 30, 2010</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">

        <front id="d2">
            <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
                <head>
                    <bibl>
                        <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                        <extent>4 pp.</extent>
                        <date value="1862-02-23">February 23<hi rend="super">rd</hi>, 1862</date>

                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney</title>
                    </bibl>
                </head>
                <p> Addie first describes her worry when there is no letter from Charlie, and her
                    joy when one arrives. She then explains that the George family of singers is
                    visiting Mecca, and the two daughters, Jesse and Mollie, are staying with
                    Addie's family. She names two song sung by the girls, "The Sword of Bunker Hill"
                    and "Union for ever for me!", and describes the effect of the performaces on
                    herself. Addie then responds to Charlie's tale of his personal history in his
                    most recent letter to her, and describes the changes in her own emotions towards
                    him, from sisterly love to true love for a "noble pure and high minded man." The
                    letter indicates that her brother Hal is home on furlough, for he teases her
                    about a possible visit from Charlie. </p>
            </div1>
        </front>

        <body id="d4">



            <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
                <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-02-23"
                        >February 23rd, 1862</date></head>
                <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0087"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">Mecca</name>
                        <date value="1862-02-23">Feb. 23<hi rend="super">rd</hi>/'62</date>
                    </dateline>

                </opener>
                <p> A welcome letter was <unclear>there</unclear><lb/> dearest brought by fridays's
                    mail<lb/> It had been long and earnestly<lb/> looked for by anxious and,
                    sometime<lb/> tearful eyes, I could not refrain<lb/> from thinking,
                        pretty <unclear>loud</unclear>, Heart!<lb/> welcome messenger of love,
                    when<lb/> it was handed, <add hand="h1" place="inline">me</add> I must
                    tell<lb/> you how or rather what a joyful<lb/> disappointment,
                        it <unclear>produced</unclear><lb/>
                </p>

                <p> The donation. that I spoke of in<lb/>
                    <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0088"/> my last "came
                    off". <unclear>Laurie</unclear><lb/> went over in the afternoon<lb/> and I waited
                    till evening.<lb/> The first place that I went<lb/> was to the office, which
                    is<lb/> under the Hall. where the<lb/> donation was held. I inquired<lb/> if
                    there was any mail for<lb/> me. <hi rend="underline">None, replied the
                    postmaster</hi><lb/> I presume I looked -- guess how<lb/> "Oh: you must not put
                    on such<lb/> a 'solemncholy' face, replied he<lb/> Well dear Charlie, I had
                    to<lb/> put forth all the resolutions which<lb/> I was capable of, to keep
                    back<lb/> the tears, presently Laurie came<lb/> down stairs with our stretched
                    hand<lb/> and <unclear>guess</unclear> I <unclear>presumed</unclear>, dont
                    you<lb/>
                </p>
                <p> Dearest, I am stealing these few<lb/> moments, but I <unclear>could</unclear> not
                    help<lb/> it we have company here<lb/>
                    <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0089"/> passing the sabbath. The<lb/> "George
                    family" consisting of<lb/> Mr. George and wife, and two<lb/> daughters have been
                    giving some<lb/> grand vocal concerts here in<lb/> Mecca, and the young
                    ladies<lb/> are staying with us. They are<lb/> sweet little<del hand="h1"
                    >s</del> girls. Misses <unclear>Jess</unclear>. <add place="inline" hand="h1"
                            >or <unclear>Jessey</unclear></add> and<lb/> Mollie. Jesse is a petite
                    little<lb/> thing, about four feet high and<lb/> very near my. Mollie is<lb/>
                    younger, Oh Charlie, if you could<lb/> but hear them sing, It raises<lb/> me up.
                    away off. I dont know<lb/> where Jesse sang, 'The Union<lb/> Forever, for
                        me"<ref target="n1" n="1">1</ref> last night. The<lb/> folds of their
                    magnificent flag<lb/> fell as graceful over her little<lb/> form. as you could
                    wish. They sang<lb/> 'The Sword of Bunker Hill"<ref target="n2" n="2">2</ref>
                    also,<lb/> I had heard<del hand="h1">of</del> it sung before<lb/>
                    <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0090"/> but never with such thrilling<lb/>
                    sweetness Hal says I am a perfect<lb/>
                    <unclear>enthusiast</unclear> when I hear music<ref target="n3" n="3">3</ref>.
                    but who<lb/> could help having this enthusiasm<lb/> rise, while listening to
                    sweet music<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>But I must not let the "George<lb/> family" fill up my letter. Dearest what<lb/>
                    a history you gave of yourself in your<lb/> last. It was <add place="inline"
                        hand="h1">as</add> unexpected as it was strange<lb/> and sorrowfull. I know
                    that I never<lb/> have spoken to you about it and what<lb/> is more <hi
                        rend="underline">I</hi> <hi rend="underline">never</hi> would unless you<lb/>
                    introduced the subject I felt no<lb/> anxiety what ever in regard to your
                    past<lb/> life. I had given you my confidence<lb/> first as a friend. I next <hi
                        rend="underline">tried</hi> to give<lb/> it as a sister, but luckily or
                    unluckily<lb/> or not. the future will tell, - failed.<lb/> and now I give it to
                    you as a true<lb/> pure hearted and youthful maiden<lb/> would give to a noble
                    pure and<lb/> high minded man, I give it you now<lb/> as a sacred gift not
                    scrupulously. but<lb/> freely <add place="inline" hand="h1"> &amp;</add>
                    with out a doubt. I surely can<lb/> not rejoice in your sorrow dearest and<lb/>
                    yet I sometimes am glad that you<lb/> tasted its bitterness It seems<lb/> as if
                    one could sympathis in an others<lb/> sorrows more earnestly when they
                    themselves<lb/> have drunk the <unclear>draughts</unclear>. but how selfish<lb/>
                    I am. Forgive me darling for such thoughts<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>I am sorry that Col. Tyler is so much disliked<lb/> in his Regt. It must be very
                    unpleasant<lb/> for him to remain when he has not the<lb/> confidence of his men
                    I am so sorry<lb/> that that ugly little quarrel arose between<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>the Col, and Hallie but I can not help it. If I had been with you when you<lb/>
                    wrote of your becoming a commissioned officer I presume I should have
                    responded<lb/> ha, ha, ha!<lb/> Thanks you<lb/> dear one<lb/> for your<lb/>
                    "sketchey'<lb/> gift I<lb/> can best<lb/> thank you<lb/>
                    <unclear>?</unclear> but<lb/> hope to<lb/> see the time<lb/> when I can<lb/>
                    show my<lb/> gratitude<lb/> in a more<lb/> beneficial<lb/> way, Hallie<lb/> was
                    looking<lb/> at your<lb/> portrait a<lb/> little while<lb/> ago and<lb/> wishing
                    you<lb/> were here.<lb/> He said<lb/> you would<lb/> be a very welcome<lb/>
                    visitor &amp; he<lb/> would feel as if you<del hand="h1">came</del><lb/>
                </p>

                <p>
                    <ref target="n4" n="4">4</ref>came<lb/> expressly to see him that is if some
                    one<lb/> else were not here giving a sly look at one<lb/>
                </p>
                <p> The girls laughed (for I am right in the room<lb/> with them Jess would not let
                    me go out)<lb/> and they<lb/> looked at<lb/> me too<lb/> Presume<lb/> I
                    blushed<lb/> for Hal. said "Dont you wish Charlie was<lb/> here to see the
                    roses" naughty boy is<lb/> he not? that is some times. How ambitious<lb/> you
                    are dear Charlie, I fear I would<lb/> rather remain dormant than trust to<lb/>
                    chances in a battle but our<lb/> natures are different in that respect<lb/>
                </p>

                <closer> But I can write but little more<lb/> as Mollie says she will be
                    compelled<lb/> to go to sleep if I do not stop writing<lb/> Wonder if it <hi
                        rend="underline">is</hi> so dull with out<lb/> me. " <hi rend="underline"
                        >Dont I feel flattered</hi>" Write often<lb/> very often dearest to cheer your<lb/>
                    <signed>Addie</signed><lb/>
                    <seg type="postscript">Please excuse this writing and<lb/> composition</seg> For
                    Charlie </closer>
            </div1>
        </body>

        <back id="d6">

            <div1 type="notes" n="1" id="d7">
                <head>Notes</head>

                <note id="n1" place="end" n="1"><seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
                    <p>"Union for ever for me!" is a 1861 song, written and composed for Miss Ada
                        Webb by William Shakespeare Hays (1837-1907). See the lyrics online atthe
                        Public Domain Music website or atthe Library of Congress's "America Singing:
                        Nineteenth-Century Song Sheets" website - this song is the second to last
                        link on the Library of Congress page. The Public Domain Music website also
                        has a MIDI of this song.</p>
                </note>

                <note id="n2" place="end" n="2"><seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
                    <p>"The Sword of Bunker Hill" is a 1855 song, written by William Ross Wallace
                        with music by Bernard Covert. The song tells of a veteran of the American
                        Revolutionary War on his deathbed giving his son the sword he took from a
                        British captain. See the lyrics online atthe Public Domain Music Web site or
                        at the Library of Congress's Web site - this song is the third link from the
                        top on the Library of Congress page. The Public Domain Music website also
                        has a MIDI of this song.</p>
                </note>

                <note id="n3" place="end" n="3"><seg type="note-symbol">3</seg>
                    <p> In researching the above two songs, it was discovered that the letterhead
                        illustration used on some of the other letters appears to have been copied
                        fromother sheet music of the period.</p>
                </note>
                <note id="n4" place="end" n="4"><seg type="note-symbol">4</seg>
                    <p>The following is written perpendicularly across page 1</p>
                </note>

            </div1>
        </back>

    </text>

</TEI.2>
