<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0163 SYSTEM "000000766_0163" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0164 SYSTEM "000000766_0164" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0165 SYSTEM "000000766_0165" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0166 SYSTEM "000000766_0166" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62g02a SYSTEM "NA62g02a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62g02b SYSTEM "NA62g02b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62g02c SYSTEM "NA62g02c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62g02d SYSTEM "NA62g02d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62g02">

    <teiHeader type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date
                        value="1862-07-02">July 2, 1862</date></title>

                <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
                <editor/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Lynn M. Fahy</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Lynn M. Fahy</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="etext">NA62g02</idno>
                <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                    <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
                    <p n="copyright"/>
                </availability>
                <date value="2004">2004</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney,</title>
                        <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>4 pp.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                        <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr
                            Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections,
                            Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </seriesStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p/>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
                <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
                    aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p/>
            </refsDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1862-07-02">1862-07-02</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <handList>
                <hand id="h1"/>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>nonfiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>feminine</term>
                    <term>American Civil War/Women Writers/Special Collections</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2009-11-09">November 9th, 2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
                    (uva-dl-tei).</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">

        <front id="d2">

            <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
                <head>
                    <bibl>
                        <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                        <extent>4 pp.</extent>
                        <date value="1862-07-02">July 2, 1862</date>
                        <date value="1862-07-03">July 3, 1862</date>

                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney</title>
                    </bibl>
                </head>

                <p> Addie writes to Charlie on July 2nd about conflicting reports in the newspaper
                    that Richmond had fallen or was again Uncle Sam's. She wishes for peace to be
                    declared on "that memorable day," the 4th. Her letter writing, which was
                    interrupted by the coming of her scholars, continues on July 3rd. Addie has
                    heard "that desperate fighting was going on at Richmond. that 1200 of our brave
                    men were already lying cold and insensible on the field", yet she yearns to be
                    with him. </p>

            </div1>

        </front>

        <body id="d4">

            <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
                <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-07-02"
                        >July 2, 1862</date></head>
                <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0163"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">East Claridon</name>
                        <date value="1862-07-02">July 2<hi rend="super">nd</hi> 1862</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My darling,</salute>
                </opener>

                <p> If I thought there<lb/> was so much happiness for me as the<lb/> probability of
                    soon seeing my loved Charlie<lb/> I would not write this morning but<lb/> as
                    every thing generally goes contrary to<lb/> our wishes and expectations. I doubt
                    not<lb/> but that such will prove to be the case<lb/> now. I do not know why I
                    had so<lb/> anxiously waited and looked for your<lb/> return, this 4<hi
                        rend="super">th</hi> but as the drowning man<lb/> catches at a straw. I
                    clung to the<lb/> little encouragement. Lieut <unclear>Brisvine</unclear>
                    gave<lb/> you. and even now I shudder at the<lb/> thought of abandoning that
                    hope.<lb/> There is scarcely a day but that I hear<lb/> of some soldier coming
                    home to meet his<lb/> friends, and when I think of Charlie<lb/>
                    <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0164"/> so long absent. I find myself
                    fervently<lb/> wishing that others were obliged to stay away<lb/> as long as he.
                    I know it is a cruel<lb/> wicked wish. but it is perfectly natural<lb/> for
                    human beings to wish for someone<lb/> to share their trials as well as
                    their<lb/> joys or at least to sympathize with<lb/> them and when I see others
                    so happy<lb/> because a dear friend has returned from<lb/> from the wars, I
                    wonder why such<lb/> happiness is given to some and denied<lb/> to others. You
                    will call me an "ungrate-<lb/> ful little minx" as Hallie says. but<lb/> refer
                    the case to yourself. Look way down<lb/> in the naughty corners. (If you
                    have<lb/> such) of your heart and if you do not<lb/> find just such rebellious
                    thoughts,<lb/> striving so hard to get the control. then<lb/> call me a poor
                    judge. But you will<lb/> say I am arguing both sides will you<lb/> not?</p>

                <p>I am<q>dying to hear</q> the news in<lb/>
                    <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0165"/> yesterdays paper. The report in
                    mondays<lb/> paper was that Richmond had fallen.<lb/> or --risen. I guess the
                    latter. at least that<lb/> Uncle Sam had/has it again. and I wish<lb/> so much
                    to have it confirmed. I can<lb/> hardly wait to hear, Would that peace<lb/>
                    could be declared the fourth. would<lb/> not that memorable day be doubly
                    dear?<lb/> Dear Charlie. my scholars are coming and<lb/> making such a noise
                    that I must cease<lb/> writing for the present. </p>

                <closer>
                    <salute>Accept the love<lb/> and blessings of your Addie</salute>
                </closer>
            </div1>

            <div1 type="letter" n="2" id="d6">
                <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, No Date</head>


                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <date value="1862-07-03">July 3<hi rend="super">rd</hi></date>
                    </dateline>
                    <lb/>
                    <salute>My darling:</salute>
                </opener>

                <p>Conflicting emotions<lb/> are now raging in my heart. Last<lb/> night I heard
                        the<del hand="h1">m</del> news. that desperate<lb/> fighting was going on at
                    Richmond.<lb/> that 1200 of our brave men were already<lb/> lying cold and
                    insensible upon the field<lb/> and what is worse. not an inch has<lb/> been
                    gained, For a few days dearest. I<lb/> have lost all knowledge of your
                    position<lb/> and who knows. oh heaven forbid. but<lb/>
                    <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0166"/> that you are there sharing the
                    perils<lb/> of the battle field. Oh. Charlie. why<lb/> does cruel fate thus
                    separate us.<lb/> Why are you so far away. suffering often<lb/> for want of the
                    comforts of life. alone<lb/> while I can remain at home in<lb/> security
                    surrounded by kind friends<lb/> all striving to make my life a happy<lb/> one.
                    but dearest I am far from happy this<lb/> morning. Could I but be with you.
                    even<lb/> on the dreaded battle field. I should be<lb/> happier than now. Bitter
                    very bitter are<lb/> my feelings this morning. darling. but<lb/> I can not
                    control them. I am not fit<lb/> to discharge the duties lying before me to-<lb/>
                    day. for I have no control o<unclear>v</unclear>er my feelings<lb/> whatever. If
                    there would but come a shower<lb/> thunder. lightning and rain mingle
                    together<lb/> in one great storm and commotion. I should<lb/> feel better. but
                    the sun shines just as bright<lb/> the birds sing just as sweetly and all
                    nature<lb/> is just as gay as if no pitiless war was<lb/> raging over our land
                    leaving desolate hearths<lb/> sobbing children and broken hearted wives.<lb/> in
                    all parts of the <sic corr="United">Unitid</sic> states. It<lb/> seems so like
                    mockery. this beautiful<lb/> morn. when my poor heart aches so hard<lb/> But
                    these fears may be all unfounded<lb/> and you may laugh--no you will never<lb/>
                    do that dearest.- but if they are unfounded<lb/> I thank God for it. But dear, I
                    must<lb/> close as it is near school time.</p>

                <closer>
                    <salute>Trusting in the guardianship of a<lb/> wise and good Savior I remain
                        ever</salute>
                    <signed>Your Addie</signed>
                </closer>

            </div1>

        </body>


    </text>

</TEI.2>
