<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0043 SYSTEM "000000766_0043" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0044 SYSTEM "000000766_0044" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0045 SYSTEM "000000766_0045" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0046 SYSTEM "000000766_0046" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY N620909a SYSTEM "620909a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY N620909b SYSTEM "620909b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY N620909c SYSTEM "620909c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY N620909d SYSTEM "620909d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>
<TEI.2 id="NA62a26">
    <teiHeader type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date
                        value="1862-01-26">26 January 1862</date></title>

                <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
                <editor/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Heather L. Horechny</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Heather L. Horechny, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text
                        Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="etext">NA62a26</idno>
                <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                    <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton/</p>-->
                    <p n="copyright"/>
                </availability>
                <date value="2000">2000</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Page images have been included from the original source.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 26 January 1862</title>


                        <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
                        <editor/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>4 p.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                        <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr
                            Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections,
                            Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </seriesStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p/>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
                <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
                    aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1862-01-26">1862-01-26</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <handList>
                <hand id="h1"/>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>nonfiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>feminine</term>
                    <term>American Civil War; Women Writers; Special Collections</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2009-11-03">November 3rd, 2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
                    (uva-dl-tei).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2010-09-30">September 30, 2010</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">

        <body id="d2">
            <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
                <head>
                    <bibl>
                        <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                        <extent>4 pp.</extent>
                        <date value="1862-01-26"/>

                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles Tenney</title>
                    </bibl>
                </head>

                <p>Addie apologizes for not responding sooner to Charlie's previous two letters. She
                    has read in the newspaper that Gen. McClellan is not granting furloughs and
                    Addie is disappointed in not being able to see him. Charlie had sent her poetry,
                    presumatively love poetry. Addie writes that she always wishes that she could be
                    a poetess and that she sees poetry everwhere in life and nature. Finally, Addie
                    comes to the main point of her letter. She claims that she sees Charlie only as
                    a brother, not a lover. She is conflicted over her feelings, hurting Charlie,
                    and the impact on family and friends. Laurie (Addie's brother) has been playing
                    a song, "Heart be still" in the background, and it has Addie's emotions riled
                    up. Addie hopes that Charlie does not take her letter badly for she does not
                    wish to hurt him. She points out that loving him as a brother places him in the
                    highest esteem, and that it is not an empty and cold declaration. Laurie
                    finishes his music and wishes Addie to go with him to a prayer meeting, so Addie
                    closes the letter praying that a guardian angel watch over Charlie.</p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d4">
                <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-01-26">26
                        January 1862</date></head>
                <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0043"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">Mecca</name>
                        <date value="1862-01-26">January 26<hi rend="underline">
                                <hi rend="super">th</hi>
                            </hi> 1862</date>
                        <lb/>
                    </dateline>
                    <salute>My Dear<corr sic="Brother," resp="unknown">Brother</corr><lb/>
                    </salute>
                </opener>
                <p>Laurie is writing to Hal<lb/> and wishes to know if I will send a<lb/> line to
                    &ldquo;my brother&rdquo; I, of course, <hi rend="underline"
                    >gladly</hi><lb/> accept the offer. I received two dear letters<lb/> from you
                    last week and neglected to answer<lb/> both till now, and consequently shall
                    answer<lb/> both in this <orig reg="one.">one,</orig> First I must tell you<lb/>
                    of what I read in the paper, which<lb/> caused unforbidden tears to flow; I<lb/>
                    read that <name type="person">Gen. McClellan</name> had forbidden<lb/> any more
                    furloughs being granted.<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>Now, dear Charles, do <hi rend="underline">you</hi> blaim me for<lb/> weeping at
                    that; when my anticipations<lb/>
                    <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0044"/> had been so hightened? I certainly<lb/>
                    could not help it although father told<lb/> me that I was &ldquo;such a
                    foolish little girl&rdquo;<lb/> But this is not answering Charlie's welcome<lb/>
                    <orig reg="letter.">letter,</orig> Indeed dear brother I felt somewhat<lb/>
                    flattered on the reciept of your poetry; How<lb/> often I have wished that I was
                        a <orig reg="poetes&longs;">poetes&longs;,</orig><lb/> It is one of
                    the wildest dreams that I ever<lb/> experienced the thought of being a <orig
                        reg="poetes&longs;">poetes&longs;,</orig><lb/> But as Laurie would
                    say, &ldquo;cut it short&rdquo; and<lb/> tell the truth &ldquo;you
                    don't know <orig reg="enough.">enough,</orig>&rdquo;<lb/> Well, dear brother,
                        even <hi rend="underline">I</hi> have begun to<lb/> believe it Poetry is--I
                    am tempted<lb/> to say--my life. I can imagine poetry<lb/> in every breeze of
                    wind that fans my<lb/> cheek, in every ripple of the merry<lb/> brook, in every
                    melodious song of the<lb/> pretty warbler, and most of all and<lb/> sweeter, yes
                    far sweeter than all these, is<lb/> poetry in the accent of love and friend<lb/>
                    <corr sic="ship;" resp="unknown">ship.</corr> but when I strive to place it
                    in<lb/> rhyme, my imagination seems to<corr sic="fly." resp="unknown"
                    >fly</corr><lb/>
                </p>

                <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0045"/>
                <p>But now comes this, &ldquo;Read this<lb/> last, please&rdquo; <hi
                        rend="underline">My</hi> <hi rend="underline">brother</hi>. how many,
                    many<lb/> happy thoughts have clustered round that<lb/> substitute for Charlie,
                    you dear Charlie would<lb/> wish to dispel those thoughts- would you?</p>
                <p>You may say I may hold in in a happier<lb/> nearer and dearer relation. <orig
                        reg="But">but</orig> my friend<lb/> the translation from a brother to a
                    love<lb/> is no common affair. I have taught my<lb/> heart to love you only as a
                    sister and have<lb/> tried to have my love returned only as a<lb/> brother.
                    Charlie, I will confes&longs; that I could<lb/> love you with the true and
                    fervent passion<lb/> of which my heart is capable, but Charlie<lb/> the dark and
                    dreadful disgrace resting<lb/> upon our family! I am sensible to the fact<lb/>
                    that there should be no blame attached<lb/> to me. But darling brother <hi
                        rend="underline">you</hi> are to pure<lb/> to unite yourself with one whom
                    the world<lb/> looks upon in such a light, or rather<lb/>
                        darknes&longs;<orig reg=", I">. I</orig> may be too sensitive. I
                    some<lb/> times feel that I am, but my darling Charlie<lb/> had I known of the
                    facts I now do, I could <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0046"/>
                    <hi rend="underline">never</hi><hi rend="underline"> never </hi> consented to
                    corresponded with<lb/> you. I am thankful very thankful<del hand="h1">
                        <hi rend="line-through">for</hi>
                    </del> to<lb/> Hallie for telling you. My heart and<lb/> conscience often
                    reproved me for not telling<lb/> you myself, but I could not. My God! I
                    would<lb/> exclaim. I could not tell <hi rend="underline">him</hi> if it even
                    to<lb/> save this nation! Was that a strong expres&longs;ion, my<lb/>
                    brother! My brother, what feelings arise upon the writing<lb/> of that word when
                    I know it is not sin. My darling<lb/> I will not call you by
                    that <unclear>ould</unclear> I may<lb/> by name, but as my own heart says. My own<lb/>
                    <unclear>s</unclear>darling Charlie which I feel to be <unclear>true</unclear>.</p>
                <p>What am I writing, dear Charlie. Will you blush<lb/> for Addie when you read
                    these the sentiment of my<lb/> heart. I fear you will, but Laurie was playing
                    and<lb/> singing one of my favorite pieces entitled &ldquo;Heart be
                    still&rdquo;<lb/> and it called out all the deeper feelings of my<lb/>
                    <hi rend="underline">rebellious</hi> heart and seemed to work opposite from<lb/>
                    its usual course for <hi rend="underline">my</hi> heart <hi rend="underline"
                        >would</hi> <hi rend="underline">not</hi> &ldquo;<hi rend="underline"
                        >be</hi> <hi rend="underline">still</hi>&rdquo;<lb/> dear Charlie will
                    you throw this from you in anger<lb/> and say &ldquo;she is nothing but a
                    silly romantic school<lb/> girl&rdquo; Will you dear Charlie; If I knew you
                    would<lb/> I would not send it, but my darling, it is an<lb/> ill tale but my
                    hand has moved over if never<lb/> before in unison with my heart and
                    feelings<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>Darling Charlie do you not think there is poetry on<lb/> this page? I know there
                    is in my heart<lb/> But fie! what an expres&longs;ion I have written near
                    the<lb/> top of this page drawing the inference that the<lb/> name of brother is
                    cold. Bles&longs; me! did I forget my<lb/> own darling brother <orig
                        reg="Hallie?">Hallie</orig> No a brother's name<lb/> is not cold but a
                    tumult of a different nature<lb/> swept over me at that moment. Than
                    fortune<lb/> Laurie has stopped playing or I should again go off into<lb/> one
                    of my wild dreams that is my nature when<lb/> I hear music, I either sit spell
                    bound or else the<lb/> inmost depth of my soul are awakened, but<lb/>
                </p>
                <closer>I must close this as Laurie wishing one to go to<lb/> prayer meeting tonight
                        with <orig reg="him.">him</orig><salute>May a guardian<lb/> angel from Heaven
                        hover round thee, forever<lb/> as the earnest prayer of your<lb/>
                    </salute><signed>Addie</signed></closer>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
