<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0111 SYSTEM "000000766_0111" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0112 SYSTEM "000000766_0112" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0113 SYSTEM "000000766_0113" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0114 SYSTEM "000000766_0114" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62d01a SYSTEM "NA62d01a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62d01b SYSTEM "NA62d01b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62d01c SYSTEM "NA62d01c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62d01d SYSTEM "NA62d01d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62d01T">

 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-04-01"
      >April 1, 1862</date></title>

    <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>Andrea Coles (Rare Book School)</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>Andrea Coles</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NA62d01</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                    <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton/</p>-->
                    <p n="copyright"/>
                </availability>
    <date value="2004">2004</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney,</title>

      <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>4 pp.</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p/>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings.</p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>

  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1862-04-01">1862-04-01</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>feminine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Women Writers/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-06">November 6th, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2010-09-30">September 30, 2010</date>
    <respStmt>
     <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">
  <front id="d2">
   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>AL</abbr>
      <extent>4 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1862-04-01">April 1, 1862</date>

      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p> Addie expresses concern about Charles' wounded arm and her belief that he is downplaying its
     severity, as well as sadness for others (Fred; Arthur Cavanah) who were wounded or died. She
     mentions a conversation she had with a friend, Laurie. Addie worried when she heard about a
     battle and then did not hear from him for three weeks. Having been offered a six month position
     as a teacher, she seeks his opinion on whether or not she should accept. She urges him to come
     home before she starts teaching. At the end, she asks if Charlie knows Edwin Williams and Will
     Braden of the 29th Ohio Regiment. </p>
   </div1>
  </front>
  <body id="d4">

   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-04-01">April 1,
     1862</date></head>
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0111"/>
    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <name type="place">Home</name>
      <date value="1862-04-01">April 1<hi rend="super">st</hi> '62</date>
     </dateline>
    </opener>

    <p> Heaven reward you and <orig reg="bless">ble&longs;s</orig> you, <hi rend="underline">my
      own</hi><lb/>
     <hi rend="underline">my dear darling Charlie</hi> for your kind and<lb/> precious letter of the
      25<hi rend="super">th</hi> <unclear>inst.</unclear>. Darling, you<lb/> do not know how much it
     relieved my<lb/> heart. of an almost sinking fear and pain.<lb/> Although it relieved me of my
     worst<lb/> fears, yet it brought painful information<lb/> that you did not escape unharmed. </p>
    <p> Dearest, I know that you<sic corr="were">was</sic> injured<lb/> far worse than you
     represented yourself to be.<lb/> Do you not think that I could see in the<lb/> very tone of
     your letter that it was with<lb/>
     <orig reg="extreme">extrem</orig> pain that you could trace those<lb/> dear lines? Oh, dear
     Charlie, please tell me<lb/> just how badly your arm was hurt.. Darling,<lb/> why should you
     attempt to conceal from me<lb/> your sufferings. Who should sooner know of <pb n="2"
      entity="DSSR_000000766_0112"/> your sufferings than one who has plighted her<lb/> love,
      aye, <hi rend="underline">even her life</hi> if necessary to you<lb/> I could not feel
     worse.dearest to know the<lb/> entire truth than I now do. What. my Charlie<lb/> trying to
     conceal from me - the one who should<lb/> be with him through the hours of
     pain <unclear>the</unclear><lb/> extent of his wounds! Oh, do not my darling.<lb/> The very
     thought is but frenzy. Why is it<lb/> that I can not be with you. God only knows<lb/> what I
     have suffered since I heard of that<lb/> fearful battle.. I had not heard from you<lb/> for
      some <orig reg="time">tim</orig> before that and when I read<lb/> of the fight. and still no
     word from Charlie.<lb/> then and only <hi rend="underline">till</hi> then did I realize<lb/>
     what life would be worth to me without<lb/> you. I said to Laurie last sabbath.
     &ldquo;What<lb/> does it mean. three weeks ago tomorrow since<lb/> I have heard from
     Charlie&rdquo;? She replied<lb/> &ldquo;Have hope Addie. Do not give up in dispair<lb/>
     for oh, that is a hard word when forced<lb/> upon you.&rdquo; Darling do you wonder that my
      <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0113"/> faith in the protection of an All wise Father<lb/>
     was beginning to totter? </p>
    <p> I sympathize with you in the <orig reg="loss">lo&longs;s</orig> of your<lb/> comrade.
      Fred. <unclear>lo__</unclear> and also with the wounded.<lb/> Arthur Cavanah. I have seen
     several times.<lb/> He formerly kept the &ldquo;Livery Stable&rdquo; at Powers<lb/>
     corners. did he not? What a sickening sight a<lb/> battle field must be. The discription of
     it<lb/> which you gave me is enough. I never wish<lb/> to see one. </p>
    <p> Darling. how would you like it if I should<lb/> teach school this summer. There is a school
     in<lb/> Claridon that is not engaged. and they wish<lb/> very much to have me teach it. Should
     I<lb/> dear. They wish for a six months school<lb/> rather long but <orig reg="nevertheless"
      >neverthele&longs;s</orig> it will do.<lb/> I do so dread this inactive, monotonous<lb/>
     life I am now leading. besides I have no<lb/> desire to live at home this summer. but<lb/> I
     will be guided by your decision. The school<lb/> is in <unclear>Miss</unclear> Leslie's
     district.. <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0114"/> How I should love to have you come
     home<lb/> darling. If I teach I wish very much to have<lb/> you come before I commence my
     school. can<lb/> you come? If you were but with me now. Oh, my<lb/> darling. I am fearful that
     your wound is much more<lb/> than you . yourself think. but I must hope for<lb/> the best. Is
     not this day. beautiful? Oh the<lb/> world is full of beauty when the heart is full of<lb/>
     love.is it not. Charlie. </p>
    <p> The twenty ninth Ohio <abbr expan="Regiment">Regt</abbr>. was engaged in<lb/> that fight were
     they not? Are you acquainted<lb/> with Edwin Williams of that Regt. he is a brother<lb/> of
     mine in the Templars <unclear>curse</unclear>. Ed. and<lb/> Will. Braden are or were firm
     friends . when<lb/> here in Mecca, He formerly belonged to the Seventh<lb/> Ohio I think. But I
     have not time<lb/> to write longer as papa is going over to<lb/> the office tonight and I must
     send this<lb/> while I have a chance these muddy<lb/> roads! Remember me to the boys. and<lb/>
     darling. be careful of your health. Do not get<lb/> cold in your arm<lb/>
    </p>
    <closer>
     <salute>Write often very often to cheer the heart of<lb/> your Addie</salute>
    </closer>
   </div1>

  </body>

 </text>

</TEI.2>
