<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0199 SYSTEM "000000766_0199" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0200 SYSTEM "000000766_0200" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0201 SYSTEM "000000766_0201" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0202 SYSTEM "000000766_0202" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0203 SYSTEM "000000766_0203" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0204 SYSTEM "000000766_0204" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0205 SYSTEM "000000766_0205" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0206 SYSTEM "000000766_0206" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62i22a SYSTEM "NA62i22a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62i22b SYSTEM "NA62i22b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62i22c SYSTEM "NA62i22c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62i22d SYSTEM "NA62i22d.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62i22e SYSTEM "NA62i22e.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62i22f SYSTEM "NA62i22f.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62i22g SYSTEM "NA62i22g.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62i22h SYSTEM "NA62i22h.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62i22">
 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <!-- todo -->
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-09-22"
      >22 September 1862</date></title>

    <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>David Seaman</name>
     <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
     <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>ETC</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NA62i22</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                    <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
                    <p n="copyright"/>
                </availability>
    <date value="2001">2001</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 22 September 1862</title>
      <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>8 pages</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p/>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p> </p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings. </p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1862-09-22">1862-09-22</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>feminine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-10">November 10th, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">
  <front id="d2">

   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>8 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1862-09-22">22 September 1862</date>

      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p/>
   </div1>
  </front>
  <body id="d4">
   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-09-22">22 September
      1862</date></head>
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0199"/>
    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <name type="place">At Dora's <add place="inline" hand="h1">Home</add> school. </name> Monday
       <date value="1862-09-22">Sept., 22<hi rend="super">nd</hi>
       <add place="inline" hand="h1">1862</add></date>
     </dateline>
     <salute>Loved Charlie</salute>
    </opener>




    <p>I am going to write <lb/> you a <hi rend="underline">good</hi> long letter to day. for I
     expect <lb/> it will be the last one I shall write you <lb/> while I remain in Claridon, (<hi
      rend="underline">Charlie</hi> Charlie <lb/> make Dora go away, she is emphasizing <lb/> my
      "<hi rend="underline">good</hi> letters"..) So you thought my <lb/> letter of Aug, 18<hi
      rend="super">th</hi>
     <hi rend="underline">short</hi> did you dear? <lb/> I am sure I know not what I <unclear/> on
     <lb/> the lengrh of it, but I guess this will <lb/> be long enough to make up for past <lb/>
     <unclear>deficeincies</unclear>. I am going to answer your <lb/>
     <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0200"/> dear letter of the 9<hi rend="super">th</hi> in every
     particular, <lb/> so here goes. certainly I will forgive you <lb/> for writing on such poor
     paper, but do not <lb/> think that I care for the paper, no. no. if <lb/> your's are only such
     dear kind letters are you <lb/> only and always do write, they will be a precious <lb/>
     treasure to me. even if writeen on poor paper <lb/> remember I am thankful for even one word
     from <lb/> you. come what way it may, (My hand trembles <lb/> this morning for some reason. I
     guess it is because <lb/> I have been walking.) I was very glad to learn <lb/> that your health
     was so good. I sometimes won= <lb/> der why it is that you retain such good health <lb/> while
     others, who evidently enjoyed just as good <lb/> health as you when they entered the service.
     have <lb/> come home many of them with shattered constit= <lb/> tions. others--to die, Yes
     darling, I have often <lb/> very often wondered at this, and while thus <lb/> wondering, evne
     my rebellious heart looks up <lb/> with a sweet assurance and murmurs, "God <lb/> is very good"
     May you still continue to recieve <lb/> that blessing. for blessing it is <lb/>
     <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0201"/> I was pleased with the <hi rend="underline"
     >resume</hi>. you gave me. <lb/> In reference to your diet. you have something <lb/> new for
     breakfast every <sic>moring</sic> do you not? <lb/> Coffee. meat. and crackers. also crackers
     meat <lb/> and coffee, quite a variety. nevertheless I am <lb/> fearful that <add
      place="inline" hand="h1">i</add> should soon become tired of it. <lb/> Time <hi
      rend="underline">must</hi> pass very wearily with you. would <lb/> that I could <del hand="h1"
      >pass</del> spend a few hours with you <lb/> daily. in useful and interesting conversation,
     <lb/> But think you not love that. with me time <lb/> also passes very wearily? The same weary
     waiting. <lb/> watching with longing eyes for the time when <lb/> peace shall be restored, and.
     Charlie can come home <lb/> to--me. May God preserve thee darling. till that <lb/> hope shall
     be realized. </p>
    <p> In speaking of your Gen's they also have to "run <lb/> the gauntlet" of a rigid criticism
     here in the north <lb/> The late movements in Maryland and Virgin- <lb/> =ia have thrown a
     different aspect over military <lb/>
     <unclear>matters</unclear>. Those who have always believed in <lb/> McClellans loyalty are
     perfectly jubilant while <lb/> those who have showered the most abusive <lb/>
     <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0202"/> invectives are sullen and silent looking forward <lb/>
     and almost wishing that McCl<del hand="h1">l</del>ellan may be <lb/> defeated <del hand="h1"
     >if</del> and brought to sidgrace if for nothing <lb/> more than to prove that their former
     assertions <lb/> were not wholly untrue.. How does "Night Hawk" <lb/> take now. I enjoyed quite
     a hearty lauch over <lb/> that "scandal" and <sic>especialy</sic> over that "adored <lb/>
     mustache." You say you wish I could hear the <lb/> rumors of the army for one day, I can not
     say that <lb/> I have any particular <add place="inline" hand="h1">desire</add> to hear them
     for the rumors <lb/> here keep<del hand="h1">s</del> me in a perfect<del hand="h1">ly</del>
     whirl of excitement <lb/> indeed I believe if I had not been a girl of pretty <lb/> strong mind
     I should have been whirled our of <lb/> the state of Ohio, for many men (and you know <lb/>
     they are of stronget mind than the women) <add place="inline" hand="h1">not a bit of it
     Dora</add> have <lb/> been seen "whirling" for Canada as fast as their <lb/> feet could carry
     them, and did not stop <lb/> till they were saluted <sic>whith</sic>, "Have you a pass" <lb/>
     Then their consternation is wonderful and even <lb/> laughable to behold. You ask me if I am
     not <lb/> fearful some daring rebel will not make a <lb/> raid up into good old Trumbull Co.?
     No, <lb/> not a bit. If they did I am certain that they <lb/> would meet with such a
     reception--perhaps of <lb/> cold lead, that they would soon have to retreat <lb/> to the sunny
     south again to obtain warmth <lb/> enough to keep them alive. Old Trumbull has <lb/> enough men
     to stand her ground against quite <lb/> a host of rebels yet, and when her sons fail <lb/> her
     daughters will then take the field. there <lb/> are enough and brage hearts left in Ohio <lb/>
     yet to defend her soil, and it will be defende[d] <lb/> if it is at the cost of losing every
     boy <unclear>al</unclear> man <lb/> of which she can boast. Oh! it would have <lb/> done your
     heart good to have seen the <lb/>
     <pb n="5" entity="DSSR_000000766_0203"/> men starting. <add place="inline" hand="h1">with</add>
     musket. shot-gun or any <lb/> thing defensive which could be found. <lb/> for Cincinnati when
     the startling news <lb/> arrived the the "Queen City of the West" was <lb/> being shelled.
     Little boys of the age of ten or <lb/> twelve years, would run with determined <lb/>
     countenances and ask, "Mother can't I go and <lb/> help fight. Husbands and fathers would leave
     <lb/> their homes and families, with hearts too <lb/> full for utterance to repeat the word
     "Good- <lb/> =bye." exclaming "a rebels foot shall never <lb/> desecrate our own our beautiful
     Ohio." <lb/> While others.--painful sight. would shudder, <lb/> stand back and sullenly
     exclaim. "Enough <lb/> with out me" But I am happy to say that <lb/> there were but few of this
     latter chaps. Soon <lb/> the joyful news arrived that the rebels were fast <lb/> retreating.
     and those who had left their homes so <lb/> hastily were permitted to return again. </p>
    <p>Oh! Charlie: Laura has just come and I am <pb n="6" entity="DSSR_000000766_0204"/> compelled
     to close I will write again <lb/> as soon as I get home My love to all <lb/> and write soon to
     your own <lb/>
    </p>
    <closer>
     <signed>Addie</signed>
    </closer>

    <pb entity="DSSR_000000766_0205"/>
    <pb entity="DSSR_000000766_0206"/>

   </div1>
  </body>
 </text>

</TEI.2>
