<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0083 SYSTEM "000000766_0083" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0084 SYSTEM "000000766_0084" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0085 SYSTEM "000000766_0085" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0086 SYSTEM "000000766_0086" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62b19a SYSTEM "NA62b19a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b19b SYSTEM "NA62b19b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b19c SYSTEM "NA62b19c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62b19d SYSTEM "NA62b19d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->

<!ENTITY longs "s" >
<!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62b19">


 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-02-19"
      >1862 February 19</date></title>
    <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>Valeria Gauz, John Carter Brown Library, Brown University</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">14</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NA62b19</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                    <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton/</p>-->
                    <p n="copyright"/>
                </availability>
    <date value="2000">2000</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>

   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Page images have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 1862 February 19</title>


      <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>4 pp.</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p>Corine Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection </p>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p>Letter does not finish on p. 4: it continues on margins of p. 1.</p>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings.</p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>

  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1862-02-19">1862-02-19</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>feminine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Women Writers/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2001-05">May 2001</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Carolyn Fay, Electronic Text Center</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Updated TEI header and tags. </item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-03">November 3rd, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2010-09-30">September 30, 2010</date>
    <respStmt>
     <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">
  <front id="d2">

   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>4 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1862-02-19">1862-02-19</date>

      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, February 19, 1862.</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>

    <p>Writing from the schoolroom, Addie relates a nightmare she had about Charlie being ill and
     delirious. She is worried about him because she has not heard from him in quite some time.
     Refering to the recent Union victory at Fort Donelson, Addie writes about the atrocities of
     war.</p>

   </div1>
  </front>
  <body id="d4">


   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0083"/>
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-02-19">1862 February
      19</date></head>
    <opener>
     <dateline>Mecca Feb. 19<hi rend="super">th</hi> 1862.</dateline>
     <salute>
      <name type="person">Dearest Charlie</name>
     </salute>

    </opener>

    <p> I can not refrain from<lb/> penning you a few lines even if my<lb/> worthy teacher should
     censure me for<lb/> I am now in the schoolroom.<lb/> So long a time has elapsed since<lb/> I
     have received any thing from you<lb/> that I fear you are ill. Oh! I had<lb/> such a strange
     dream last night.<lb/> I shudder even now when I think of it.<lb/> You are lying ill and
     delirious<lb/> where I could both see and hear you.<lb/> You calling for me and yet I <pb n="2"
      entity="DSSR_000000766_0084"/> could not go to you. I struggled<lb/> long earnestly and in
     vain, but there<lb/> seemed some great obstacle between<lb/> us which I could not
     surmount.<lb/> And the more aggravating it was<lb/> that these, were all whom I had ever had
     the<lb/> least feeling of anger toward making me. One thing makes it<lb/> almost
      laughable. <abbr expan="Colonel">Col.</abbr> Tyler was one<lb/> of them. I awoke completely
     exhausted<lb/> and - do not laugh, dearest - weeping.<lb/> Be assured, my darling, there was
     no<lb/> more rest for me. Why bless your<lb/> dearest. I have not read a letter from<lb/> you
     for two weeks, and it is no<lb/> wonder that such dreams, as the<lb/> above come to torture me
     when<lb/> you, before, have written so often.</p>
    <p> Why! I believe the tortures of the rack<lb/> can be nothing to the <orig reg="imaginings"
      >imaginnings</orig> of<lb/> such dreams.</p>
    <p>Has <abbr expan="Captain">Capt</abbr> Asper arrived yet? I sent<lb/> a letter by him or
     rather, Hallie gave <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0085"/> it to him enclosed in it was<lb/>
     a portrait of "Your Addie" as you persist<lb/> in calling her. Oh! I can not<lb/> drive that
     ugly dream from my<lb/> mind. It has given me that detestable desease commonly termed<lb/> "the
     blues" and I do not think that<lb/> there is a thing which will relieve me<lb/> except a letter
     from you. Now please<lb/> write will you not? as soon as you<lb/> receive this</p>
    <p> Darling, do you not think "Julius" a<lb/> beautiful signature? Questions such as<lb/> this
     "who is there in <abbr expan="Company">Co.</abbr> <unclear>H</unclear>
      <unclear>7th</unclear> Ohio <abbr expan="Regiment">Reg't</abbr><lb/> by the name of "Julius"?
     Bless you<lb/> dearest the same beautiful flow<lb/> of thoughts: the same dear form<lb/> of
     writing, and the same formal<lb/> manner of writing are visible in<lb/> "Julius" letters as in
     "Charlie's".<lb/> I could distinguished it among<lb/> a thousand others letters.</p>
    <p> Darling how difficult it is to write in a <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0086"/> a school
     room. In imagination picture a<lb/> school room by fifty scholars ranging in<lb/> age from the
     blooming girl of twenty down to<lb/> the lisping child of four years. Some engaged<lb/> in
     studying - perhaps their lessons and perhaps<lb/> not - some in whispering and others is -
     sitting<lb/> still, looking at the next on one side of the<lb/> room sits our young teacher,
     before a little<lb/> boy who is reciting his Geography lesson, in<lb/> a kind of "dont care"
     way, and then for the<lb/> busily writing, as - one of our scholars<lb/> says, "writing to her
     beloved of ". Well I don't<lb/> know as I have any reason to doubt upon it. While<lb/> such ...
     as that ... from lips to me.</p>
    <p> Add! Let me see it when you get it finished. I<lb/> want to learn how to write "Love". "Add
     I will tell<lb/> the teacher". you will pardon my poor<lb/> composition after reading this will
     you not?</p>
    <p>
     <name type="person">Hal</name> is well perfectly so, with the exception of<lb/> his cold. The
     same feeling seems to pervade <unclear>Hal</unclear><lb/> that does human beings. That of liking
     him<lb/> if friends were always as faithful as is his<lb/> cold I presume he could have more
     than he now<lb/> does. But he has enough. Our sleighing has all gone<lb/> and left us. It
     lasted four days. I can assure you<lb/> that was well <unclear>improved</unclear>. There is to
     be a donation<lb/> for our pastor, Mr. Arnold, this evening. I shall not<lb/> attend if I do
     not feel more cheerful than at the<lb/> present hour.</p>
    <p> Oh, what a buzzing zing there is around me<lb/> it sounds more like a swarm of bees than
     like human<lb/> beings. How do you get along for reading, do you have<lb/> enough? If not write
     me and let me know and I will<lb/> send you some by <unclear/>. Hal and Laurie went to<lb/>
     Bristol last week to see<name type="person">Charlie Brooks</name>, and <name type="person">Mr
      Miller</name>.<lb/> He thinks Mr Miller will not live long. Charles Brooks<lb/> starts soon
     for his <abbr expan="Company">Co.</abbr>. If I can I will send some<lb/> papers, and books by
     him. What a victory our troops<lb/> won at Fort Donaldson<ref target="n1" n="1">[1]</ref>. How
     have the <unclear>particulins</unclear> have gone not; and still at what a cost. We lost
     heavily. And yet we must expect it<lb/> How barbarous it does seem to fight as they died, yet
     it is necessary. People say they can<lb/> read of such battles now with out a shudder, but I
     can scarcely believe it. Think of hundreds<lb/> (I move to first page)<ref target="n2" n="2"
      >[2]</ref><lb/>
    </p>
    <p> of souls entering the dread within a few short hours, and hundreds of<lb/> others lying
     wounded and writhing in their <unclear>gone</unclear>. Oh, it is horrible to think<lb/> of say
     nothing of the sight. Dear Charlie this question<lb/> involuntarily rises<lb/> to my lips. And
     they<lb/> preferred to die!<lb/> What an<lb/> important<lb/> and fearful<lb/> question, and yet
     how little is<lb/> thought of it, My darling I do not profess<lb/> to be a christian, and yet I
     know there is<lb/> such a thing as religion. There is something in true religion which I would
     give worlds to<lb/> possess, but I do not I have no hesitancy in<lb/> saying that I do not
     believe that one half<lb/> who profess to love their Savior know any thing<lb/> about it. And
     yet I know there is a God who<lb/> is there that can look on this beautiful world<lb/> and
     doubt it. Everything declares it<lb/> I do not think Religion consists in putting on<lb/> long
     faces and looking as if the world<lb/> were coming to an end if we laugh where<lb/> I do not
     think Christ intended we should<lb/> give up all pleasure here for him. But<lb/> what
      a <unclear>strain</unclear> of thought I have been<ref target="n3" n="3">[3]</ref><lb/>
    </p>

    <p> let into It is almost noon and I must close "Remember me for all of the<lb/> boys and write
     soon very very soon will you not dearest? Please do not keep Addie in suspense.<ref target="n4"
      n="4">[4]</ref><lb/>
    </p>
    <closer>
     <salute> Yours, now, and forever</salute>
     <signed>Addie</signed>

     <ref target="n5" n="5">[5]</ref>
     <lb/>
    </closer>
   </div1>
  </body>

  <back id="d6">


   <div1 type="notes" n="1" id="d7">
    <head>Notes</head>
    <note id="n1" place="end" n="1"><seg type="note-symbol">[1]</seg>
     <p> The Battle of Fort Donelson took place between the 13th and 16th of February. This was an
      important Union victory, led by General Ulysses S. Grant, who demanded immediate and
      unconditional surrender from Confederate General Buckner.</p>
    </note>
    <note id="n2" place="end" n="2"><seg type="note-symbol">[2]</seg>
     <p> The preceding paragraph is written along the left margin of page four.</p>
    </note>
    <note id="n3" place="end" n="3"><seg type="note-symbol">[3]</seg>
     <p> The preceding paragraph is written along the left margin of page one.</p>
    </note>
    <note id="n4" place="end" n="4"><seg type="note-symbol">[4]</seg>
     <p> The preceding paragraph is written along the left margin of page two.</p>
    </note>
    <note id="n5" place="end" n="5"><seg type="note-symbol">[5]</seg>
     <p> The preceding paragraph is written along the left margin of page three.</p>
    </note>
   </div1>
  </back>


 </text>
</TEI.2>
