<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0139 SYSTEM "000000766_0139" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0140 SYSTEM "000000766_0140" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0141 SYSTEM "000000766_0141" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0142 SYSTEM "000000766_0142" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62e26a SYSTEM "NA62e26a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62e26b SYSTEM "NA62e26b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62e26c SYSTEM "NA62e26c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62e26d SYSTEM "NA62e26d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62e26">

 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-05-26"
      >May 26<hi rend="super">th</hi> 1862</date></title>

    <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>Janet Catterall</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>University of Saskatchewan Library Special Collections</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NA62e26</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
    <date value="2004">2004</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title/>
      <author/>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>4 pp.</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p/>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings.</p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>

  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1862-05-26">1862-05-26</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>feminine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Women Writers/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-09">November 9th, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">

  <front id="d2">
   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>4 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1862-05-26">May 26<hi rend="super">th</hi>, 1862</date>

      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney.</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p> Adelle has not heard from Charles in three weeks and fears the worst. She laments that her
     dreams may prove true, that he has been killed, and prefers death for herself rather than the
     intolerable suspense of not knowing. Trying to end the letter more on a more positive note, she
     goes talks about her enjoyment of school teaching. Finally she indicates at the end of the
     letter that she has just received two letters from Charlie. </p>
   </div1>
  </front>

  <body id="d4">
   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-05-26">May 26<hi rend="super">th</hi>
     1862</date></head>
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0139"/>
    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <name type="place">My school room</name>
      <date value="1862-05-26">May 26<hi rend="super">th</hi> 1862.</date>
     </dateline>

     <salute>Dearest Charlie</salute>

    </opener>

    <p> My school room is unoccupied<lb/> with the exception of one lonely being and<lb/> how
     thankful she is to obtain that solitude for which<lb/> she has all day wished, But is it right
     for her<lb/> to be alone? Alone to those torturing thoughts<lb/> which cling to her sleeping or
     waking. and which<lb/> nothing but a letter from that idolized being can<lb/> drive away? Oh
     Charlie! My own loved one. if it<lb/> is in your power. why do you not break the silence<lb/>
     between us Three long lingering weeks have <orig reg="passed">pa&longs;sed</orig> since<lb/>
     last I heard from you and God only know how<lb/> much longer time will <orig reg="pass"
      >pa&longs;s</orig> before I shall. Are<lb/>
     <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0140"/> you ill darling and not able to write. If so why<lb/>
     not let me know. I could bear <hi rend="underline">that</hi> Or - Oh. <unclear>no</unclear><lb/>
     I will never write that thought, If I did<lb/> I should feel every letter sinking into my
     heart.<lb/> as if written with a pen of fire, Ah! those tears thank<lb/> heaven for them,, But
     they are but few to what I<lb/> have shed over my dreams. The thoughts while waking<lb/> are
     not enough to torture my poor heart but dreams.<lb/> frightful dreams! Oh I can not think of
     them,<lb/> If the cruel monster <hi rend="underline">Death</hi> - My God <hi rend="underline"
      >must</hi><lb/> I write it - has done his work. why do I not know<lb/> it for then yes then. I
     might die. Die! Ah. what is<lb/> death to this fearful suspense. It is nought. And<lb/> then I
     might meet my idol, Here again I am<lb/> thinking that it <hi rend="underline">must</hi> be so.
     just as my dreams<lb/> picture to me. and not only thinking but writing<lb/> it, Is this <orig
      reg="madness">madne&longs;s</orig>? or is it caused by <unclear>short And</unclear><lb/>
     yet at times sharp pain around my heart<lb/>
    </p>

    <p> My own precious friend why do you not come home<lb/> or else write. would that you could
     experience for<lb/> one moment the anguish which I do. But<del hand="h1">
       <unclear>not</unclear>
     </del><lb/>
     <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0141"/> no, not for one moment would I wish it. I would<lb/>
     spare you that my darling. But I must stop<lb/> and seek society or I shall go mad. May heaven
     grant<lb/> tonight that boon I so much crave - a word from<lb/> Charlie. or I could almost say
     - death,<lb/>
    </p>

   </div1>

   <div1 type="letter" n="2" id="d6">
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, Morning of the 27<hi rend="super"
     >th</hi></head>
    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <date value="1862-05-27">Morning 27<hi rend="super">th</hi>.</date>
     </dateline>
    </opener>

    <p> Darling Charlie. I fear you will be frightened<lb/> when you read this. I felt very<sic
      corr="melancholy">melancholly</sic> last eve<lb/> when I wrote this above. and even now do not
     feel<lb/> much better, but &ldquo;I live in hope&rdquo; Ah! that <orig reg="blessed"
      >ble&longs;sed</orig><lb/> word &ldquo;Hope&rdquo; How many poor mortals would
     have been<lb/> driven to desperation did not Hope whisper to<lb/> them so tenderly, Dearest can
     you tell why I am<lb/> not happy? I ought to be had I not? At times<lb/> darling, I am very
     very lonely. although so much beauty<lb/> and <orig reg="loveliness">loveline&longs;s</orig>
     surround me yet I can not banish<lb/> my fears caused by this silence. While in company<lb/> I
     can appear happy, but <unclear>ohi</unclear> that pain in my<lb/> heart. Night after night I<sic
      corr="receive">recieve</sic> the same answer. &ldquo;No<lb/> letter for you&rdquo; and
     turn to hide the tears that will<lb/> come, and then so anxiously wait watch and pray only<lb/>
     <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0142"/> to be disappointed. Charlie I came to my school
     room<lb/> this morning with the determination that I would finish<lb/> this in a more cheerful
     mood than I commenced it<lb/> but I believe I am incapable of doing it<lb/> Would you like to
     know how my school is <orig reg="progressing">progre&longs;sing</orig>?<lb/> I have now
     thirty scholars, and a pleasanter school I could<lb/> not wish for, Charlie I do not flatter
     myself one bit when<lb/> I say. I have not a scholar that would willingly<lb/> disregard my
     slightest wish. for I know I have not,<lb/> I sometimes wonder how they came to love me so,
     You<lb/> remember what you wrote me before my school commenced<lb/> that if my experience could
     be like yours I would<lb/> find the bitter with the sweet. I <orig reg="guess"
     >gue&longs;s</orig> mine is not like<lb/> yours darling. for as yet but little of the
     bitter has been<lb/> found, Teaching. so far has been a very pleasant employment<lb/> and I am
     now teaching the fourth week. Time flies<lb/> swiftly while I am in the school room. I would
     like<lb/> to have you visit my school this summer, wish you could<lb/> see me now sitting here
     no one near. for it is yet scarcely<lb/> eight o'clock. writing very busily while at my right
     hand<lb/> lies my Bible. I have been reading in it darling<lb/>
    </p>

    <p> How much I am in need of that wisdom and strength<lb/> so clearly spoken of in that <orig
      reg="blessed">ble&longs;sed</orig> Book, How soon<lb/> shall I<sic corr="receive">
     recieve</sic> it. I do not know. But it is time<lb/> to call school, <orig reg="Bless"
      >Ble&longs;s</orig> you a thousand times my own<lb/> darling. Ashley Armstrong has just
     handed me<lb/> two letters in the well know hand writing of my<lb/> Charlie. I will read them
     and answer<corr sic="tonight" resp="unknown">to night</corr><lb/>
    </p>

    <closer> Your unchanging<lb/>
     <name type="sender">Addie</name>
    </closer>
    <lb/>
   </div1>

  </body>


 </text>

</TEI.2>
