<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;  

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0147 SYSTEM "000000766_0147" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0148 SYSTEM "000000766_0148" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0149 SYSTEM "000000766_0149" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0150 SYSTEM "000000766_0150" NDATA jpg>

	<!--<!ENTITY NA62f04a SYSTEM "NA62f04a.jpg" NDATA jpg>  
	<!ENTITY NA62f04b SYSTEM "NA62f04b.jpg" NDATA jpg>  
	<!ENTITY NA62f04c SYSTEM "NA62f04c.jpg" NDATA jpg>  
	<!ENTITY NA62f04d SYSTEM "NA62f04d.jpg" NDATA jpg>  -->
	<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s as typically found in 18th century text --> 

	
	]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62f04">

    <teiHeader type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenny, <date
                        value="1862-06-04">June 4<hi rend="super">th</hi>, 1862</date></title>
                <author>Case, Adelaide E., fl. 1861-1863</author>

                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription and TEIXLITE encoding.</resp>
                    <name>Brett Carnell. Library of Congress. Prints and Photographs Division. Rare
                        Book School 2005.</name>
                </respStmt>

            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Albert H. Small Special Collections Library, University of Virginia</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Va.</pubPlace>
                <idno type="etext">NA62f04</idno>
                <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
                <availability>
                    <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
                    <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
                    <p n="copyright"/>
                </availability>
                <date value="2005">2005</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenny, 04 June 1862</title>
                        <author/>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                        <date value="1862-06-04">1862-06-04</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <handList>
                <hand id="h1"/>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2009-11-09">November 9th, 2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
                    (uva-dl-tei).</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">

        <front id="d2">
            <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
                <head>
                    <bibl>
                        <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                        <extent>4 pp.</extent>
                        <date value="1862-06-04">June 4, 1862</date>
                        <!--<idno rend="suppress">NA62f04</idno>-->
                        <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenny</title>
                    </bibl>
                </head>
                <p> Addie muses about her school, 30 scholars from 4 to 17 years old, who study
                    writing, arithmetic, geography, grammar, algebra and orthography, and she lists
                    the names of texts used. She asks Charlie what he thinks of the retreat of
                    General Banks and discusses her views of the occupation of Winchester. She also
                    tells of her feelings of very old and very young men going to war. She says that
                    Laura has visited and told her brother Hal is back in the army and has gone to
                    Columbus. </p>
            </div1>

        </front>

        <body id="d4">



            <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
                <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenny, <date value="1862-06-04"
                        >June 4<hi rend="super">th</hi>, 1862</date></head>
                <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0147"/>
                <opener>

                    <!--<seg>
                        <figure rend="page" entity="NA62f04a">
                            <figDesc/>
                        </figure>
                    </seg>-->

                    <dateline>
                        <name type="place">East Claridon</name>
                        <date value="1862-06-04">June 4<hi rend="super">th</hi> 1862</date>
                    </dateline>
                    <lb/>
                    <salute>My own loved <name type="recipient" key="CNT">Charlie</name></salute>
                    <lb/>

                </opener>
                <p> Did you ever see a more <orig reg="disagreeable">disagree-<lb/> -able</orig>
                    morning than this? Rain, rain nothing but rain<lb/> and has been so for nearly a
                    week. Don't you pity the<lb/> school teachers such a day as this? Here have I
                    walked<lb/> nearly half a mile through the rain and much before<lb/> eight
                    o'clock, and after building a fire to make<lb/> it appear more cheerful have
                    gone to writing. But<lb/> what are my inconveniences when compared with the<lb/>
                    soldiers. Here I find a dry and pleasant school-room<lb/> to enter and although
                    they are not now here, there soon<lb/> will be happy faces hurrying to receive
                    their teachers<lb/> morning ki&longs;s. and then follows the pleasant hours
                    to<lb/> be spent in learning and reciting lessons. While with<lb/> the soldier,
                    how different. Perhaps for their employment<lb/> is a long and tedious march
                    through the storm<lb/> with no covering, to be welcomed only with a cry<lb/> of
                    revenge and maybe death. Really my labors<lb/>
                    <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0148"/>
                    <!--<figure rend="page" entity="NA62f04b">
                        <figDesc/>
                    </figure>-->
                    are but light. and how much nobler is the cause<lb/> in which they are engaged
                    than is mine.<lb/> But you will be anxious to hear how my school is<lb/>
                    prospering. I think it "goes of" finely. Not quite as well<lb/> as I could wish
                    (for you know we are prone to wish more than<lb/> can be expected sometimes) but
                    full as well and perhaps better<lb/> than I expected. Thirty scholars attend
                    now. they are from<lb/> four to seventeen years of age. Have I ever told you
                    the<lb/> branches that are studied? They are reading writing. <orig
                        reg="Arithmetic">Arithme<lb/> -tic</orig>. parts 2<hi rend="super">
                        <hi rend="underline">nd</hi>
                    </hi> and 3<hi rend="super">
                        <hi rend="underline">rd</hi>
                    </hi> Ray's. <name type="book Title">Mitchells Geography</name>, <name
                        type="book title">Pin<add hand="h1" place="supralinear">n</add>eo's<lb/>
                        Grammar</name>, and <name type="book title">Ray's Algebra</name><ref
                        target="n1" n="1">1</ref>. also Orthography. Now do you<lb/> not think I
                    have a <hi rend="underline">school</hi>? I do. There. I told you<lb/> they would
                    come. one. two three four five - all coming to say<lb/> good morning. and the
                    girls to receive the ki&longs;s which I<lb/> had to stop writing long enough
                    to give them. I would<lb/> that you could see them, darling, one little boy
                    wishes<lb/> me to stop writing and talk to him, shall I do<lb/> it? I know you
                    would say yes, dear Charlie. were you<lb/> here so I will gratify him </p>

            </div1>

            <div1 type="letter" n="2" id="d6">
                <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenny, Noon of <date
                        value="1862-06-04">June 4<hi rend="super">th</hi>, 1862</date></head>

                <opener> Noon, </opener>


                <p> Were you here dearest, I would want more time to<lb/> talk with you and also
                    have it more connected than<lb/>
                    <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0149"/>
                    <!--<figure rend="page" entity="NA62f04c">
                        <figDesc/>
                    </figure>-->
                    it necessarily must be. For you know a teacher<lb/> must write when <del
                        hand="h1">they</del>
                    <add hand="h1" place="supralinear">she</add> can. Charlie do you <orig
                        reg="remember">remem<lb/> ber</orig> the "<name type="book title"
                        >Mi&longs;sing Bride</name>" that you was reading while<lb/> home on
                    furlough? and do you remember<lb/> represented there as Jaqualina? (Is that
                    spelled right?)<lb/> I asked you. because if you do you are acquainted<lb/> with
                    one of my scholars, only she is awful. "spunky"<lb/> Her actions are <hi
                        rend="underline">so</hi> like Jacka's. You ought to see her<lb/> eyes. I
                    never saw such black eyes in my life. and<lb/> how she will look. I often am
                    obliged to turn<lb/> my face from her to avoid laughing.<lb/>
                </p>
                <p> Charlie, dear, what do you think of the retreat of<lb/>
                    <name>Gen. Banks</name>. Are you not angry that the rebels<lb/> again occupy
                        <name type="place">Winchester</name>? I should think your<lb/> right arm
                    would rise up in indignation, or <orig reg="something">some-<lb/> thing</orig>
                    worse. Many here think it a <sic corr="strategical">strategetial</sic><lb/>
                    movement. That the Union soldiers intended <orig reg="surrounding">surrou<lb/>
                        -nding</orig> and capturing what they can. but people will<lb/> speculate
                    upon the movements if the army; whether they<lb/> know the truth or not. Also
                    what do you think<lb/> of the evacuation of <name type="place">Corinth</name>.
                    If the rebels were<lb/>
                    <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0150"/>
                    <!--<figure rend="page" entity="NA62f04d">
                        <figDesc/>
                    </figure>-->
                    so strongly fortified as the pretended to be and had<lb/> such a large force,
                    why did they leave it? Where is their<lb/> boasted courage! There army so
                    devoted to their <orig reg="traitorous">trait-<lb/> orous</orig> institution!
                    Gone after the <name type="ship">Merimac</name><ref target="n2" n="2">2</ref>,
                    perhaps?<lb/> How excited are the northern loyalists in regard to<lb/> the call
                    for more volunteers. Boys, no more than 14 or<lb/> 15 years of age require the
                    utmost exertion of their<lb/> parents and friends to prevent them from leaving
                    all<lb/> and join the army. Old men that are bending with<lb/> age and have now
                    one foot on eternity as we might<lb/> say listen to the hard fought battles with
                    a <unclear>desirething</unclear><lb/> eye and wish they were young again for
                    nothing but to<lb/> serve our country. Oh, Charlie such scenes do my heart<lb/>
                    good. Although <del hand="h1">there</del> I would shrink from the sight of<lb/>
                    suffering. and always have. yet there <hi rend="underline">are</hi> insults for
                    which<lb/> nothing but blood can atone. Such an insult has the<lb/> Southerners
                    given to the north. Had the north and south<lb/> understood each other, never
                    would this civil war here<lb/> been. but you have enough of this in your own
                    camp<lb/> I presume and as it is nearly time to commence<lb/> school I must
                    close. Shall I ask you to excuse this<lb/> poor letter? I have written in a
                    great hurry<lb/> besides having the scholars playing all round one<lb/> I
                    presume I look "sweet" now for the scholars<lb/> have wreathed my hair with
                    flowers. one little girl<lb/> said she wanted it to look like my face.
                    Little<lb/> flatterer is'nt she. </p>


                <closer>
                    <salute>But I must say my good by<lb/> and accompanied with it are the
                        ble&longs;sings<lb/> of </salute>
                    <signed>
                        <name type="sender">Addie</name>
                    </signed>
                    <lb/>

                    <seg type="postscript">My regards to the Boys if you please<lb/>
                        <lb/> Oh! I forgot to tell you that <name>Laura</name> was up to<lb/> see me
                        last week and <name type="person" key="AEC">Hal</name> has gone to the army
                        again<lb/> he has gone to <name type="place">Columbus</name> with a company
                        that he<lb/> organized in <name type="place">Warren</name>. Darling boy, he
                        did not come up<lb/> to see me nor did I know<lb/>
                        <lb/> that he had gone till I saw in the "<name type="newspaper title"
                            >Leader</name>"<ref target="n3" n="3">3</ref> that <name>Capt.
                        Case</name><lb/> went through there last friday enroute for <abbr
                            expan="Columbus">C</abbr> with his <abbr expan="company">co.</abbr><lb/>
                    </seg>

                </closer>

            </div1>
        </body>

        <back id="d7">
            <div1 type="notes" n="1" id="d8">
                <head>Notes</head>
                <note id="n1" place="end" n="1"><seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
                    <p>XML coded with the words "book title".</p>
                </note>
                <note id="n2" place="end" n="2"><seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
                    <p>XML coded with the word "ship"</p>
                </note>
                <note id="n3" place="end" n="3"><seg type="note-symbol">3</seg>
                    <p>XML coded with the words "newspaper title"</p>
                </note>
            </div1>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
