<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0211 SYSTEM "000000766_0211" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0212 SYSTEM "000000766_0212" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0213 SYSTEM "000000766_0213" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0214 SYSTEM "000000766_0214" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NA62j04a SYSTEM "NA62j04a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62j04b SYSTEM "NA62j04b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62j04c SYSTEM "NA62j04c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NA62j04d SYSTEM "NA62j04d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NA62j04">
 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <!-- todo -->
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-10-04">4
      October 1862</date></title>

    <author>Case, Adelaide E.</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>David Seaman</name>
     <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
     <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>ETC</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">11</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NA62j04</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
    <date value="2001">2001</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, 4 October 1862</title>
      <author>Adelaide E. Case</author>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>4 pages</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p/>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p> </p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings. </p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>

  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1862-10-04">1862-10-04</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>feminine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-10">November 10th, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">
  <front id="d2">

   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>4 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1862-10-04">4 October 1862</date>

      <title>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p/>
   </div1>
  </front>
  <body id="d4">
   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Adelaide E. Case to Charles N. Tenney, <date value="1862-10-04">4 October
     1862</date></head>
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0211"/>
    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <name type="place">Mecca. </name>
      <date value="1862-10-04">October 4<hi rend="super">th</hi> 1862</date>
     </dateline>
     <salute>My darling Charley</salute>
    </opener>

    <p>Where do you guess I am <lb/> to day. Do you remember of Hal. taking your <lb/> glass--when
     you was home, over a year ago, looking <lb/> down south. and trying to "shake hands with Uncle"
     <lb/> as you then said? I am at said uncle's house.. <lb/> Why. do you ask? I will tell you.
     Aunt Sarah <lb/> is in Oberlin. spending a few weeks, and cousin <lb/> Mary. or Mamie. as we
     call her was left to "keep <lb/> house" Mamie's health not being very good and <lb/> she not
     knowing very well how to discharge the <lb/> duties incumbent upon her.--as she is not <lb/>
     thirteen years of age yet--Uncle wished me to come <lb/> and "kinder of oversee her in baking
     bread takin' <lb/> care of the pickles &amp;c." So you see instead of a <lb/>
     <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0212"/> "school-ma'am," I am now. "maid of all work. <lb/>
     Are'nt you sorry that you are not of the opinion <lb/> of Homer Powers? But of course you do
     not know <lb/> him. so I must enligten you. When I tell you that <lb/> I once heard him say
     that he could not <unclear>ever</unclear>
     <lb/> respect a woman. who could act in the capacity <lb/> of both housekeeper and lady. you
     will have learned <lb/> [rest of scan damaged] <lb/>
     <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0213"/> could I say. Were I to speak the truth--as of <lb/>
     course I must-- I should tell you that if <lb/> you <del hand="h1">are</del> are not so large a
     [piece or price]. as Uncle Sam <lb/> appears to be, yet the love that belongs to you is <lb/>
     far stronger than all that Uncle Sam has, <lb/> But you are a privileged character darling so
     <lb/> you will not <hi rend="underline">scold</hi> me for not loving my country <lb/> enough
     will you? Remember that love for my <lb/> country is paramount to every thing but <hi
      rend="underline">God and <lb/> you</hi> dearest. But do not think darling that because <lb/> I
     love you so dearly I would have you shirk <lb/> from <hi rend="underline">your duty</hi>. No.
     no. love. Although danger may <lb/> surround you uet if God wills it my love and prayers <lb/>
     shall be an armor to guard you through this strug= <lb/> =gle in safety. May God bless you
     dearest and give <lb/> you strength to discharge your duty as faithfully <lb/> as you have
     heretofore. I am not the only one <lb/> one who gazes with such proud rapture upon that <lb/>
     little band--<hi rend="underline">the noble seventh</hi>. Knowing as we do <lb/> how true they
     have always been in every engage= <lb/> =ment it is no wonder that we look forward <lb/> with
     so much confidence when we know that our <lb/> noble seventh is to participate. and of what
     proud <lb/>
     <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0214"/> emotions swell our hearts when we read <lb/> "Another
     glorious virtory" "The gallant Seventh Ohio <lb/> again distinguished iteslf" Pen can not
     describe the <lb/> feelings of my heart when I read such sentences <lb/> for I know <hi
      rend="underline">one</hi> at least <del hand="h1">in</del> of that little band <lb/> who would
     never <hi rend="underline">never</hi> falter. Is it any wonder <lb/> Charlie that I love you so
     proudly? Uncle is now <lb/> reading <add place="inline" hand="h1">aloud</add> the details of
     the battle of Sharpsburg <lb/> Often he is obliged to cease reading and wipe away the <lb/>
     great tear-drops that will flow in sympathy for <lb/> the faithful fallen, WHat a man is Gen.
     Hooker. how <lb/> indispendable were his services on the dreadful field <lb/> And yet he was
     wounded. You ask if the obscurity has <lb/> been removed at all within the past 10 days. Much,
     <lb/> very much. McClellans victories have changed the <lb/> aspect of things entirely. As you
     phrophesied, people <lb/> are even more enthusiastic over McClellan and wildly <lb/> shouting
      "<hi rend="underline">He is the man for the times</hi>" <lb/> By the tone of our letters I see
     that John Pope is no <lb/> favorite of yours. also McDowell. I do not like McDowell <lb/> but I
     believe Pope did the best he could under the circum <lb/> stances. <unclear>[T]</unclear>o what
     was his defeat attributed There seems <lb/> to have been some misunderstanding or else
     treachery. <lb/> Can you give me any light upon the subject for it is <lb/> to me the most
     unconvincible mess I ever heard of <lb/> before. I should judge that your culinary department
     <lb/> were not very extensive. Only three pints of water for <lb/> two! I believe I shoud enter
     a protest against such <lb/> scarcity. Who is your "partner" Would'nt I laugh <lb/> to see you
     cooking your breakfast or "preparing <unclear/>
     <lb/> Say Charlie, who takes the head of the table where <lb/> you live, Which do you wait upon
     first ladies or <lb/> gentlemen But </p>
    <p> "Brave boys are they <lb/> Gone at their countries call &amp;c." </p>
    <p> so I must not laugh <lb/> at you, By the way dearest did you ever hear the <lb/> song "Brave
     boys are they? If so do you not think <lb/> it splendid? The first time I heard <del hand="h1"
      >of</del> it I could <lb/> not listen to all the song it came so near home <lb/> Miss Carrie
      <unclear>Hib[l?]bee</unclear> played and sang it for me and <lb/> I had to request her to
     cease playing. I was <lb/> [end of page 4: rest of letter missing] <lb/>
    </p>

   </div1>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI.2>
