<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0381 SYSTEM "000000766_0381" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0382 SYSTEM "000000766_0382" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0383 SYSTEM "000000766_0383" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0384 SYSTEM "000000766_0384" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NC61i16a SYSTEM "NC61i16a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC61i16b SYSTEM "NC61i16b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC61i16c SYSTEM "NC61i16c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC61i16d SYSTEM "NC61i16d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>
<TEI.2 id="NC61i16">
    <teiHeader type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date
                        value="1861-09-16">September 16, 1861</date></title>

                <author>Tenney, Charles N.</author>
                <editor/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Mott Linn, Clark University</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Mott Linn, Clark University</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">15</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="etext">NC61i16</idno>
                <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
                <date value="2001">2001</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Page images have been included from the original source.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, September 16, 1861</title>


                        <author>Charles N. Tenney</author>
                        <editor/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>4 pp.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                        <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr
                            Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections,
                            Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </seriesStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p/>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
                <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
                    aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p/>
            </refsDecl>
      
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1861-09-16">1861-09-16</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <handList>
                <hand id="h1"/>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>nonfiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>masculine</term>
                    <term>American Civil War/Special Collections</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2009-11-11">November 11th, 2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
                    (uva-dl-tei).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2010-09-30">October 7th, 2010</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">

        <front id="d2">
            <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
                <head>
                    <bibl>
                        <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                        <extent>4 pp.</extent>
                        <date value="1861-09-16">September 16, 1861</date>

                        <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case</title>
                    </bibl>
                </head>
                <p>Charlie writes about life in the army while mentioning towns that the boat he is
                    writing on goes down the Ohio River. He talks about first seeing action at Cross
                    Lanes and about other Ohio regiments fighting at Carnix's Ford (presumably
                    Carnifex (or Carnifix) Ferry).</p>
            </div1>
        </front>

        <body id="d4">
            <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
                <head>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date value="1861-09-16"
                        >September 16, 1861</date></head>
                <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0381"/>

                <opener>
                    <dateline>On board the U.S. Steamer,<lb/> Silver Lake, Ohio R., Sept 16th<lb/>
                        1861</dateline>
                    <lb/>
                    <salute>Dear Friend Addie;</salute>
                </opener>
                <lb/>
                <p> War has its visissitudes as<lb/> well as the other phases of life and they<lb/>
                    are not a few I'll assure you. For the past<lb/> few weeks things have been
                    constantly<lb/> changing; one day we would be reposing<lb/> in perceived
                    security and perhaps the<lb/> next morning be awakened and moved<lb/> to haste
                    to prepare to meet the meet the enemy<lb/> who were momentarily expected to
                    come<lb/> upon us, still except in the instance of<lb/> Cross Lanes they have
                    not made an<lb/> open attack upon us. The <unclear>?</unclear><lb/>
                    <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0382"/> But you will think this is a
                    strange<lb/> opening for a letter but today it is my<lb/>
                    <q>"style"</q> Among other changes, ten, includ<lb/> ing
                    Will <unclear>B</unclear> and my self, from<lb/> Co. H. have been detailed as
                    guards on<lb/> the Steamer Silver Lake under command<lb/> of Lieut Wood. (I wish
                    very much that<lb/> Hal was in his place) We have made<lb/> these trips from
                        Camp <unclear>E</unclear>, 12 miles<lb/> above Charleston Va. to Gallipolis
                    Ohio<lb/> and we are now<lb/> We have on board several of the wounded<lb/> from
                    the battle ofCarnix's Ford<ref target="n1" n="1">1</ref> fought<lb/> last
                    Tuesday, and the remains of Col.<lb/> Lowe of the 12th O. Regt. who fell at
                    the<lb/> same battle fighting bravely. Among the<lb/> wounded are Col. Lytle of
                    the 10th Regt<lb/> Lieut. Col. <unclear>Mason</unclear> of the 13th and Capt<lb/>
                    <unclear>McGoverty</unclear> of the 13th. It is perhaps necessary<lb/> for me to
                    state that the day was won<lb/> by our gallent Ohio boys. as you ere<lb/> this
                        must<add place="inline" hand="h1">have</add> received the particulars<lb/>
                    <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0383"/> I had no idea of the feelings
                    produced<lb/> by being engaged in a battle until the<lb/> fight at Cross
                        Lanes<ref target="n2" n="2">2</ref>. These feelings were<lb/> indescribable.
                    I had no thoughts of dodging<lb/> the balls nor did I think of getting
                    killed<lb/> All I did was to take one thought of friends<lb/> (including you, my
                    dear Addie) then watch for<lb/> an opportunity to send some <unclear>
                        <q>"Secesh"</q>
                    </unclear> to<lb/>
                    <q>"Kingdom Come"</q> but although we saw them<lb/> on our front, right, and
                    left, I thought I<lb/> would reserve my fire till I was sure of<lb/> my man, or
                    at least till the order was given<lb/> to fire so lost a chance to discharge my
                    piece </p>

                <p>I cannot speak too highly of Hal. he<lb/> acted so cooly and bravely; not an
                    action<lb/> did he commit to lessen the respect and<lb/> admiration he commands
                    in the entire<lb/> regiment I would that I could send<lb/> you his portrait as
                    he stood while we<lb/> were waiting the approach of the enemy<lb/> his sword was
                    drawn and his revolver<lb/> in his left hand ready to face the<lb/>
                    <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0384"/> coming foe. Every oder was given
                    in<lb/> a manner that showed he meant to<lb/> be obayed. Suffice it to say that
                    we did merit<lb/> the apporbrium bestowed upon us by the Cin-<lb/>
                        cinnati<q>"Gazette"</q> in that they pronounced<lb/> the affair<q>"Tyler's
                        disgraceful defeat and <unclear>run</unclear>"</q><lb/>
                </p>

                <p> We are passing through a most beautiful<lb/> section of the country. we have now
                    passed<lb/> Rome, Hanging Rock, Portsmouth, Aberdeen<lb/> and Higginsport, Ohio
                    and Ashland,<lb/> Maysville, Rome, Augusta Ky.<lb/> On the Ohio side the
                    hillsides are covered with<lb/> vineyards that are now purple with grapes<lb/>
                    while the Kentucky hills are covered with<lb/> fields of Corn and Tobacco. We
                    have just<lb/> met three steamers loaded with a <unclear>part</unclear><lb/>
                            of<q>" <unclear>Piatt's</unclear> Zouave Brigade."</q> We are now
                    just<lb/> between Foster's Landing Ky. and Nevillsville Ohio.<lb/> Moscow is in
                    sight. If the Kanawha Valley was<lb/> more thickly inhabited it would be almost
                    as<lb/> beautiful as the Ohio and it soon will be <unclear>for</unclear><lb/> the
                    formation of the State of Kanakha makes it<lb/> the most important of any
                    section of the state<lb/> But I must bring this <unclear>uninteresting</unclear>
                    letter to a<lb/> close. Since I received your last letter which<lb/> I did not
                    get until we arrived at Charleston<lb/> I have written you a letter covering two
                    and a half<lb/> sheets did you get it? I have been waiting impatiently<lb/> for
                    an answer ever since but can get none. I can scarcely<lb/> get time to write we
                    have so much to do. Standing guard<lb/>
                    <unclear>?</unclear>. The boat trembles so that I doubt if you can<lb/> read
                    this rough thing. can you? We just passed<lb/> Point Pleasant Ohio and New
                    Richmond is in sight<lb/> we are now twenty miles from Cincinnati. we are<lb/>
                    running fast and the scenery is splended. Now opposite<lb/> California Ky. Hall
                    is well or was two or three days<lb/> ago. I wish he was on here. he would enjoy
                    it so much<lb/>
                </p>

                <p> With this I send you a rough pencil sketch of<lb/> Weston, where Col Tyler took
                    for the government $37000. The<lb/> view is taken from a hill overlooking the
                    camp. The stream<lb/> between Camp and town is the West fork of the
                    Monongahela<lb/>
                </p>

                <closer> But I must now stop for it is almost time for me to<lb/> go on guard. Write
                    soon Addie and a good long letter<lb/> your letters are so good and
                    entertaining. I love them.<lb/> Give my respects to Laurie and all to whom you
                    see fit and believe<lb/> me I remain <salute>Sincerely and ever yours</salute><lb/>
                    <signed>Charlie</signed><lb/> Direct to Charleston Kanawha Co. Va.<lb/>
                    <seg type="postscript">There is New Richmond<lb/> a beautiful town I wish<lb/>
                        the boat would stop I<lb/> would sketch it<lb/>
                    </seg></closer>
            </div1>
        </body>

        <back id="d6">
            <div1 type="notes" n="1" id="d7">
                <head>Notes</head>
                <note id="n1" place="end" n="1">
                    <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
                    <p>Carnifex (or Carnifix) Ferry was fought on Tuesday, Sept. 10, six days before
                        he wrote the letter. The 10th, 12th, and 13th Ohio Regiments all fought in
                        this battle.</p>
                </note>
                <note id="n2" place="end" n="2">
                    <seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
                    <p>According to "Battles and Leaders of the Civil War", Tyler's 7th Ohio was
                        routed on August 26th at Cross Lanes.</p>
                </note>
            </div1>
        </back>

    </text>
</TEI.2>
