<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0393 SYSTEM "000000766_0393" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0394 SYSTEM "000000766_0394" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0395 SYSTEM "000000766_0395" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0396 SYSTEM "000000766_0396" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NC61j01a SYSTEM "NC61j01a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC61j01b SYSTEM "NC61j01b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC61j01c SYSTEM "NC61j01c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC61j01d SYSTEM "NC61j01d.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY filename SYSTEM "filename.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>
<TEI.2 id="NC61j01">
 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date value="1861-10-01"
      >1861 October 1</date></title>

    <author>Tenney, Charles N.</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>Bret Payne, Oak Spring Garden Library</name>
     <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
     <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>Bret Payne</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NC61j01</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
    <date value="2001">2001</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, 1861 October 1</title>


      <author>Charles N. Tenney</author>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>4 pp.</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p/>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings.</p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>

  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1861-10-01">1861-10-01</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>fiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>masculine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-11">November 11th, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2010-09-30">October 7th, 2010</date>
    <respStmt>
     <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">
  <front id="d2">
   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>8 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1861-10-01">October 1, 1861</date>

      <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p> </p>
   </div1>
  </front>
  <body id="d4">

   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date value="1861-10-01">1861 October
     1</date></head>
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0393"/>

    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <name type="place">Charleston Va.</name>
      <date value="1861-10-01">Oct 1<hi rend="underline">st</hi> |61<lb/></date>
     </dateline>

     <salute>My dear Addie:</salute>
    </opener>

    <p> You will doubtless<lb/> think I mean you shall<lb/> have enough of my non<del hand="h1"
     >s</del><lb/> sense but perhaps it will be as<lb/> heretofore, you may not get this.<lb/>
     However, I will address you once<lb/> more. "I am well as usual, and hope these<lb/> few lines
     will find you the same," and having<lb/> a few moments liesure I improve<lb/> the same in
     writing to you.-There,-<lb/> cant I tell a thing two or three times<lb/> if any one can? It
     would be a<lb/> pleasure to me to be in Mecca,<lb/> to-day. I could enjoy my self, "right<lb/>
     smart, I reckon" and the Virginians<lb/> say. Mecca, I suppose is not so<lb/> lively now, as
     last year at this<lb/> time. of course the War produces its<lb/>
     <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0394"/> awful effects even in Oildom, does it<lb/> not? I, you
     percieve, am off the<lb/> boat now, the Valley has become so<lb/> quiet as not to need a guard,
     so<lb/> we came off last Saturday<lb/>
    </p>
    <p> Charleston has been the scene of<lb/> great excitement, during the past<lb/> few days. Last
     Thursday, it commen-ced<lb/> raining, and it rained heavily, too.<lb/> till Friday night. Then
     the River<lb/> commencing to swell, it continued <add place="inline" hand="h1">rising</add>
     until<lb/> Monday morning. and the whole town<lb/> was submerged, whole houses were<lb/>
     carried away and every person in town<lb/> suffered more or less. It is painful<lb/> to go
     through town and see the<lb/> devastation every where visible. The place<lb/> was a second
     Venice, the people went<lb/> about not in gondoliers, but canoes<lb/> skiffs, and on floats. I
     went<lb/> yesterday.- the waters have nearly<lb/>
     <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0395"/> subsided now--to one of the houses<lb/> to assist a
     "secesh" lady to remove<lb/> her goods, and we found the furniture<lb/> nearly ruined. A
     splendid new piano<lb/> stood in the Parlor, and it is almost<lb/> spoiled, I would not now
     give one<lb/> sixth of the original cost for it. Splendid<lb/> paintings were entirely ruined.
     Oh!<lb/> it is too bad but it cannot be helped<lb/> The more superstitious say it is on<lb/>
     account of the war in which we are<lb/> engaged the it was sent as a judgment<lb/> upon them,
     and I have no doubt<lb/> of it. At the house where I<lb/> went, there was a very pretty
     young<lb/> lady, (not as much so as Addie though)<lb/> by name of Helen Caldwell, on see-<lb/>
     ing the ruined state of her piano<lb/> and music burst into tears and exclaimed<lb/> "I did not
     care so much for my ward-<lb/> robe, but my poor piano", It <hi rend="underline">was poor"</hi><lb/>
     <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0396"/> It is feared much harm will<lb/> be done down on the
     Ohio at the<lb/> different towns but I hope not.</p>

    <p> I do not know when we shall<lb/> leave here. I hope before long. for it<lb/> is getting
     rather unhealthy here.<lb/> and in fact it would be much<lb/> better if we should move.<lb/>
     Hal's health is good &amp; he is now<lb/> acting Adjutant here, as Adj. DeForest<lb/> is at
     Ganley Bridge. Capt Asper<lb/> is now on a furlough home and<lb/> consequently Lieut Wood is
     commandant<lb/> of the Company. Some thrity of our<lb/> men are now at Camp Ganley<lb/> under
     command of Lieut Robinson of<lb/> Co. G. I do not know why they went<lb/> or what they have to
     do. Co's B &amp; D<lb/> went down to Pt. Pleasant to lay<lb/> a telegraph. to day. But you
     will<lb/> consider this more as a newsletter<lb/> than a letter of friendship or regular
     correspondence.<lb/> I am very glad you promised to correspond with me, for it is a source<lb/>
     of much pleasure to me I cannot forget the many kindnesses you showed<lb/> me while at your
     home (I almost feel as if it were <hi rend="underline">my</hi> home)<lb/> I often wish my sister
     would evince as much feeling and interest in my<lb/> welfare as <hi rend="underline">you</hi>
     have already shown, but though I have written two or<lb/> three times to her and the rest of
     the family<lb/> I can get no reply whatever. The last<lb/> time I wrote I told them "I could
     write<lb/> no more unless they thought enough of<lb/> me to answer my letters." Now Addie<lb/>
     what do you think and what would you do?<lb/><lb/> Hal<ref target="n1" n="1">1</ref> is a
     brother to me and has been ever since I became acquainted<lb/> with him. He is so kind and
     good. I don't wonder you love him.</p>

    <p>I hope for his promotion soon. and I think he <add place="inline" hand="h1">soon</add> will<lb/>
     <del hand="h1">be</del> <add place="inline" hand="h1">will recieve one</add> too, surely, no
     one<lb/> deserves it more. than he does. He is already the pride of the Seventh Regt<lb/> Do
     you know James <unclear>Beebe</unclear>? he joined this<lb/> company under the three month[s?]
     enlistment<lb/> What is he doing now? Is he at Mecca now?<lb/> The company did not like him
     very well for some<lb/> cause </p>
    <lb/>

    <p>And<ref target="n2" n="2">2</ref> Stephen Bishop too. You know his folks. do you not? How are
     they now? Some how<lb/> to me it seems as if he does not care for them <add place="inline"
      hand="h1">as he ought</add> and indeed I have heard vague<lb/> rumors that he did not take
     proper care of his family. Is this true?<lb/>
    </p>

    <closer> But I must close. Give my respects to Laura and<lb/> all other inquiring friends. and
     Dear Addie<lb/> write soon to yours ever and truely<lb/>
     <signed>Charley Tenney.</signed><lb/> To <name type="recipient">Addie</name>
    </closer>
   </div1>
   <div1 type="notes" n="1" id="d6">
    <head>Notes</head>

    <note id="n1" place="end" n="1"><seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
     <p>The following text is written in the margins of page 3.</p>
    </note>
    <note id="n2" place="end" n="2"><seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
     <p>The following text is written in the margins of page 2.</p>
    </note>
   </div1>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI.2>
