<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0613 SYSTEM "000000766_0613" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0614 SYSTEM "000000766_0614" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0615 SYSTEM "000000766_0615" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0616 SYSTEM "000000766_0616" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0617 SYSTEM "000000766_0617" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0618 SYSTEM "000000766_0618" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0619 SYSTEM "000000766_0619" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0620 SYSTEM "000000766_0620" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NC62i05">
 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <!-- todo -->
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date value="1862-09-05">5
      Spetember 1862</date></title>

    <author>Tenney, Charles N.</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>David Seaman</name>
     <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
     <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>ETC</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">12</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NC62i05</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
    <date value="2005">2005</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case</title>


      <author>Charles N. Tenney</author>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>8 pages</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p/>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p> </p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings. </p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>

  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1862-09-05">1862-09-05</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>masculine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-16">November 16th, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>

 <text id="d1">
  <front id="d2">

   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>8 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1862-09-05">1862-09-05</date>

      <title>Letter from Charles Tenney to Adelaide Case</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p/>
   </div1>
  </front>
  <body id="d4">
   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date value="1862-09-05">5 Spetember
      1862</date></head>
    <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0613"/>
    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <name type="place">Camp in Maryland, 3 miles above Georgetown, </name>
      <date value="1862-09-05">Sept. 5th, 1862</date>
     </dateline>
     <salute>My own darling Addie;</salute>
    </opener>

    <p> At last, I have a chance to write a few lines,with a hope that it will soon reach you. I
     wrote you a good long letter from Culpepper <unclear/> on the 18th of August, but as we left
     there that day, I supposed it has never been sent. On the 20th, an order was recieved from Gen.
     Halleck forbidding the further transmission of mails, and until now I have had no opportunity
     to send a line to apprise you of my safety. I know how you must suffer, and how thoughless you
     must think me, but all I can plead is the inexorable character of military orders. I have much
     to write you as soon as we can remain 24 hours in a place. Since the 18th, we have been
     constantly under arms and for more than 3/4 of the time under fire from the enemy, but we have
     not lost a man. I have kept a full journal of all our proceedings, which I shall send to the
     Chronicle for publication, as soon as I can. </p>
    <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0614"/>

    <p>Out of 18 days, we have march 11, and but two nights have we slept under a blanket, and those
     the last two nights. But scarce is a murmer of dissatisfaction have I heard, except at the
     almost <unclear/> manner in which we have been deprived of news from home. But is not the
     record of the last three weeks a dark one? While on the 11th of Aug. we had a Point-d'apprei on
     the Rapidan river, we have the Potomac for a base of operations- not to say <hi
      rend="underline"> of defense</hi>. </p>
    <p>We have lost in killed, surrounded, and prisoners not less than twenty thousand men.
     <unclear/> poorly has John Pope met the expectations of the nation. (No event has caused such
     general and genuine rejoicing in the army, as has the <unclear/> of Gen. McClellan to the
     command of the entire army of Virginia, I confess that my confidence in him is <unclear/> and
     <unclear/> and I believe all feel the same. Gen. Pope was too strong in written pronuniciamento
     (whew what a long word!) upon the start to hold out good in action. While he condcuted a small
     army in the west most admirably, against really inferior generals, he has <pb n="3"
      entity="DSSR_000000766_0615"/> proven himself incompetent to handle a large force, against a
     wily and subtle Jackson or an accomplished Lee. </p>
    <p>But I guess this will not be very interesting to you, so I will change the subject. (while we
     have been performing arduous marches and course temmarches, through rain, mud, sunshine and
     dust. <del hand="h1"> "I have" </del> and with less that 1/3 rations of Bread and coffee, I
     have not forgotten that it was for my country and thee for whom I was fighting, and though we
     passed unscathed through the sotrm of balls and skulls, I have remembered that it was in answer
     to your prayers that the bullets <unclear/> past me harmlessly, and the horrid shell burst in
     rain. I have enjoyed perfect health during the entire time, not even contracting a cold, not
     withstanding the exposure we have endured. Had I been allowed to write to you, and to recieve
     letters from you. I should have been happy, but instead my mind has been filled with vague
     fears for your health and happiness, and I am as anxious as ever. God grant my fears may be
     unfounded. </p>
    <p>As if to add to my anxiety, I have not heard <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0616"/> one
     word from Hal since we left Alexandria. <unclear/> he and what is he doing? <unclear/> Corps)
     <unclear/> nearly surrrounded at the Bristoe Station <unclear/> since, by a large rebel force,
     but they <unclear/> "cute" enough for and loved general for <unclear/> down the Brentsville
     road, as though <unclear/> going down to Fredericksburg, then turned <unclear/> the flank of
     the enemy just above <unclear/> Junction, croped Bull Run, and seemed <unclear/> near
     Centreville. This was on Sunday <unclear/> marched eleven miles making but <unclear/> a few
     minutes each. When we <unclear/> about a mile from Bull Run, we saw <unclear/> fifteen rebel
     cavalry.--these were the videttes <unclear>, so you see how narrowly we escaped. <unclear/>
      long soon we to remain secure at Cent-</unclear> for the very next day, they made a deour to
     <unclear/> to Fairfax, VA, thus placing us again in <unclear/> Accordingly we evacuated C.
     Banks' <unclear/> taking the direct road to Alexandria, while <unclear/> to Alexandira, while
     <unclear/> mess went toward Fairfax. Already <unclear/> storm arose shortly after we started.
     <unclear/> attacked Stevens' and Kearney's divisions. </p>

    <pb n="5" entity="DSSR_000000766_0617"/>

    <p>on the Fairfax road, but even repulsed with a heavy <unclear/> . Gens. Stevens and Kearney
     were both killed. We could hear the fighting but could render no assistance. That night we lay
     in the rain and mud without fire or ven a blanket. The next day we were delayed by the heavy
     trains and did not reach our camp- 4 miles from Alexa.- until nearly two oclock at night. The
     next P.M. we moved next to Arlington Heights,- to the rear of Fort Albany, and as we supposed
     to go into camp for a few days. But about mid-night orders came to get ready to start for
     Ports-ville Md. with 2 days rations, at 8 1/2 A.M. We started about noon yesterday, crossed the
     river at Georgetown, and halted here. Col. Asper joined us, and took command at the
     Rappahannock, on the 23rd. and is with us at present. He gives very good satisfaction. </p>
    <p>Gen Moore is still at Alexandria in the Hospital, and so is my friend Bob Murray (Will Boaden
     is in Washington. He is recovering slowly. <pb n="6" entity="DSSR_000000766_0618"/> I trust
     soon to record the victorious achievements of Little Mac. and to hear of the utter defeat or
     capture of Lee and Jackson. </p>
    <p>I have not recieved a letter from you since we left Culpepper. How soon may I expect one? How
     lonsome I have been, and am now! Yes, I feel that "alls for the best," I wish I had mor time to
     write. I would write you 3 or 4 sheets jull, but the mail closes in just 5 minutes so I must
     close. </p>
    <p>Don't fail to write soon-- Give my love to <hi rend="underline"> Addie mine, </hi> and
     remember me to Dora. </p>
    <p>Best assured that although we cannot converse as frequently as we could wish, yet- my heart
     is with thee forever, and you are continually in my thoughts. </p>
    <closer> Please write very often to your own Affelction and loving Charley. <lb/> C.H. 7th.
     R.O.V.I.<lb/> 1st Brigade, 2nd Div. Banks Corps.<lb/> Via Washington, D.C.<lb/> (Care of
     Capt.-McClellan)<lb/>
    </closer>

    <pb entity="DSSR_000000766_0619"/>
    <pb entity="DSSR_000000766_0620"/>
   </div1>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI.2>
