<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0633 SYSTEM "000000766_0633" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0634 SYSTEM "000000766_0634" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0635 SYSTEM "000000766_0635" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0636 SYSTEM "000000766_0636" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0637 SYSTEM "000000766_0637" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0638 SYSTEM "000000766_0638" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY N620925a SYSTEM "620925a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY N620925b SYSTEM "620925b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY N620925c SYSTEM "620925c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY N620925d SYSTEM "620925d.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY N620925e SYSTEM "620925e.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY N620925f SYSTEM "620925f.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NC62i25">
    <teiHeader type="migrated">
        <!-- todo -->
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date
                        value="1862-09-25">25 September 1862</date></title>

                <author>Tenney, Charles N.</author>
                <editor/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>David Seaman</name>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>ETC</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">21</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="etext">NC62i25</idno>
                <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
                <date value="2001">2001</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, 25 September 1862</title>
                        <author>Charles N. Tenney</author>
                        <editor/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>6 pages</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                        <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr
                            Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections,
                            Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </seriesStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p/>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p> </p>
                <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
                    aid in establishing analytical groupings. </p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p/>
            </refsDecl>

        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1862-09-25">1862-09-25</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <handList>
                <hand id="h1"/>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>nonfiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>masculine</term>
                    <term>American Civil War/Special Collections</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2009-11-16">November 16th, 2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
                    (uva-dl-tei).</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text id="d1">
        <front id="d2">

            <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
                <head>
                    <bibl>
                        <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                        <extent>6 pp.</extent>
                        <date value="1862-09-25">25 September 1862</date>

                        <title>Letter from Charles Tenney to Adelaide Case</title>
                    </bibl>
                </head>
                <p/>
            </div1>
        </front>
        <body id="d4">
            <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
                <head>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date value="1862-09-25">25
                        September 1862</date></head>
                <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0633"/>

                <opener>
                    <salute>My own loved Addie;</salute>
                </opener>


                <p> Here I am once more in Virginia-- again on sacred soil. Not only in Va. but way
                    up on the Blue Ridge, where the very clouds are often under our feet. It would
                    be very pleasant, if it were not for two very serious drawbacks.-- It is quite
                    cold, and we have to go down the mountain half a mile for water, There is a kind
                    of Block house up here, from which and we have a splendid view of the
                    surrounding country, particularly to the north and west. We can see the
                    church-spires of Martinsburg with the aid of a field glass.- 21 miles distant
                    and were it not for intervening hills and forest we could see Winchester. Away
                    as far as the eye can reach the Alleghenies raise their lofty peaks, far above
                    the heights of North Mountain and the Shenandoah Mountains both of which
                    intervene. As far as romance goes, this is by far the most interesting place we
                    have been in. </p>

                <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0634"/>

                <p> Well, we are here, and romance of reality, we must bear all without a murmur. I
                    wrote you from Maryland Heights a few days since, just to assure you of my
                    safety, and said I had two letters to answer. Last evening, I was again
                    gladdened by the receipt of another of your priceless <unclear/> , and as there
                    is our prosepect of immediate removal, I thought I would devote my time to
                    replying to the three still unanswered, so "here goes." </p>
                <p> I was very much pleased with your description of and comments upon the marriage
                    of Mr. Hathaway. Indeed, I think if I were a lady, and were engaged to a young
                    man, at such a crisis as existed at the breaking out of the Rebellion, I should
                    have strenuous <unclear/> my <unclear/> to the reserve of our glorious Union;
                    and if he were disposed to <hi rend="underline"> display the white
                    feather</hi>,-- as in the case of Hathaway-- I should have summarily dismissed
                    him as unworthy the respect not to say <hi rend="underline"> love</hi> of any
                    patriotic minded person. Indeed in any estimation, the love of our country
                    should be paramount to all but the <hi rend="underline">"love of God."</hi> If I
                    do battle for my country; am I not vindicating the cause of all we hold dear? --
                    am I not resenting an insult to every loyal heart; whether male or female? Most
                    assuredly I am, and, should count myself unworthy the least of <hi
                        rend="underline">your</hi>notice, <hi rend="underline"> my treasure, </hi>
                    were I to sit idly by, at this <unclear/> moment. Turly "coward is his name. <hi
                        rend="underline"> "Love honor, and obey." God bless you </hi> for your
                    outspoken indignation at such a man. So you thought our national sky very much
                    darkened, about the 10th of Sept. Has the osbcurity been removed at all within
                    the past 10 days? Yes, it did sound stragely "Maryland and Ohio invaded." and
                    one would <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0635"/> have thought we stood sadly
                    in need of a man of nerve and fortitude, as in truth, we did, but has not Gen.
                    McClellan sustained all I ascribed to him? Has he not resisted the charges of
                    "Ultra" peep of the north, such as daily emanated from the N.Y. Tribune? </p>
                <p> You know the Tribune has always claimed to be the organ of the Union party?
                    Well, its influence in the border states has been anything but favorable to our
                    cause, -- on the contrary, by its indiscriminate attacks upon Gen. McClellan,
                    and other generals who did not precisely agree with that sheet, in every <hi
                        rend="underline"> political</hi> point of view, however slight. It has
                    tended to sow distrust and discontent. I have conversed with very many of the
                    Army of the Peninsula, both officers and men, and they love McClellan with a
                    feeling beyond mere respect. No one knows the result of an engagement better
                    than the men who participate therein and I have not conversed with a soldier,
                    officer, or private, who will say that McClellan was defeated in either of the
                    battles before Richmond but on the contrary, they say that in every case, the
                    enemy was driven from the field. But in the case of the six days fighting where
                    the aim of McClellan was to change his base of supplies to a point, where if he
                    could not have the cooperation the troops <hi rend="underline"> promised hims by
                        the Secretary of War</hi> he could at least be in a position where the
                    famous Raid upon Tunstall's Stn. could not be renewed, -- in this case, each
                    day, with its victory, left him in a situation equally as critical as at first,
                    so the only alternative was to secure his point at Harrison's Landing, as he had
                    not the support requisite to an advance upon the works at Richmond. But those
                    cavillers, ready to use the least seeming advan-tage to cry down a really good
                    general, put their fingers to their 
                    
                    <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0636"/>
                    ears, and ran toward Fortress Monroe, crying <hi rend="underline"> defeat,
                        defeat. </hi> I know not what the "C. Herald" based its assertion upon that
                    Gen. McClellan's army was demoralized, but if I know anything of a body of
                    men,-- and having been in the army 17 months, I ought to.-- then Gen.
                    McClellan's army was very far from being demoralized, but on the contrary were
                    in a high state of discipline, though very faint and weary. The plain truth is,
                    if <hi rend="underline">any</hi> army was "demoralized", it was John Pope's-- a
                    portion of it commanded by McDowell notwithstanding the Herald's adoration of
                    Gen. Pope. I am sorry Gen. McClellan has no more friends in the north, but I am
                    sure if the people of the north knew this brave man as well as the army does,
                    they would say with us, <hi rend="underline"> and against the N.Y. Tribune</hi>
                    "he is the man for the times." I venture prophecy--<hi rend="underline"> Gen.
                        McClellan's star shall rise, and the nation will praise his valour and
                        statesmanlike conduct.</hi> Have you not noticed that the Herlad, &amp;
                    Tribune have all along evinced a disposition to condemnation our noble
                    president? The aim is the same-- to destory the present administration as
                    Secretary Seward told G.F. Train a few days since <hi rend="underline">"Put out
                        McClellan and break up the administration."</hi> You ask "what will become
                    of the country?" I will tell you as "Mr. Seward told Mr. Train--<hi
                        rend="underline">"You cannot stop God's waterworks; the great wheels turn
                        around, the wheat comes down, the big millstones move, and the wheat will
                        come out flour in all good time." </hi> Be of good cheer my love to me the
                    prospect seems clearer than it has since at any time for the past three months
                    and we must recollect that "tis darkest just before day." </p>
                <p> Our men "conquered" no, never: while a hundred patriot hearts remain, a traitor
                    shall not prosper. I admire your adherence to this belief, and that you may
                    never have cause to change yours. </p>

                <pb n="5" entity="DSSR_000000766_0637"/><!-- Missing transcription-->
                <pb n="6" entity="DSSR_000000766_0638"/>
                <p> But you made inquiry about "the boys". <hi rend="underline">"Is he [Gen. Moore]
                        my friend too?"</hi> A naive question, turly. Of course, he is. Who is not,
                    who knows you, or have seen your lovely features? But he is really your friend,
                    and often requests to be remembered to you. I must tell you what he told me once
                    on his return from home last winter. Said he, -- "Charlie were it not that you
                    have a better claim upon her affections, I would be tempted to love her myself.
                    She is the most interesting and <hi rend="underline">noble</hi> young lady I
                    ever saw." How he learned that I love you, I could not say: I never told him,
                    and yet he said, "she loves you." George is a noble boy, (boy-ha!-ha!) and is
                    doing well, I learn. John Chafee was in the engagement at Culpepper and at
                    Sharpsburg, from both of which he came our all right. He is well. </p>
                <p> Bishop hasx never been wit the regt since the Winchester Battle, and we recieved
                    official notice of his discharge a few days since. No one mourns his exit from
                    the company--"requiescat-in pace." The other boys are doing well. </p>
                <p> Now that "Maryland, my Maryland" is liberated from "southern scum", the
                    apprehensions of the North must be relived in a measure. Certin it is that
                    Pennsylvania is safe, and if we soldies of 17 months standing made be allowed to
                    judge the rebel horders might be driven to a more genial atmosphere to their
                    polluted hearts than the north, and that in double quick time. Here is one thing
                    which inspires me with confidence in "Little Mac." In conversing with a capture
                    rebel lieutenant, he told me that "so long as Pop was in command, they
                    entertained no fears but that the incusion into Maryland would prove a sweep;
                    but as soon as Gen. McClellan took command, they began to tremble. For while
                    they despised Pope, they respected and feared McClellan." He said that "he for
                    his part, knew as soon as he learned, that he had taken Pope's commany that <hi
                        rend="underline"> they were a whipped army.</hi> Is not proof from the enemy
                    conclusive? </p>
                <p> I have not yet heard from Hallie. <del hand="h1">yet</del> I supposed he has
                    been mustered out of the service ere this, and resumed his duties in his office,
                    has he not? Addie, has your paper ever mentioned to you the fact of my writing
                    to him from Alexandira, asking his consent to our union at a time specified by
                    you? I wrote you concerning it from <unclear/> peper, but I guess the letter has
                    not been sent, and is still in the Captain's trunk. I recieved for a reply one
                    which gave me great satisfation, and which places me under a thousand
                    obligations to your- <hi rend="underline"> our father</hi> He says <hi
                        rend="underline"> "If it is your and Addie's wish to connect your destinies
                        for life, you shall have my best wishes and approval, unless that I shall
                        learn of some dishonor attached to you or her." </hi>
                </p>

                <!-- See first page.
first page continuation -->

                <p> Those words have given me most unalloyed pleasure, and ought I not to be
                    grateful? Truly it was a happy day for me when I first saw my darling Addie. You
                    have a good Father and may God grant that I may always enjoy his love and
                    esteem. I am patiently waiting for this unfathomable war to be terminated, so
                    that I may return to claim my precious one; and at the same time I pray that
                    ours may not be the wedding of a <hi rend="underline">Hathaway</hi>. How I wish
                    I had materials for sketching? I would like to send you sketches of the things
                    of interest around the memorable "Harper's Ferry." Here is the ruins of the
                    arsenal which John Brown took possession of at his famous insurrection. and the
                    Engine house where he confirmed his prisoners,-- the ruins of the bridges across
                    the two rivers,-- the rocky crags wehre Brown was wont to observe the
                    proceedings of the people below, and a hundred other interesting scenes. </p>
                <p> But as I have no conviences for carrying the materials, that pleasure must be
                    forbidden. But I percieve that my space is fast becoming limited, so I must soon
                    close. Then I have written quite a lengthy epistle have I not? and does it weary
                    you to read so long ones? You must write soon and good long letters, and
                    remember that your Charlies is ever faithful, and though he may sometimes be in
                    a situation where he cannot write as often or as extended as he would like, yet
                    he will do so as often as possible, and will try to make them as interesting as
                    is possible. </p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Give my love to all and write soon to your loving</salute>
                    <signed>Charlie</signed>. </closer>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>
