<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0647 SYSTEM "000000766_0647" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0648 SYSTEM "000000766_0648" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0649 SYSTEM "000000766_0649" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0650 SYSTEM "000000766_0650" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NC62j13a SYSTEM "NC62j13a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62j13b SYSTEM "NC62j13b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62j13c SYSTEM "NC62j13c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62j13d SYSTEM "NC62j13d.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>

<TEI.2 id="NC62j13">
    <teiHeader type="migrated">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date
                        value="1862-10-13">13 October 1862</date></title>

                <author>Tenney, Charles</author>
                <editor/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
                    <name>Nora Yeh</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Nora Yeh, University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">22</num> kilobytes</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
                <idno type="etext">NC62j13</idno>
                <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
                <date value="2000">2000</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note>
                    <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, October 13, 1862</title>


                        <author>Charles Tenney</author>
                        <editor/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent>4 p.</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher/>
                        <pubPlace/>
                        <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr
                            Nettleton Civil War Collection, Department of Special Collections,
                            Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <seriesStmt>
                        <p/>
                    </seriesStmt>
                    <notesStmt>
                        <note>
                            <p/>
                        </note>
                    </notesStmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
                <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to
                    aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <p/>
            </refsDecl>
           
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <date value="1862-10-13">1862-10-13</date>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <handList>
                <hand id="h1"/>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
            <textClass>
                <keywords>
                    <term>nonfiction</term>
                    <term>prose</term>
                    <term>masculine</term>
                    <term>American Civil War;Special Collections</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords>
                    <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Corrector</resp>
                    <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2009-11-16">November 16th, 2009</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
                    (uva-dl-tei).</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date value="2010-09-30">October 14th, 2010</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>corrector</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text id="d1">

        <front id="d2">
            <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
                <head>
                    <bibl>
                        <abbr>ALS</abbr>
                        <extent>4 pp.</extent>
                        <date value="1862-10-13">October 13th, 1862</date>

                        <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case</title>
                    </bibl>
                </head>

                <p>Charlie write to Addie from Harper's Ferry, Va. He was very happy about Hal's
                    promotion and talked about the temporary replacement by Seth Coon to be his
                    partner. He and several partners built a log house for themselves because there
                    was little space for new recruits. He went through lengthy details explaining
                    his delay to respond to two letters from her. He also told her why General Rope
                    was defeated. And what he expects a wife to do in the matter of housekeeping.
                    The postscript told Addie that they might stay put for the winter.</p>
            </div1>
        </front>
        <body id="d4">


            <div1 type="letter" n="1862-10-13" id="d5">
                <head>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date value="1862-10-13">13
                        October 1862</date></head>
                <pb n="1" entity="DSSR_000000766_0647"/>

                <opener>
                    <abbr expan="October">Oct.</abbr>
                     <name type="place">Harper's Ferry, Va.,</name>
                    <date value="1862-10-13"><abbr expan="October">Oct.</abbr> 13<hi rend="super"
                        >th</hi> 1862</date>
                    <lb/>
                    <salute>My own darling:</salute>
                </opener>
                <lb/>
                <p>Permit me to address a few lines to you, hoping to<lb/> interest you for a few
                    moments. There, is not that in style? Now that<lb/> I am to correspond with a <hi
                        rend="underline">Colonel</hi>'s sister, I suppose I must "put on a<lb/>
                    little style." I - I - <hi rend="underline">can't</hi>, -- dont know how. I
                    evo-(come pretty near<lb/> writing a naughty word)- rather not try, as I shall
                    do as I see proper, unless<lb/> there be certain contingencies arising. How is
                        it? <hi rend="underline">Must</hi> I?<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>Your Charlie is well as usual, and of course as happy as he<lb/> can be away from
                    thee, so you need not fear for me. I was so<lb/> glad to hear of Hal's
                    promotion, I threw my cap into the air and laughed<lb/> for joy. How do you
                    suppose it made Brig. <abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr> <name type="person">E. R.
                        Tyler</name> feel<lb/> when he learned that, that Lieutenant whom he
                    persecuted and affected<lb/> "taken down." It nettled Lt. Col. <name
                        type="person">Asper</name> considerably. I understood that<lb/> "he thought
                    the military committee might have selected some one <hi rend="underline"
                    >older</hi> and<lb/> more fitted for the position than Case, especially since he
                    had that rupture<lb/> with <abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr> <name type="person"
                        >Tyler</name>. Now <hi rend="underline">I</hi> think he would like the
                        position <hi rend="underline">himself</hi>.<lb/> but he is eminently <hi
                        rend="underline">dis</hi>qualified for any office higher than the one he
                    now<lb/> occupies. <unclear/> other officers in the regiment, who thought that by
                    taking<lb/> sides with Tyler they would court his favor, and gain his influences
                    to<lb/> promote <hi rend="underline">themselves</hi>, also feel rather annoyed at
                    his (Hal's) rapid rise<lb/> For my part I congratulate him and tender to him my
                    warmest<lb/> sympathies and earnest goodwill. May God be with him.<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>But I forget that I have two letters from you to answer, and<lb/> you will wonder
                    why I have not sooner replied seeing that we remain<lb/>
                    <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0648"/> in camp. I will explain. Since I wrote
                    you last we have<lb/> changed the immediate location of the Camp,
                        our <unclear>Sabley</unclear>tents have come,<lb/> and we had to clear
                        off <orig reg="off">offas</orig> the ground before pitching them, and
                    when<lb/> we got them up as nice as you please, a lot of recruits came, and
                    it<lb/> was found that we had not tents enough. Accordingly <name type="person"
                        >Seth Coon</name>,<lb/> myself and <hi rend="underline">another</hi>
                    enterprising young man set to work and built a log<lb/> house, 8ftx10. for
                        our <orig reg="special">especial</orig> accommodation, exclusive of recruits,
                    Said house<lb/> is heated by means of a stove, manufactured of sheet iron, by
                    our selves, and<lb/> lighted by means of a canvass skylight. Altogether, when
                    finished (for it is not<lb/> yet complete,) it will be a comfortable dwelling
                    place for three U.S. privates.<lb/> My time has been so completely taken up in
                    this work, with my usual "guard duty, (We are now Headquarter guards to <abbr
                        expan="General">Gen.</abbr> <name type="person">Georg.</name>) that I could
                    not sooner write<lb/> - and this is my reason. <hi rend="underline">Now</hi>
                        for <unclear>practically</unclear> replying.<lb/>
                </p>
                <p>I was not at all pained to learn that you were housekeeping, nor<lb/> was I ever
                    of young Powers' mind. I not only respect a lady who can act<lb/> in both
                    capacities but on the contrary, I consider no lady's accomplishments are<lb/>
                    perfect unless she has a <hi rend="underline">general</hi>, if not a
                    complete<!-- overstrike -->understanding knowledge of house<lb/> keeping. Yet I
                    do not hold as a sequence that every lady <hi rend="underline">must</hi>, of <hi
                        rend="underline">necessity</hi> or <hi rend="underline">choice</hi>, <hi
                        rend="underline">be</hi> a housekeeper; by no manner of means, yet it is
                        a <hi rend="underline">conveneince</hi>, at<lb/> times, to understand how to
                    bake a little bread, or even to sweep a floor.<lb/> But do not think that I
                    would make a servant of <hi rend="underline">my</hi> wife, <hi rend="underline"
                        >not for the world</hi><lb/> would I. Next your God, you love me but," <hi
                        rend="underline">God bless you</hi>.<lb/> darling, for such devotion. Did
                    you know that your love gives more strength<lb/> to do my duty, and that "Love
                    makes the hours go lightly by"? No, love I will <hi rend="underline"
                    >not</hi><lb/> "scold" you for loving me thus well, indeed I fear I shall
                    deserve a treatment of<lb/> that "antidote for wrong" for not being good enough
                    for you. But my heart, my<lb/> all is yours, and <hi rend="underline">yours
                        forever</hi>.</p>
                <p>Now for the military department of my letter. You make inquiries<lb/> of <abbr
                        expan="General">Gen.</abbr> <name type="person">Pope</name> - why he was
                    defeated on the <name type="place">Rappahannock</name> etc.<lb/>
                    <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0649"/> To begin I will make this
                        statement. <abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr> <name type="person">Pope</name>,
                    although he should<lb/> himself competent to handle a single corpo in the field,
                    while in the West;<lb/> is insufficient in himself to wield an enormous army of
                    120,000 men.<lb/> Other men are so, not only in the North but in the South, but
                    unfortunately<lb/> for us the South understands this better than ourselves,
                    hence, although it was the <orig reg="popular">pop-<lb/> pular</orig> wish of the
                    people that <name type="person">Jackson</name> should be placed at the head of
                    the Confederate<lb/>
                    <date value="1862-10-13">Oct. 17</date>Gen army, he was assigned to only a
                        single <hi rend="underline">corpo d'armee</hi>, while. <name type="person"
                    >Lee</name>, although lacking<lb/> in that peculiar quality- <hi rend="underline"
                        >dash</hi>- was made first in command, because he could plan<lb/> a campaign
                    on a <hi rend="underline">large scale</hi>, and handle the entire force with
                    ease, leaving for<lb/> generals of smaller commands the rapid moves to. Now <abbr
                        expan="General">Gen.</abbr> <name type="person">Rope</name><lb/> was
                    altogether too fast in making his advances into <name type="place"
                    >Virginia</name>, for while he was <orig reg="making"><lb/> ing</orig> the bold
                    advance directly upon the rebel <name type="place">Capitol</name>, he did not
                        sufficiently <hi rend="underline">guard</hi><lb/>
                    <hi rend="underline">the flanks</hi>. Thus the Valley of Va. was comparatively
                    free from our army, while<lb/> there should have been a strong force acting in
                    concert with the grand army.<lb/> And in like manner the line of the <name
                        type="place">Rappahannock</name> from the edge of Culpepper County<lb/> was
                    left without <hi rend="underline">even</hi> a <hi rend="underline">picket
                    line</hi>, to <hi rend="underline">within eight miles of <name type="place"
                            >Fredericksburg</name>!</hi><lb/>
                </p>
                <p>You will see that as <abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr> <name type="person"
                    >Pope</name> had his entire army maped in the vicinity of<lb/> Culpepper,
                    nothing was easier for the enemy than to turn either flunk. When this<lb/> at
                    last became evident to the worthy General, instead of having <name type="person"
                        >Burnside</name> and<lb/>
                    <name type="person">McClellan</name> come to his relief <hi rend="underline"
                        >via</hi> <name type="place">Fredericksburg</name> and the <name type="place"
                        >Rappahannock</name>, he ordered<lb/> them to come to his rear by way of
                    Alexandria, and the same course taken<lb/> by himself, so that is <name
                        type="person">McClellan</name> had been two days earlier, he would have<lb/>
                    been on the <name type="place">Rappahannock</name> and <name type="place"
                        >Washington</name> <hi rend="underline">unprotected</hi>; for the "dash" of<lb/>
                    <name type="person">Jackson</name> <hi rend="underline">by <name type="person"
                        >Lee</name>'s order</hi>, had completely outfluncked <name type="person"
                    >Pope</name>'s entire army, placing it<lb/> in the greatest danger of <unclear/>
                    annihilation, had it not been for the timely presence of <abbr expan="General"
                        >Gen.</abbr> <name type="person">McClellan</name><lb/> which retarded <name
                        type="person">Jackson</name> materially. But you will say that it<lb/>
                        was <name type="person">Pope</name>'s men who fought the disastrous 2<hi
                        rend="super">d</hi> Battle of Bull Run. In part, it was and<lb/> in part
                        by <name type="person">McClellan</name>'s men, but had it not been for the
                    presence of the army of the<lb/> Peninsula, the "grand advance" of the rebel
                    army would have been neither more nor less<lb/>
                    <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0650"/> than an assault upon our own <name
                        type="place">Capitol</name>. While we came upon the<orig reg="Rappahannock"
                        ><lb/> pahannock</orig>, we could see plainly the rebel troop across the
                    river, moving around to our<lb/> right, and <abbr expan="General"
                        >Gen.</abbr> <name type="person">Sigel</name> requested permission to
                    intercept the movement, (as might have<lb/> been done by guarding the passes of
                        the <name type="place">Blue Ridge</name> and Thoroughfare Units.) but <abbr
                        expan="General">Gen.</abbr><lb/>
                    <name type="person">Pope</name> told him it was but a ruse, and that he should
                    be needed on the river.<lb/> Sigel was right, <name type="person">Pope</name> was
                    wrong. The rebels went around, and <abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr> <name
                        type="person">Banks</name><lb/> corps which was the rear-guard -- just where
                    the advance should have been was once<lb/> cut off and surrounded, but by the
                    superior skill of <abbr expan="General">Gen.</abbr> <name type="person"
                    >Banks</name> we were <orig reg="extricated">extrica-<lb/> ted</orig>. Haven't
                    made the matter any clearer for you. By the way, <abbr expan="General"
                        >Gen.</abbr> <name type="person">Halleck</name> said<lb/> at the time <name
                        type="person">Pope</name> was appointed that he had but little confidence in
                    him.</p>

                <p>Since I<del hand="h1" rend="line-through">wrote you last</del>commenced painting
                    this, we haven't around our camp down the hill<lb/> nearer to water but our
                    splendid view is impaired some what; I was interrupted<lb/> while writing for
                    that purpose, thus we have the labor of clearing another encampment to<lb/>
                    perform. You ask me who is my partner, <name type="person">Seth Coon</name>, sho
                    has<lb/> been absent all summer, in the Pioneer Corps, is acting in that
                    capacity now, while my<lb/> regular partner, Bob. Murray is still in the
                    Hospital, having been surrounded at<lb/> Cedar Mountain.</p>

                <closer>But I must close this as the boys are waiting for me to help fix the tent.
                    Please give my love to all. not forgetting <hi rend="underline">Addie</hi>,<lb/>
                    and write soon, to<lb/>
                    <salute>Your own loving</salute><signed>
                        <name type="person">Charley,</name>
                    </signed><lb/>
                    <seg type="postscript">It is said that we remain here this
                winter.</seg></closer>
            </div1>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI.2>
