<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!NOTATION jpg SYSTEM "JPEG">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0469 SYSTEM "000000766_0469" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0470 SYSTEM "000000766_0470" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0471 SYSTEM "000000766_0471" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0472 SYSTEM "000000766_0472" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0473 SYSTEM "000000766_0473" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0474 SYSTEM "000000766_0474" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0475 SYSTEM "000000766_0475" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000000766_0476 SYSTEM "000000766_0476" NDATA jpg>

<!--<!ENTITY NC62a01a SYSTEM "NC62a01a.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62a01b SYSTEM "NC62a01b.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62a01c SYSTEM "NC62a01c.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62a01d SYSTEM "NC62a01d.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62a01e SYSTEM "NC62a01e.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62a01f SYSTEM "NC62a01f.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62a01g SYSTEM "NC62a01g.jpg" NDATA jpg>
<!ENTITY NC62a01h SYSTEM "NC62a01h.jpg" NDATA jpg>-->
<!ENTITY longs "s" ><!-- long s -->
]>
<TEI.2 id="NC62a01">
 <teiHeader type="migrated">
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title type="main">Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date value="1862-01-01"
      >1862 January 01</date></title>

    <author>Tenney, Charles N</author>
    <editor/>
    <respStmt>
     <resp/>
     <name/>
     <resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
     <name>Crabbe, Stuart John</name>
     <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
     <name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
     <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
     <name>Crabbe, Stuart John</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
    <idno type="etext">NC62a01</idno>
    <idno type="callNo">MSS 11616</idno>
    <availability>
     <p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
     <!--<p n="public">URL: http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/civilwar/nettleton </p>-->
     <p n="copyright"/>
    </availability>
    <date value="2001">2001</date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <seriesStmt>
    <title>The Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War Collection</title>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
    <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Nettletoncivilwarletters</idno>
   </seriesStmt>
   <notesStmt>
    <note>
     <p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
    </note>
   </notesStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <biblFull>
     <titleStmt>
      <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, 1862 January 01</title>


      <author>Charles N. Tenney</author>
      <editor/>
      <respStmt>
       <resp/>
       <name/>
      </respStmt>
     </titleStmt>
     <editionStmt>
      <p/>
     </editionStmt>
     <extent>8 pp.</extent>
     <publicationStmt>
      <publisher/>
      <pubPlace/>
      <idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted: Manuscript letter, Corinne Carr Nettleton Civil War
       Collection, Department of Special Collections, Alderman Library, UVa.</idno>
     </publicationStmt>
     <seriesStmt>
      <p/>
     </seriesStmt>
     <notesStmt>
      <note>
       <p/>
      </note>
     </notesStmt>
    </biblFull>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
   </projectDesc>
   <editorialDecl>
    <p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been retained.</p>
    <p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme to aid in
     establishing analytical groupings.</p>
   </editorialDecl>
   <refsDecl>
    <p/>
   </refsDecl>

  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <creation>
    <date value="1862-01-01">1862-01-01</date>
   </creation>
   <langUsage>
    <language id="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <handList>
    <hand id="h1"/>
    <hand id="author"/>
    <hand id="unknown"/>
    <hand id="cataloger"/>
   </handList>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>nonfiction</term>
     <term>prose</term>
     <term>masculine</term>
     <term>American Civil War/Special Collections</term>
    </keywords>
    <keywords>
     <term type="Field650">LCSH</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change>
    <date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>Corrector</resp>
     <name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2009-11-11">November 11th, 2009</date>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
     <name>Digital Curation Services Staff</name>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Converted markup (originally TEI Lite) to comply with the UVa Library TEI DTD
     (uva-dl-tei).</item>
   </change>
   <change>
    <date value="2010-09-30">October 14th, 2010</date>
    <respStmt>
     <name id="jkl8b">Julie Lim, University of Virginia Library</name>
     <resp>corrector</resp>
    </respStmt>
    <item>Minor corrections to spacing.</item>
   </change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text id="d1">
  <front id="d2">
   <div1 type="summary" n="1" id="d3">
    <head>
     <bibl>
      <abbr>ALS</abbr>
      <extent>8 pp.</extent>
      <date value="1862-01-01"> January 01, 1862</date>

      <title>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case</title>
     </bibl>
    </head>
    <p> The first day of a New Year and Charles bids Adelaide a Happy New Year. Charles asks for two
     wishes for the New Year, a letter form Adelaide and Hal's recovery from his illness and laments
     the lack of letters from Adelaide. He then describes a night on picket and closes by wishing
     all a good New Year. A second letter on the same day sees Charles in higher spirits, his two
     wishes for the day being fulfilled, a letter from Adelaide and Hal's recovery. Charles is moved
     to describe that he has given up the domestic evils of drink, tobacco and cards and thanks
     Adelaide for her kindness in writing to him. </p>
   </div1>

  </front>
  <body id="d4">

   <div1 type="letter" n="1" id="d5">
    <head>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, <date value="1862-01-01">1862 January
      01</date></head>
    <pb entity="DSSR_000000766_0469"/>


    <opener>
     <dateline>
      <name type="place">Romney Va.</name>
      <date value="1862-01-01">Jany 1<hi rend="super">st</hi> 1862</date>
     </dateline>

     <salute>A happy New year to you, dear<lb/>
      <name type="recipient">Addie</name>, and my kindest wishes in<lb/> your interest.</salute>
    </opener>

    <p> How do you do, this<lb/> beautiful day? Did you ever see such<lb/> a beautiful new years day
     in your life?<lb/> The day here is as pleasant as the most<lb/> delightful day I ever saw in
     May.<lb/> The main things <add place="inline" hand="h1">wanted</add> thought, to make me<lb/>
     perfectly happy to-day, are, first a letter<lb/> from my <name type="recipient">Addie</name>.
      second <name type="person">Hal's</name> recovery<lb/> from his present indisposition. He
     has<lb/> not been well for the past few days<lb/> and last night he was some worse,<lb/> but
     is, I trust, better this morning<lb/> I hope he will soon be able to resume<lb/> his duties. He
     is not so bad however, as<lb/> to call in the Doctor yet, and I hope will not.<lb/></p>

    <pb n="2" entity="DSSR_000000766_0470"/>

    <p>I have <del hand="h1">not</del> recieved but one letter since<lb/> we left <name type="place"
      >Charleston</name>, and that one was sent<lb/> to <name type="place">Charleston</name> first.
     In it you spoke of not<lb/> recieving a letter from me since Capt Asper<lb/> returned. Have you
     not recieved any of<lb/> the letters I have written? I sent one from<lb/>
     <name type="place">Charleston</name>, one from <name type="place">Parkersburg</name>, one from<lb/>
     <name type="place">Green Spring Run</name>, and two from <name type="place">Romney</name><lb/>
     together with a picture of "your's truly"<lb/> I have been waiting for <name type="person"
     >Wood</name> to return<lb/> hoping he would bring me some tidings<lb/> from you, but he does
     not come, and<lb/> as I went in and saw <name type="person">Hal</name>, he asked<lb/> me to
     write home and let you know<lb/> he was unwell, so I add one more to<lb/> the list of
     unanswered letters.<lb/></p>
    <p> I was on picket the other day and had<lb/> a first rate time. I send you a hasty sketch<lb/>
     of the headquarter of the outpost where I<lb/> was stationed. The smaller part of<lb/>
     <pb n="3" entity="DSSR_000000766_0471"/> the house took fire, in the night, and great<lb/>
     excitement ensued in consequence. Many who<lb/> were asleep supposed the rebels had
     attacked<lb/> us, and were very much alarmed.<lb/> There is a peculiar sort of excitement<lb/>
     in standing on picket guard that I love<lb/> One takes his post in the evening, banishes<lb/>
     all though of comfort <unclear/> rest, and gives<lb/> way to his own thoughts, all the time
     on<lb/> the <unclear>
      <q>"qui vive"</q>
     </unclear>, expecting to hear the click<lb/> of a gun lock, the step of an enemy, or,<lb/>
     perchance, the discharge of a gun itself,<lb/> summoning him to another world. The<lb/>
     rustling of the breeze through the dry leaves,<lb/> (for there is no snow) or the cry of some
     night<lb/> bird calling for its mate makes him<lb/> involuntarily get his gun in readiness<lb/>
     to meet the expected foe. Some times<lb/> it happens that inefficient men are placed<lb/> on a
     dangerous post, as on the last night<lb/>
     <pb n="4" entity="DSSR_000000766_0472"/> I stood. A man was placed on a post<lb/> near mine,
     and towards daylight he fancied<lb/> he saw a man, preparing to make a<lb/> hostile movement:
     frightened nearly to death<lb/> he drew up his musket and fired. An<lb/> alarm was thus raised
     needlessly. In<lb/> the morning, we visited the spot where<lb/> the supposed <unclear/> had
     stood, when lo, a bush<lb/> appeared, having seen it move he shot it.<lb/></p>
    <p> I made a sketch of some points of<lb/> interest, intending to send them to you<lb/> but
     while on picket the other day, they<lb/> were stolen. <name type="person">Mr. Davis</name>
     arrived safe did<lb/> he not? Did you get the picture?<lb/></p>
    <p> But I must bring this uninteresting<lb/> letter to a <q>"finis"</q>. Do write soon dear<lb/>
     <name type="recipient">Addie</name>, for I am so lonesome<lb/> Give my kind wishes to all,
      bid <name type="person">Laurie</name><lb/> and <name type="person">Dora</name> (when you see
     her) a happy new year for me,<lb/> and please accept my love yourself<lb/></p>

    <closer> Yours as ever<signed>Charlie</signed>
     <seg type="postscript">I am perfectly well. &amp; trust you are too. Excuse poor writing.
      for I have a poor pen </seg>
    </closer>
   </div1>

   <div1 type="letter" n="2" id="d6">

    <pb n="5" entity="DSSR_000000766_0473"/>
    <head>Letter from Charles N. Tenney to Adelaide E. Case, 1862 January 01</head>

    <opener>
     <name type="place">Romney Va</name>.; Happy New years.,<lb/>
     <salute>My dear friend;-</salute>
    </opener>

    <p> Although I have once<lb/> written to day, duty and <hi rend="underline">my own</hi><lb/>
     inclination lead me to pen a<lb/> few more scattered thoughts to<lb/> my dearest, kindest,
      friend <name type="recipient">Addie</name><lb/> Now, to speak truly, I feel<lb/> more like
     myself to-night than<lb/> this morning, for two reasons,<lb/> which reasons, are the
     fulfillment<lb/> of my two wishes expressed in<lb/> my note of this
     morning <unclear>orig</unclear>.--<lb/> the reception of a letter from you<lb/> and about <name
      type="person">Hal's</name> getting better.<lb/> He is some better tonight, though<lb/> not
     well. The wind has been<lb/> blowing very hard,all day,<lb/>
     <pb n="6" entity="DSSR_000000766_0475"/> Page 2.<lb/> and the tent kept flapping
     a <unclear/><lb/> making a very disagreable <orig reg="noise">noi</orig><lb/> to <name
      type="person">Hal</name>, consequently, a severe <orig reg="head">hea</orig><lb/> ache ensued,
     but the gale has<lb/> in a measure subsided, and I<lb/> trust a good night's rest will<lb/>
     restore him to his wanted good<lb/> health. But to turn to <orig reg="other">oth</orig><lb/>
     subjects. Have you passed a<lb/> happy new-year's day? and did<lb/> you thoughts revert
      once <del hand="h1">of</del> to<lb/>
     <q>"Soldier boy"</q> <name type="sender">Charlie</name>? and wonder<lb/> if he was engaged in
     some<lb/> Bechanalian excesses? Thanks,<lb/>
     <name type="recipient">Addie</name>, for the question which sis-<lb/> ter <name type="person"
      >Laurie</name> prompted you to ask<lb/> me. You may inform her that<lb/>
     <name type="sender">Charlie</name> never was intoxicated in<lb/> his life, and furthermore,
     while<lb/> at <name type="place">Summersville</name>, I<lb/> pledged myself to <q>"touch not</q>,<lb/>
     <pb n="7" entity="DSSR_000000766_0474"/> 3<hi rend="super">rd</hi> Page <q>taste not, handle
      not the wine,"</q> or,<lb/> in other words became a teetotaller.<lb/> In making these
     assertions, I think<lb/> I can be borne out in them by Co. H.<lb/> and its officers. While on
     the subject[s]<lb/> of domestic evils, let me remark that<lb/> over two months ago, I eschewed
     the<lb/> use of tobacco in any form, and while<lb/> at <name type="place">Green Spring
     Run</name>, I forswore the<lb/> practice of playing cards. This I did<lb/> for my own benefit
     and character<lb/> hereafter. Is <name type="recipient">Addie</name> satisfied with this<lb/>
     statement? It is I believe the truth.<lb/> Oh! the temptations of a soldier's life!<lb/> How
     great the want of some restraining<lb/> influence at home! <q>"Home,"</q> Tears invol=<lb/>
     untarily spring to my eyes as I utter<lb/> that endearing word, and think.<q>" <hi
       rend="underline">I<lb/> have no home</hi>."</q> But fate has decreed<lb/> that <hi
      rend="underline">one</hi> remains, not too proud to<lb/> own an <hi rend="underline">outcast
      soldier</hi> as a <hi rend="underline">brother</hi><lb/>
     <pb n="8" entity="DSSR_000000766_0476"/> That you should find anything<lb/> worthy a sister's
     love in my poor<lb/> self, is a matter of wonder to me.<lb/> How can I ever repay you for
     your<lb/> kindness in noticing one so far<lb/> below your happy position?<lb/> But, do I wound
     you? Forgive me<lb/>
     <hi rend="underline">dear, kind</hi> sister, and I will endeav <unclear/><lb/> or to dispel the
     unpleasant state<lb/> of mind, which has come over me<lb/> in a few moments of <hi
      rend="underline">bitter</hi> thought<lb/> Would you know how the day<lb/> has been passed by
     me? Well<lb/> in the morning, after performing<lb/> the usual routine, I called on <name
      type="person">Hal</name><lb/> and was pained to learn that he<lb/> had passed an ill night,
     after<lb/> fulfilling his request to write home,<lb/> I read <q>"Guy Mannering"</q> until<lb/>
     Battalion drill, after which I returned<lb/> to attend to the wants of my<lb/> brother <name
      type="person">Hall</name> where I now am and will remain<lb/> tonight <name type="person"><abbr
       expan="George">Geo.</abbr> Moore</name> is with me and requests<lb/> me to give his respects
      to <q>"the family,"</q> I suppose he<lb/>
     <sic corr="has">has</sic> some one <orig reg="in p">articular</orig>. By the bye <name
      type="person">George</name> is a<lb/> good boy and is a true man.</p>

   </div1>

  </body>

 </text>
</TEI.2>
