<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="oplkeno"?>
<?dlps page-images="color" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="other"?>


<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY oplkeno_back SYSTEM "uva-lib:504329" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY oplkeno_contents SYSTEM "uva-lib:504330" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY oplkeno_cover SYSTEM "uva-lib:504331" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY oplkeno_foredge SYSTEM "uva-lib:504332" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY oplkeno_head SYSTEM "uva-lib:504333" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY oplkeno_spine SYSTEM "uva-lib:504334" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY oplkeno_tail SYSTEM "uva-lib:504335" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY oplkeno_title SYSTEM "uva-lib:504336" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>
<TEI.2 id="oplkeno">
<teiHeader type="migrated" creator="Etext">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Chiricahua Apache`s Account of the Geronimo Campaign of 1886</title>
<title type="sort">chiricahua apache s account of the geronimo campaign of 1886</title>
<author>Opler, Morris; Kenoi, Sam</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>Creation of machine-readable version:</resp>
<name>M. Eleanor Culley</name>
<resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
<name>University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">65</num> kilobytes</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia</pubPlace>
<idno type="ETC">OplKeno</idno>
<date value="2001">2001</date>
<availability status="public">
<p n="copyright">Copyright &copy; 2001 by the Rector and Visitors of the University of Virginia</p>
<p n="access">Publicly accessible</p>
</availability>
<idno type="uva-pid">uva-lib:477230</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<seriesStmt>
<title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
<idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
</seriesStmt>
<notesStmt>
<note>
<p>Illustrations have been included from the original source.</p>
</note>
<note>
<p>Republished with permission of New Mexico Historical Review, &copy;1938, all rights reserved. This text may be used and shared in
accordance with the fair use provisions of US and international copyright law and agreement, provided that it is accompanied by full
citation:   "A Chiricahua Apache`s Account fo the Geronimo Campaign of 1886", by Morris E. Opler, Vol. 13:4 (October 1938), 360-386.</p>
</note>
</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblFull>
<titleStmt>
<title type="main">A Chiricahua Apache`s Account of the Geronimo Campaign of 1886</title>
<title level="j">New Mexico Historical Review, Vol XIII, No. 4, October, 1938.</title>
<title type="sort">chiricahua apache s account of the geronimo campaign of 1886</title>
<author>Morris Opler,&nbsp;&nbsp; Sam Kenoi</author>
<editor>Lansing B. Bloom</editor>
</titleStmt>
<extent>pp. 360-86; or 26 pages</extent>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Historical Society of New Mexico and University of New Mexico</publisher>
<pubPlace>University of New Mexico, Albuquerque</pubPlace>
<date value="1938">1938</date>
<idno type="callNo">Source copy consulted:    Alderman Library, University of Virginia, F 791.N76 Vol 13-14, 1938-9.</idno>
</publicationStmt>
</biblFull>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<projectDesc>
<p>Prepared for the University of Virginia Library Electronic Text Center.</p>
</projectDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<p>All unambiguous end-of-line hyphens have been removed, and the  trailing part of a word has been joined to the preceding line.</p>
<p id="ETC">Some keywords in the header are a local Electronic Text Center scheme  to aid in establishing analytical groupings.</p>
</editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<creation>
<date value="1938">1938</date>
</creation>
<langUsage>
<language id="eng" usage="main">English</language>
<language id="apa">Apache</language>
<language id="spa">Spanish</language>
</langUsage>
<textClass>
<keywords>
<term>nonfiction</term>
<term>prose</term>
<term>masculine</term>
<term>Native American</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date value="2001-08">August 2001</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>corrector</resp>
<name>M. Eleanor Culley, Electronic Text Center</name>
</respStmt>
<item>added TEI header and tags, added Sam Kenoi as a co-author</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2005-07">July 2005</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Corrector</resp>
<name>John Ivor Carlson</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted to XML and/or checked tags.</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2007-09">September 2007</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Ethan Gruber, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Converted XML markup from TEI Lite to uva-dl-tei (TEI P4 with local customizations).</item>
</change>
<change>
<date value="2008-01">January 2008</date>
<respStmt>
<resp>Migration</resp>
<name>Greg Murray, University of Virginia Library</name>
</respStmt>
<item>Programmatically updated TEI header markup (but not header content) for minimal compliance with current QA requirements.</item>
</change>
    
    <change>
        <date value="2008-09">September 2008</date>
        <respStmt>
            <resp>Migration</resp>
            <name>Scholarly Resources, University of Virginia Library</name>
        </respStmt>
        <item>Added and/or replaced the digital images accompanying the electronic text.
            To achieve consistency between text and images, all images were digitized from
            the source copy from which the text was originally digitized (Call Number: F791 .N76).</item>
    </change>
    
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<front id="d2">
    <pb entity="oplkeno_spine" pid="uva-lib:504334" n="Spine"/>
    <pb entity="oplkeno_cover" pid="uva-lib:504331" n="Cover"/>
    <pb entity="oplkeno_back" pid="uva-lib:504329" n="Back"/>
    <pb entity="oplkeno_head" pid="uva-lib:504333" n="Head"/>
    <pb entity="oplkeno_tail" pid="uva-lib:504335" n="Tail"/>
    <pb entity="oplkeno_foredge" pid="uva-lib:504332" n="Foredge"/>
    <pb entity="oplkeno_title" pid="uva-lib:504336" n="Title"/>
    <pb entity="oplkeno_contents" pid="uva-lib:504330" n="Contents"/>
</front>

<body id="d3">
<div1 type="article" id="d4">
<head><bibl><title>A CHIRICAHUA APACHE'S ACCOUNT OF THE GERONIMO CAMPAIGN OF
1886</title><author>MORRIS OPLER</author><author>SAMUEL E.
KENOI</author></bibl></head>


<div2 type="introduction" id="d5">
<head><bibl><title>INTRODUCTION</title><author>MORRIS OPLER</author></bibl></head>
<p>
During the years 1931-33, while I was engaged in ethnological research among the
Chiricahua Apache Indians now living on the Mescalero Indian Reservation of New
Mexico,<ref target="a1" n="1">l</ref> one of my most helpful informants was a fifty-seven or fifty-eight-year-old man, Samuel E. Kenoi. In 1932 a long
autobiographical account was recorded from Mr. Kenoi. The pages that follow
comprise the section of that life story which has to do with the 1885-86
campaign against the Chiricahua leader, Geronimo. Many of the American military
leaders who participated in that campaign have offered, in reports, articles,
and books, their versions of the event. It is certainly in order that the less
articulate Chiricahua be consulted before we may say that all relevant
historical material concerning the episode is before us.
</p>
<p>
The Chiricahua Apache tribe may be divided into three bands, the Eastern,
Central, and Southern Chiricahua. Before the reservation period, the Eastern
band, better known as the Warm Springs Apache, ranged mostly in southwestern New
Mexico.<ref target="a2" n="2">2</ref> Mangus Colorado, Victorio, Nana, and Loco are
come of the better known leaders of this band. The Central Chiricahua, led at
various times by Cochise, Chihuahua, and Naiche, controlled the southeastern
part of Arizona.<ref target="a3" n="3">3</ref> The Southern Chiricahua, with whom
the names Geronimo, Bonito, and Juh (Who, Whoa, or Ho) are to be identified,
lived primarily in the state of Chihuahua, Mexico, but frequently entered
southern Arizona as well.<ref target="a4" n="4">4</ref>
</p>

<note place="foot" id="a1" n="1"><seg type="note-symbol">1.</seg><p> This research was made possible by the Laboratory of
Anthropology of Santa F&eacute;, the Southwest Society, the University of
Chicago, the Social Science Research Council, the National Research Council, and
Columbia University.
</p></note>
<note place="foot" id="a2" n="2"><seg type="note-symbol">2.</seg><p> The Chiricahua name for the Eastern Chiricahua is <foreign
lang="apa">Tcihende</foreign>, "Red Paint People."
</p></note>
<note place="foot" id="a3" n="3"><seg type="note-symbol">3.</seg><p> In their own language the Central Chiricahua are known as
Tcokanene. The word does not yield to linguistic analysis.
</p></note>
<note place="foot" id="a4" n="4"><seg type="note-symbol">4.</seg><p> The native name for the Southern Chiricahua is Ne'na'i, "Enemy
People."
</p></note>

<pb n="361"/>

<p>
In order to settle and pacify the two bands living wholly within the boundaries
of the United States, reservations were established. In 1872 a reservation was
set aside in the Dragoon Mountains of Arizona for the Central Chiricahua under
Cochise. Previously the Ojo Caliente Reserve in western New Mexico had been
established for the Eastern Chiricahua or Warm Springs Apache. Under this
policy, which allowed the bands to remain by themselves within their former
territories, conditions improved markedly. Serious trouble broke out when these
reservations were abolished after 1875 and an attempt was made to concentrate
all Chiricahua on the White Mountain Reservation (now the San Carlos and White
Mountain reservations) of the Western Apache. The Chiricahua bitterly resisted
removal and failed to make a satisfactory adjustment to the Western Apache, from
whom they considered themselves separated by a sharp difference in dialect and
customs. At the time of the removal of the Chiricahua to the Western Apache
Reservation, as many Southern Chiricahua as could be found were taken, too, but
quite as many were not apprehended. As the following narrative attests, the
distrust of the Western Apache, the nostalgia for their former homes, and the
resistance against the close supervision of the white military, led to frequent
escapes of small Chiricahua parties and marauding expeditions. Many of these
raiding parties became involved with the unsubdued So&uacute;thern Chiricahua in
depredations or fled to Southern Chiricahua territory for refuge, and it was not
long before the Southern Chiricahua who were still at large were the target of
the military and an attempt was made to place them at San Carlos as well. Since
the Southern Chiricahua operated on both sides of the border, it was necessary
for General Crook, in his campaign of 1883, to cross over into Mexico to conquer
these Apache and to bring a large number of them to San Carlos.
</p>

<pb n="362"/>

<p>
The increasing number of outsiders was hardly welcomed by the Western Apache.
Suspicion and unrest continued, friction increased, a conflict over authority
between civil and military officers added to the uncertainty and confusion, and
in 1885 Geronimo, Chihuahua, Mangus, and Naiche had again left the reservation
with their followers and resumed raids throughout New Mexico and Arizona.
General Crook followed and carried on the war until he was relieved of command
in favor of General Nelson A. Miles. The surrender of Geronimo, September 5,
1886, ended the contest.
</p>
<p>
The father of the narrator was a Southern Chiricahua, but he was in no way
involved in the Geronimo outbreak. Many other Chiricahua not only refused to
heed the advice of the headstrong leaders, but rendered signal service to the
United States troops throughout the expedition. Mr. Kenoi gives special credit
to two Chiricahua, Charles Martine and Kaitah, for locating the hiding place of
Geronimo in the Sierra Madre and for inducing him to surrender. That estimate of
the contributions of these two men to the final victory has been concurred in by
Captain John G. Bourke (<hi rend="italic">0n the Border With Crook</hi>) and
Britton Davis (<hi rend="italic">The Truth About Geronimo</hi>). The subsequent
imprisonment and removal from the west of the entire tribe, including the
peaceful and co&ouml;perative elements, is still a source of bitterness and
reproach, as Mr. Kenoi's account indicates.
</p>

</div2>


<div2 type="section" id="d6">
<head><bibl><title>
A CHIRICAHUA APACHE'S ACCOUNT OF THE GERONIMO CAMPAIGN OF 1886</title>
<author>Samuel E. Kenoi</author>
<editor>Morris Opler</editor></bibl></head>

<p>
I was born in 1875. I remember the last time Geronimo went on the war-path. That
was in 1885, but I had heard about his taking the war-path before this.
</p>
<p>
My father was a Southern Chiricahua. He ran all over the country, here, there,
and everywhere. Ho<ref target="b1" n="5">1</ref> was the leader of my father's
group, which was a small group. But my father did not stay with them very long.
He went to San Carlos, to Fort Apache, to Mescalero. My father was never with
Geronimo on the war-path.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b1" n="5"><seg type="note-symbol">1.</seg><p> Ho, also written Juh, Who, and Whoa in reports and historical
accounts, was a Southern Chiricahua leader. His son, Asa Datlogi, is still
living at Mescalero.
</p></note>

<pb n="363"/>

<p>
But one time my father and another man by the name of Adis, Tom Duffy's father,
were chosen as scouts at Fort Apache. This was before Geronimo escaped for the
last time. There was a big hostile band out before Geronimo went. Ho was chief
of that band. It was a Southern Chiricahua group. The United States Army
officers selected my father and Adis to go out after them. Small round tickets
with numbers were issued to my father and Adis by the army officer. Only the
oldest scouts were issued tickets in th&iacute;s way. You had to be a scout in order to
get one, and you had to be recognized in Washington too. These tickets were
issued to the Indians by the officers just the same as they were issued to their
own white scouts. After these two men were selected, they were issued an army
rifle, Springfield 45-70, with belt and cartridges and plenty of ammunition. The
two men were told to go and get Ho's band, make peace with them, and bring them
in. This happened about 1873.<ref target="b2" n="6">2</ref> Because my father and
this other man were Southern Chiricahua and Ho's band was Southern Chiricahua,
they were told to go and get them. My father and Adis went out, because my
father had many relatives by marriage in Ho's band.<ref target="b3" n="7">3</ref>
They went over and got those Indians and brought them back to Fort Apache.
</p>
<p>
From the way they talked in the old days, it seems that the Indians didn't say
much about the white people except what good they were doing, giving them plenty
of blankets and rations. They seemed to be on good terms with them in those
days. Even during the wars the peaceable Indians at the agency talked like that.
They said the white man came from across the ocean.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b2" n="6"><seg type="note-symbol">2.</seg><p> This date is probably set too early, since few Chiricahua were
settled in Western Apache country prior to 1876.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b3" n="7"><seg type="note-symbol">3.</seg><p> In their own languge the Central Chiricahua are known as <foreign lang="apa">Tcokanene</foreign></p></note>

<pb n="364"/>

<p>
What they didn't like was so much ruling; that's what they didn't like. They
didn't have all the Indians at the agency in those days. It was the people who
lived around the agency, who saw white people all the time, who were controlled.
The people out away from the agency were wild. That's why some thought the white
men had queer ways and hated them. After they got to know the white man's way,
they liked it. The white men gave them new things, new food, for instance. But
it was the new-comers like Ho and Geronimo who didn't like the white man. If
there was any ruling to do, they wanted to do it.
</p>

<p>
The Indians and the Mexicans were enemies. The Indians thought the Mexicans were
no good. It seems that even the different Apache groups, like the Southern
Chiricahua and the Central Chiricahua, were not so close. It was the country.
They loved the country, the place where their parents were born. They claimed
that country.
</p>

<p>
Looking back over the way those Indians lived, it seems to me that the
Department of the Interior or the War Department was just trying to outlaw the
Indians, just to have something to do. They put the Indians on a reservation,
trying to civilize them; and in place of civilizing them, they herded them in on
that reservation, naked, starving, sad, too far from any white people. The
nearest school the government had in those days was in Carlisle, Pennsylvania.
There was no Indian school in Fort Apache or anywhere near in those days. The
only white men they sent out were some very rough army officers, as rough as
they could find in the United States Army, to put in charge of these poor
ignorant Indians.
</p>

<p>
I remember seeing General Crook directing the Western Division of the United
States Army. He had been to this reservation. It is very cold in Fort Apache in
winter. Still they were living in brush huts with whatever they could get hold
of, a piece of cowhide or sheep hide, to prevent the water from going through
their huts.
</p>

<pb n="365"/>

<p>
General Nelson A. Miles was second in charge of these Indians. He relieved
General Crook. He also saw the conditions. Instead of making conditions a little
better, his soldiers were always scaring small groups here and there. Then these
frightened Indians would go on the war-path.
</p>

<p>
This is the way it would happen. Suppose Ho was on the war-path, and suppose
Naiche<ref target="b4" n="8">4</ref> was on the war-path, and suppose Geronimo was
on the war-path. Well, they might send two Apache to Ho to get him to come back
to the reservation in a peaceable way. The government might send two men after
Naiche. The government might send two men after Geronimo. They might all come
back at the same time to the agency. When they got back on the reservation,
these three groups would be full of fear. They might think they were going to be
hung or have their heads cut off. So they were sure to listen and try to find
out what was said about them. They would go around to this camp and the next
camp to learn. They were full of fear.
</p>
<p>
The soldiers would point to them, asking, "Which is Naiche? Which one is Ho?
Which is Geronimo?"
</p>

<p>
In order to get some fun out of them, a soldier might run his hand along his
throat as if to slit it, when the officer wasn't looking.<ref target="b5" n="9">5</ref>  
    Then the Indians would be more afraid than ever; something
would be done about it. Those three, Ho, Geronimo, and Naiche, would hold a
secret council when everybody was asleep that night. They would say to each
other, "That white soldier met us and made a motion as if he were cutting his
throat. It's bound to mean something. He might be a good man trying to let us
know just what they are going to do to us.."
</p>

<p>
They wo&uacute;ld take it that way. They would think that white soldier was a kind
fellow, that he was telling them that they were going to have their heads cut
off. That soldier did it for fun and never knew why those Indians left the
reservation again. But those Indians were wild. They didn't know any better.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b4" n="8"><seg type="note-symbol">4.</seg><p> Naiche was the son of Cochise, the great chief of the Central
Chiricahua. Naiche's sons, Christian Naiche and Barnabas Naiche, are now living
at Mescalero.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b5" n="9"><seg type="note-symbol">5.</seg><p> All old Chiricahua agree concerning what they now recognize as
obvious attempts of the white soldiers to terrorize them.</p></note>

<pb n="366"/>

<p>
The Indians who had been on the war-path would listen to find out anything that
was said about them. A soldier, a private, might say, "Those Indians ought to go
to jail," or, "Those Indians ought to be killed for that." Maybe some uneducated
Indian who knew just a little English would hear this. He would spread the news
that the Indians were going to jail or were going to be killed. And off they
would go again.
</p>
<p>
The Indians on the reservation stayed around the agency buildings when the
bandits were out, because the bandits would capture anyone who could carry a gun
and make him go with them. And they took women too. If you wanted a horse from
pasture, you would have to send a little boy for it to be safe.
</p>
<p>
Rock piles and mountains bounded the reservation. I was a little fellow. I
didn't know the boundaries. But my father and mother knew them, and all the
older people knew. My father was already on the reservation when I was born. My
father was first brought to the agency by General George Crook. It was before my
time. They told him, "Here is your agency, Fort Apache. You can go from here to
San Carlos. You can camp anywhere between."
</p>
<p>
I think it was in 1871 that many groups of Indians were put on that reservation.
They had to comply with the regulations and orders. Anyone violating the laws
against killing and stealing was punished. Most of the Indians complied with the
regulations. Just a few didn't.
</p>
<pb n="367"/>

<p>
There was Geronimo, for instance. He was called a human tiger.<ref target="b6" n="10">6</ref> 
    He would rather be on the war-path than anything else. He
would advise his parents' group, and his wife's relatives, and any other
relatives, to leave and he would take them out with him.<ref target="b7" n="11">7</ref> 
    And since I have thought about Geronimo I feel this way: He
was always suspicious of living on the reservation as other Indians did. He was
always afraid. Then there was his foolish ceremony.<ref target="b8" n="12">8</ref> He
thought the white people were going to kill him or send him to jail somewhere.
Then he would hold his ceremony and see some vision and it would say, "Go out on
the war-path."
</p>
<p>
Ho was Asa's<ref target="b9" n="13">9</ref> father. The name doesn't mean anything.
He was called that because he stuttered. He was a war shaman, and during the
trouble with the white men he had a great deal of influence. He always managed
to keep a few men stirred up and out raiding and fighting. Then the whole tribe
would be blamed for it, and it was because of men like him that we were held
prisoners of war and were treated as we were.
</p>
<p>
Geronimo was nothing but the same kind of man, an old trouble maker. He was a
shaman. He was as cowardly as a coyote. You can ask men like Perico what he was
like.<ref target="b10" n="14">10</ref> Perico is a brave man and was one of the best
Apache fighters. He is well known for this, as was his brother, Eyelash, who was
also called Fun. Fun was a great fighter. He killed himself in Alabama.<ref target="b11" n="15">11</ref> Perico will tell you how he and others did all the
fighting while Geronimo stayed behind like a woman.
</p>


<note place="foot" id="b6" n="10"><seg type="note-symbol">6.</seg><p> The informant has leen a very popular commercial picture of
Geronimo with this phraee on it and has picked it up.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b7" n="11"><seg type="note-symbol">7.</seg><p> Geronimo was not a chief in the accepted Chiricahua sense of
the term. As this passase indicates, his influence was exerted primarily on
relatives and close friends. This is one reason why those over whom he had no
control resent the fact that the government exacted the penalty from them as
well.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b8" n="12"><seg type="note-symbol">8.</seg><p> Among his own people Geronimo's chief claim to prominence prior
to his defiance of the white forces, was his ceremonial power. One of his
ceremonies was designed to determine the whereabouts and intentions of the
enemy. During the period under discussion he used this to predict the actions of
the white man. Since he had definite fears in respect to this subject and since
his ceremony was the servant of his fears, the directions of his "power" were
likely to involve him in flight and further difficulties.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b9" n="13"><seg type="note-symbol">9.</seg><p> Between Ho's son, Asa, and the narrator, there exists sharp
political rivalry and some personal animosity. Ho has been consistently
described as aggressive and cruel, however.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b10" n="14"><seg type="note-symbol">10.</seg><p> Perico has died since this story was recorded.
</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b11" n="15"><seg type="note-symbol">11.</seg><p> Fun is said to have injured his wife in a fit of jealousy.
Thinking he had killed the woman (she later recovered) he took his own life.
</p></note>


<pb n="368"/>


<p>
Once Geronimo's men were caught in a cave by the Mexican soldiers in Old Mexico.
The women and children of the party were in there too. The Mexicans set fire to
the grass all around and tried to smoke and burn them out, and they kept up a
steady fire into the entrance of that cave. The Apache were falling right and
left. Instead of standing up and fighting, Geronimo got behind the women and
children. Women and children were dying right on top of him, with their blood
running down over him, and he was under them, burrowing in the sand. One of his
soldiers caught him by the feet and pulled him up and said to him, "Where are
you going? You were man enough at the start. Why don't you stand up now and
fight like a man?"<ref target="b12" n="16">12</ref>
</p>

<p>
I know plenty of stories like this about Geronimo. Now some of the young people
try to make him out a hero. They say he was a fine man and stood up and fought
for his country, and things like that.
</p>

<p>
I was talking about him once at Fort Sill,<ref target="b13" n="17">13</ref> and one
Indian said to me, "What do you know about Geronimo?"
</p>

<p>
I said to him, "I know plenty about him. I know that he and a few others like
him were the cause of the death of my mother and many of my relatives who have
been pushed around the country as prisoners of war. I know we would not be in
our present trouble if it was not for men like him, and you honor him for that!"
</p>
<p>
I remember how it was at Fort Apache. Most of the Indians were peaceful. They
were attending to business. They were raising crops. They had their sheep and
cattle and were getting along very well. Then somebody would say, "Geronimo is
out again," and there he would be with a small band of about forty men up in the
mountains. Pretty soon he would raid a settlement here, or kill a person, and
the whole tribe would be blamed for it. Instead of coming and getting his
rations and settling down and trying to be civilized, he would be out there like
a wild animal, killing and raiding. Then they would organize the Chiricahua
scouts and send them out after Geronimo's men. In this way he caused Apache to
fight Apache and all sorts of trouble to break out among our people.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b12" n="16"><seg type="note-symbol">12.</seg><p> I happened upon this story a number of times during my
stay.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b13" n="17"><seg type="note-symbol">13.</seg><p> Fort Sill, Oklahoma, where the Chiricahua were quartered as
prisoners of war from 1894 to 1913.</p></note>

<pb n="369"/>

<p>
Naiche was one of the sub-chiefs under Geronimo. Naiche was a good man in some
ways, but you couldn't civilize him. He liked his Indian dancing, and he liked
his fighting, and he liked his drinking. You could make a good soldier out of
him, and that was all. He was always influenced by Geronimo. Mangus was another
trouble maker. He always had three or four men on the war-path, and the whole
tribe would be blamed. His daughter is still living here. She is George
Martine's wife. This is not Mangus Colorado, but another Mangus. Mangus Colorado
lived before this and was a good man. Roger Tulane is his grandson.
</p>

<p>
I asked Perico who were the best chiefs he knew. He said Mangus Colorado was by
far the best of them. Perico is an old man, even older than Chatto. He says that
when he was a boy he saw Mangus Colorado sign a peace treaty for the Indians.
This treaty was signed July 1, 1852, according to a government paper that I
have. Perico says that he was twelve or fourteen years old then. He says that
Tcic was second best.<ref target="b14" n="18">14</ref> Tcic was Christian Naiche's
father's father. He says that Bonito, a Southern Chiricahua, was the next best
man. Loco, Johnny Loco's father, was afraid, he said, and just hung around Warm
Springs.<ref target="b15" n="19">15</ref> Victorio was another trouble maker.
</p>


<note place="foot" id="b14" n="18"><seg type="note-symbol">14.</seg><p> Tcic, "Nose," known to the whites as Cochise.</p></note>
<note place="foot" id="b15" n="19"><seg type="note-symbol">15.</seg><p> Johnny Loco is still living near Apache, Oklahoma. In 1913
when the Chiricahua were freed from military supervision, some chose to remain
in Oklahoma and receive allotments; most decided to take up residence at
Mescalero, New Mexico. Johnny Loco accepted allotment in Oklahoma.
</p></note>
<pb n="370"/>

<p>
At Fort Apache they said Geronimo was always suspicious. There were two women
and three men who were secret service agents for Lieutenant Davis. They were
Western Apache. These are a different tribe. That is what caused many of the
stories that were going around. The two women who were secret service agents
would go after midnight to these army official and tell them what had been said,
what the Indians intended to do. Most of the trouble came through the Western
Apache. They told stories, mostly false. We don't know who the secret service
people were. But I don't think the government offlcials can deny that they had
secret agents, men and women.
</p>

<p>
Really the reservation belonged to the Western Apache. It was their land just as
other places belonged to other groups. There were the Warm Springs Apache. There
were the Central Chiricahua; they had a little strip of country away from the
reservation. The Southern Chiricahua had another little place of their own. And
there were the people of Mount Mora and Baronko. There were small groups here
and there, relatives and people related by marriage, people who knew each other,
scattered out in different country. The Mohave Apache<ref target="b16" n="20">l6</ref> had their own country, and they were brought there too.
In about 1871 the United States Government started to herd the Indians on the
reservation. It reached the Warm Springs Indians and those other groups. They
spoke the same language. These groups were put on these two reservations, San
Carlos and Fort Apache.<ref target="b17" n="21">17</ref>
</p>

<p>
The Chiricahua got along all right with the Western Apache at first. Then the
Western Apache in about a year began to be uneasy, began to be jealous of the
other tribes on their reservation, though these Chiricahua were put there and
compelled to live there. When these Western Apache, who had owned that
reservation before we were put there, began to have a jealous feeling against
the other tribes, they told the agent and other army ofilcials some false
stories so they might get something to do from the government if the Chiricahua
went on the war-path.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b16" n="20"><seg type="note-symbol">16.</seg><p> The Yavapai, who are often mistakenly called Mohave Apache,
are meant. They are in no way Apache and speak a language of an entirely
different linguistic stock. Some of them are still living on the San Carlos
Indian Reservation.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b17" n="21"><seg type="note-symbol">17.</seg><p> Fort Apache was the agency center for the White Mountain
Reservation.</p></note>


<pb n="371"/>

<p>
The name we called the Western Apache Indians, <foreign
lang="apa">Biniedine</foreign><ref target="b18" n="22">18</ref>, was made long before
my father or his father. It meant, according to the old people, that they were
foolish, didn't have much sense. There are a good many stories that show how
well this name fitted them. There were not many marriages between the Western
Apache and the Chiricahua, not as many as between the Mescalero and Chiricahua
here.
</p>
<p>
The Navaho acted as scouts against the Chiricahua on the war-path, and so did a
few Pueblo Indians and some of the "People without Moccasins." These are a
people in Arizona, around Tucson somewhere. I think they are the Pima. They were
barefooted. If they got stickers in their feet they just rubbed them off on the
ground.
</p>

<p>
In 1885 Geronimo went on the war-path again. Some of those who stayed on the
reservation were sympathetic toward Geronimo because they didn't know any
better. General Nelson A. Miles, General Lawton (Captain Lawton at that time),
Captain Crawford, 1st Lieutenant Gatewood, 2nd Lieutenant Britton Davis, were
all at Fort Apache.
</p>
<p>
Uncus'<ref target="b19" n="23">19</ref> father, George Noche, was called by General
Miles one night. General Miles said, "I want you to organize the Chiricahua
Apache Scouts to run down the renegades."
</p>

<p>
And I feel that General Miles did the right thing to organize Apache scouts who
knew the country in Arizona, New Mexico, and Old Mexico. These Indian scouts
were familiar with all the water holes, with all the rough country, and all the
trails in that region. George Noche was highly respected by General Miles.
Whenever General Miles wished to do anything about the bandits, he asked George
Noche.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b18" n="22"><seg type="note-symbol">18.</seg><p> Literally "People with no Sense." All Western Apache sroupa
are called this by the Chiricahua.</p></note>
<note place="foot" id="b19" n="23"><seg type="note-symbol">19.</seg><p> Uncus, a blind Chiricahua now past middle age, was alive and
was employed as agency interpreter at Mescalero when this story was being
recorded.
</p></note>

<pb n="372"/>

<p>
After the troop was organized, they gave them two rounds of ammunition and
issued them Springfield U. S. Army rifles. The only thing they issued them in
the way of clothing was a coat, a black uniform coat. To show who was a non-commissioned man and who was not, they wore their coats. Those non-commissioned
wore their stripes according to what they were. And they made George Noche
sergeant-major. They claim George Noche knew all the country. He was not a
leading man among the Indians, however.
</p>

<p>
Another night George Noche was called again. That night General Miles told
Noche, 'I'm going to give you two days and two nights. I leave it to you to
decide which is the best way to get Geronimo and his band. I have sat here day
and night and I have tried my best with white troops to catch Geronimo, but all
my attempts seem to have failed. Now I give you two days and two nights to think
about it, and on the morning of the second day you come back and let me know.
That's why I called you over here." That's what General Miles told George Noche.
</p>

<p>
So George Noche told General Miles, "There is no need for you to give me two
days and nights to think it over. It seems to me right now I know how to get
that man. I appreciate and thank you for the high respect you show to me to do
this important work. Now I want to tell my plan to get that man. If it doesn't
work you can get someone else. It's the best I can do. If you agree to it we can
set out tomorrow.
</p>

<p>
"Here's my plan. I have two men here for you, Kaitah and Martine. I will have a
talk with them in the morning and bring them over to you. I will tell you the
reason I have chosen these men. Martine has many close relatives in that band
and so has Kaitah. Also Geronimo is Kaitah's relative-in-law. So it would be
almost impossible for those bandits to kill these men. It is impossible to send
any other men, for they will not come back alive."
</p>

<p>
General Miles was well pleased with Noche's idea. He said, "We must do that."
</p>

<p>
George Noche saw Martine and Kaitah. In the morning they went to General Miles
with George Noche. They agreed to it. He enlisted them as scouts, issued them
guns and gave
<pb n="373"/>
them each a mule. So they went out the following day, starting for Mexico. They
told General Miles that when they got Geronimo they would bring him to Fort
Bowie, Arizona.
</p>

<p>
Those men went by themselves with Lieutenant Gatewood of the 6th Cavalry. In a
day or so the 3rd Cavalry with a hundred Indian scouts set out for Mexico too,
to look for him. And in the meantime Mexican soldiers ran Geronimo into Arizona;
then these soldiers chased him into Mexico again. They were hot on his trail.
</p>

<p>
Crawford had his troops and Indian scouts close to the Mexican border. For some
reason Crawford's troops were several miles behind, but Crawford was with the
Indian scouts ahead. This was in Old Mexico. It was on a mountain. Then they met
a Mexican troop of about five hundred or more soldiers. They were after Geronimo
too. The Mexican troop was here on a flat, coming up to them. The Mexican troop
stopped, and the Indians were on a ridge over there with Captain Crawford. There
were about five hundred Mexican soldiers lined up, and Crawford only had about a
hundred Indian scouts. The commanders of these Mexican troops got together in
front. They started to march over there. And then all at once as these officers
were going along, one of these men began to shoot.
</p>

<p>
Crawford got up. He took his handkerchief out and waved it. He said, "We're
United States troops. We're friends."
</p>

<p>
But those Mexican officers didn't pay attention to Crawford. One of them shot
him. He fell down to the rocks below. The Indians had told him not to get on
that rock, but he did not think the Mexicans would shoot. He had another army
officer with him, 2nd Lieutenant Maus.
</p>

<p>
The Indians loved Captain Crawford. After they saw him knocked off that big rock
one Apache who could speak Mexican said to the Mexicans, "Don't run if you are
men. You're going to meet up with men today."
</p>

<pb n="374"/>

<p>
The Mexican officers cursed them right back. They said, "We are the troops that
cleaned out Victorio's bunch."<ref target="b20" n="24">20</ref>
</p>

<p>
The Indians told them, "Right from where you are now, you are not going to make
tracks for another place."
</p>

<p>
And they were standing behind trees, two or three of them behind every tree, and
they said, "We are the ones that killed Victorio, and we can kill every one of
you today."
</p>

<p>
Then the scouts got a couple of pack mules with ammunition. Maus didn't want
them to fight. But they said, "They killed our commander, now let's go over this
Lieutenant's head and kill them. Half go one way and half stay here along the
ridge."
</p>

<p>
And they threw the ammunition down and filled their belts and pockets. One half
said to the other, "We're going to cut loose on them from the side."
</p>
<p>
The Mexican officers felt that they had more men, so they were eager to fight.
They kept saying, "Why don't you shoot? You just sit up there and talk. You're
no women !" That's what they said.
</p>

<p>
So this Indian said, "All right, get ready. We're going to fire on you right
now."
</p>

<p>
The Indians were all strung around on the ridge. They fired on the Mexicans. The
way the old men tell it, and they laugh about it, is that the officers were
falling over each other behind those trees trying to get out of the way. The
trees were just riddled. Every one of these officers was killed. And the other
half began shooting on the soldiers. They killed about a hundred and chased
them.
</p>

<p>
I heard the story then and I still hear it told. Sundayman, Benjamin, Paul,
Cooney, Arnold, and lots of others were there. Perico was on the war-path with
Geronimo. Stephen and Evan Zozoni were there.<ref target="b21" n="25">21</ref> Some
of the scouts were out with other troops. There were many bands looking for
Geronimo.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b20" n="24"><seg type="note-symbol">20.</seg><p> Victorio was killed and his command almost annihilated in
1880 when he met a superior force of Mexican soldiers in Mexico.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b21" n="25"><seg type="note-symbol">21.</seg><p> Of all the men mentioned here, only two, Arnold Kinjoni and
Stephen Gaji, are still alive.</p></note>

<pb n="375"/>

<p>
The Indian scouts gathered together again after the Mexicans put up their white
flag. They were gathering up their dead. They carried Crawford. He was still
alive but he couldn't talk. They didn't have any doctor with them. So they took
him in a sort of crate made from long poles which a mule dragged. The Indian
scouts did the best they could, but he died before they got to Fort Bowie.
</p>

<p>
Meanwhile Kaitah, Martine, George Wratten, and Gatewood were out. All the troops
and Indian scouts were looking in different parts of the country for Geronimo.
And Kaitah and his bunch were trailing them too. A body of troops was following
Kaitah and the others, many miles behind.
</p>

<p>
They came to a mountain called Sierra Madre. They were down at the foot of the
mountain, and they saw those men at the top of the mountain. While they were
down on the flat, Kaitah hoisted up a white flag to them. Kaitah says Martine
was afraid to go up. Martine must have been behind him, always tying his
shoestring or something. Kaitah told the two white men to stay down, and he
started up with the white flag. When Kaitah got about half way up he looked
back. Martine wasn't anywhere in sight.<ref target="b22" n="26">22</ref>
</p>

<p>
Geronimo's men were pretty well armed and ready. Before Geronimo knew it was
Kaitah he ordered his men not to let any man get up to that place or down alive.
</p>

<p>
Kaitah kept on going up till he got in sight, and they knew it was Kaitah. He
stopped once in a while, for he thought they were going to shoot at him.
</p>

<p>
After they were sure it was Kaitah, his relatives said, "Come on up. No one is
going to hurt you."
</p>

<p>
Then he went up there. He sat up there and talked with all those men. Still
Martine hadn't come in sight.
</p>


<note place="foot" id="b22" n="26"><seg type="note-symbol">22.</seg><p> There has been some dispute between the Martine and Kaitah
factions concerning the bravery of Martine on this occasion. Certain it is that
Kaitah was more closely related to members of Geronimo's band and therefore
stood in least danger. Both Kaitah and Martine acted as informants for me during
my ethnological field-work. Kaitah has since died, but Martine was alive in 1935
and may still be living.</p></note>

<pb n="376"/>

<p>
Kaitah told these men, "All of you are my friends, and some of you are my
brothers-in-law. I think a lot of you Indians, and I don't want you to get
killed. The troops are coming after you from all directions, from all over the
United States. You people have no chance whatever. The War Department's aim is
to kill every one of you if it takes fifty years to hunt you down. But if you
people come as the government wants you to do, they will not harm you at all.
Everything is against you. Even pieces of stick will hurt you. At night you do
not rest as you should. If you are awake at night and a rock rolls down the
mountain or a stick breaks, you will be running. The high cliff even is your
enemy. At night you go around, and you might fall off the cliff. You have the
wild animals for your enemies. You even eat your meals running. You have no
friends whatever in the world.</p>

<p>
"So I beg you, my friends, do what the government wants you to do. That's what
I'm up here for. I have followed you people around for several months. It's not
a very pleasant life. So agree with me. I live at the agency. I live peaceably.
Nobody bothers me. I sleep well; I get plenty to eat. I go wherever I want, talk
to good people. I go to bed whenever I want and get all my sleep. I have nobody
to fear. I have my little patch of corn. I'm trying to do what the white people
want me to do. And there's no reason why you people shouldn't do it. I'm doing
it. I know you people could do it. You all agree with me and behave yourself and
go back to the reservation with me. We'll live longer, more happily, and rest
better. So I want you to go down with me when the troops come, and they want you
to come down on the flats and have a council with them."
</p>

<p>
Then all these men said, "All right, we'll do what you say, and we'll come
down."
</p>

<p>
Kaitah had kept watching for Martine. Martine hadn't come up yet all through the
conversation. And Kaitah wondered what was wrong, and he went down a little way.
There was Martine coming, listening for gun-fire too, I guess. And when Kaitah
came to Martine he ordered him to go down and tell Wratten to run his horse back
and get those troops on the flat as fast as possible. So Martine went.
</p>

<pb n="377"/>
<p>
When he came back Kaitah was eating and joking with the men. Then the troops
came. They came where Lieutenant Gatewood was. So at that time they sent a
despatch to Fort Bowie that they had Geronimo and that General Miles should meet
them half way. Then they brought all those families down.
</p>

<p>
They had a little talk. They came to an agreement to take them to Fort Bowie.
Right here one army officer told them that General Miles would meet them on the
way to Fort Bowie. They hadn't disarmed them yet. That day they took them and
went with them all day till dark. They weren't guarded. Some of those men were
running on the side, hunting as they went along. Next day General Miles met
them. He came in a government stage coach. They met again the next day.
</p>

<p>
General Miles, when he met them, asked Geronimo to hold a conference with him.
General Miles, the way Kaitah tells this story, said, "The people of these three
states, the State of Arizona, the State of New Mexico,<ref target="b23" n="27">23</ref> and the State of Mexico, are enforcing laws to capture
you or bring you back dead. We were forced to look for you. When we are forced
to look for you, we must carry out our orders. We are like slaves. We have to do
according to what the people of the United States say. In these two states, New
Mexico and Arizona, the governments and the people do not like the way you have
been treating them, killing them, taking their stock and destroying the homes of
the settlers. They made a law to force the War Department either to kill you or
bring you back alive. If you fight, we will kill you. If you surrender, we will
bring you back alive. You have killed many settlers, killed many soldiers, and
taken their horses and mules and other equipment. The people do not like it. You
see those mountains over there. If you do not agree with me that what I am
telling you is the best thing you could do, I give you the privilege to go to
your mountains. I'll give you a whole night and a day before I follow your gang.
Then I shall kill every last one of you, even your children. But if you want to
go back with me to Fort Bowie and be peaceful and faithful like other Apaches
who are at Fort Bowie and San Carlos, all right. Take your choice.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b23" n="27"><seg type="note-symbol">23.</seg><p> Both Arizona and New Mexico were still territories at this
time, of course.
</p></note>

<pb n="378"/>
<p>
"The government has spent several million dollars in order to catch you. You
have taken many lives. You have destroyed many homes. Those people you have
destroyed are human just like you. They wanted to live. Why should you do that?
And there's Kaedine.<ref target="b24" n="28">24</ref> He was one of the dangerous
young war chieftains. He's right here in the midst of us now. He has rendered me
a great service. A two year sentence in a California Federal prison has done him
good. Since he got back he admits that he used to do wrong. I have high respect
for him, for turning into as good a man as he is since he got back.
</p>

<p>
"Now, Geronimo, Naiche, all you men, members of this band, you could do as well
as this Kaedine did, maybe better. Instead of that you have everything on earth
against you, and you live, dodging people, like a coyote, ambushing innocent
people. I'm here under authority to take you to Fort Bowie. There I will put you
in prison until further orders from Washington. Now I'd like to hear from you,"
he told Geronimo.
</p>
<p>
Now Geronimo talked. He didn't say very much. What little he said covered a lot
though.
</p>

<p>
"I agree with you about taking us back. You said just the right thing when you
told me that everything is my enemy. It's just the way of you white people. You
always have a ground of your own to make your statement as though it was the
only true statement. But there is still something that causes you to criticize
us in that manner. The earth is listening to us. The winds listen to us. The sun
sees us and hears everything we say, all these things.
</p>


<note place="foot" id="b24" n="28"><seg type="note-symbol">24.</seg><p> The name means "No Arrows" and implies that the individual is
so brave he has shot them all. Kaedine was one of the leading spirits of the
Chiricahua raids of the early '80's. After his surrender to General Crook in
1883 the prison sentence to which reference ia made was imposed. After his
return he assisted the government in pacifying the rest of his tribesmen.
</p></note>

<pb n="379"/>

<p>
"The second time I went on the war-path it was because of your having so many
Indian secret service men telling you some false story about me. 'Geronimo is
going to do this,' 'Geronimo says this,' `You ought to have Geronimo in some
jail,' and so on. Some of your own white soldiers, when they saw me and some of
my men, would motion as though they were going to cut our throats.
</p>

<p>
"When I was on the reservation before, you people taught me nothing. You did not
come to my home or teach
me how other people live. You are here right in the midst of these soldiers.
Where have you ever tried to he1p me? Then.you criticize me for killing white
people here. I did kill many Mexicans, but I have never killed as many white
people as you say I have. I know some of your big generals. You become generals
just because you are good liars. Why I tell you that you are a liar right in the
midst of your troops
is that you never have caught me shooting. And now, General Miles, I have come
with my men to you with good will, but I know just what you are going to do. You
will say this, I know: 'I have caught Geronimo while he was shooting and made
him surrender to me.'" That's what he told General
Miles.
</p>

<p>
"I'm here. The earth, the sun, and the winds all listen to me. <foreign lang="apa">Yusn</foreign><ref target="b25" n="29">25</ref> listens to me. I do not
lie to you. I lay my arms down. I will not ask for mercy. If you wish, line us
up and shoot us today or tomorrow. I won't care. I'll take my medicine like a
man. So here's my gun." And he and his men laid their guns down.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b25" n="29"><seg type="note-symbol">25.</seg><p> <foreign lang="apa">Yusn</foreign> is an Apache loan word
from the Spanish <foreign lang="spa">D&iacute;os</foreign>. The final <hi
rend="italic">n</hi> is a relative, having the force of "he who is."
</p></note>

<pb n="380"/>

<p>
Then General Miles talked again. He shook hands with Geronimo. "No, don't have
that idea, Geronimo. We do not kill people who don't offer any fight. What I
said a while ago to you, I repeat. I will take you back to Fort Bowie, have you
under guard as prisoner until further orders from Washington. As I said a moment
ago, I have to carry out my orders from the War Department." And General Miles
said, "I myself do not like the idea, but I'm a soldier of the United States,
and I get my orders. If I don't obey them, they have me under guard just as I'm
going to have you under guard. Don't worry about what they may do to you, for
you are causing all this trouble; you brought it on yourself."
</p>

<p>
So they took all their arms. Then they decided to go. They took Geronimo in that
coach, and Naiche and Perico and the principal men rode with Miles. The men,
women, and children were followed by Indian scouts and several troops of
cavalry. In a day or so they were in Fort Bowie. They had Geronimo already under
guard in prison when the rest got there. They had that small band in prison,
women, children, and all. They had those men and women under armed guard, had
them working with picks and shovels making ditches around the post. They had
Chihuahua's little band, just a few men, already in prison when Geronimo
arrived. They were working too, under armed guard.
</p>

<p>
And Mangus was still out with a very small group, three or four men. General
Miles had spoken at the council with Geronimo about this and told Geronimo, "It
is not necessary to run down Mangus, because it will mean just so much more
expense, more hardships for the soldiers. He can keep going if he wants to, but
he will not get anywhere; for I know, Geronimo, when he hears that you and
Chihuahua have made peace with the government, he will not be out there by
himself any longer. I know he will come into one of these reservations, San
Carlos or Fort Apache."
</p>

<p>
That first band captured in the fall of 1886, Chihuahua's little band, they took
to Fort Marion, St. Augustine, Florida, and put them in prison.<ref target="b26" n="30">26</ref> It's one of the oldest posts in the United States, right
on the edge of the ocean, where, when the heavy tide comes in, it flaps against
the building. It is an old Spanish fort made of stone and cement.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b26" n="30"><seg type="note-symbol">26.</seg><p> Chihuahua has a son, Eugene Chihuahua, and a daughter still
living at Mescalero.</p></note>

<pb n="381"/>

<p>
Geronimo's band, the second group captured, was taken to San Antonio, Texas.
They had them in prison there for several months.
</p>

<p>
The third group taken was composed of the faithful Indians who lived at Fort
Apache. After all the Indian scouts came home from the expedition, when they
thought they were all at home at Fort Apache, they called all the Indian scouts
together and lined them up.<ref target="b27" n="31">27</ref> Then the commander
ordered his troops to take their belts and ammunition and their guns away from
them. By order of the commander to his soldiers, they herded the scouts in the
horse barn and guarded them day and night. They threw them horse blankets to li
on. Soldiers guarded them, the very men they had gone out with before. If they
wanted to urinate the soldiers went with them.
</p>
<p>
After these Indians had gone through all these hardships for the good of the
people of these two states, they did this to them. Many of these scouts and most
of the other Indians were farming all this time at the agency. Some of them had
sheep, some had goats, some had mule teams, wagons, harnesses; some of them had
horses and fine saddles.
</p>

<p>
The Chiricahua scouts did not know what was happening. That night the Western
Apache gave a big social dance, and the women were in there dancing. No one was
worried. Suddenly the escort wagons were there. They herded the children, the
women, and the old men at the camps down to the agency. They loaded them on
escort wagons. They wouldn't allow any of them to carry any kind of weapon. They
just let them take what they had on, a shawl, a blanket. All the crops were
ready to be gathered. I was about ten or eleven years old then, and I was one of
them.
</p>

<p>
The nearest railroad station was at Holbrook, Arizona. It is about a hundred
miles away, maybe a little more, I don't know. That's where they were taking us,
to load us on a train for Fort Marion, St. Augustine, Florida, the same place
where Chihuahua was. They took us from Fort Apache to Holbrook in escort wagons,
a two or three days' trip in escort wagons, strung out, a long way.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b27" n="31"><seg type="note-symbol">27.</seg><p> The Indian scouts referred to are the Chiricahua who had been
serving the government in the Geronimo campaign.
</p></note>

<pb n="382"/>

<p>
I was with my father in an escort wagon. My mother was with some other people. I
didn't know where she was until we got off at Holbrook. Then I found her. At
Holbrook the Indians had a big dance that night with the Western Apache scouts,
negroes, and white people all present.
</p>

<p>
We didn't know where we were to be taken from Holbrook. Some thought we were
going to be taken to the ocean and thrown in. Some thought we were going to be
killed in some other way.
</p>

<p>
These people, these Chiricahua Apache, who lived at Fort Apache peacefully, and
the scouts who had helped the army run down Geronimo's band, were taken to
prison for what Geronimo had done.
</p>

<p>
And I say this much about it. The white man plants corn. But he puts two kernels
in the ground. One good kernel will yield, but one rotten kernel will kill the
good one if you put them together. So, as smart as the white people pretend to
be, there's one time they planted a good kernel with a rotten one. The shadow of
the shameful way they treated these faithful Indians and United States Scouts
still lies over us.
</p>

<p>
At Holbrook, Arizona, they loaded us on a train, and they took us to Fort
Marion, St. Augustine, Florida.
</p>

<p>
It was the first time most of us had seen a train. When that train was coming
along the river and it whistled, many said it was run by lightning, and they
began to pray to the train. I saw many old men and women do&iacute;ng this. They said,
"Bless us, that we may be blessed wherever we go."
</p>

<p>
Lots of the children were running out in the brush. They were afraid of the
train. The soldiers had to chase them and get them in. I ran away from them;
they had to catch me. I was afraid. I was thinking that they were taking me
somewhere to kill me. I was so afraid. I had so much serious fear in me, that I
don't know how I felt.
</p>

<pb n="383"/>

<p>
It took us about a week to get to St. Augustine. There were two soldiers at each
door. The train stopped somewhere around Albuquerque, New Mexico, in the plains,
and we were told to get off. The Chiricahua all thought it was their last day.
The soldiers came with hardtack barrels and fed us. The rest of the time we ate
on the train. They drove us back in there and we went on. It was the only time
we got off. The soldiers kept making motions as if they were going to cut our
throats every time they went through the train to give coffee. The Indians, poor
and ignorant, took it that they were going to have their throats cut.
</p>
<p>
There was one scout, Massi, who jumped off the train.<ref target="b28" n="32">28</ref> He jumped in sandy place somewhere in Colorado. He got
away. He was one of the scouts who had been in that battle where Crawford had
been killed. He's a relative of Stephen, Duncan, and Benjamin.<ref target="b29" n="33">29</ref> He was related to Duncan's father. He got back here and
was wild for a long time. He never came to town. Once he ran away with a woman
who was gathering pi&ntilde;on nuts at Rinconada. He forced her to go. He just
threw her on his back and went off to the San Andreas Mountains. They chased him
but couldn't catch him.
</p>

<p>
This woman is still living and is the wife of a Spanish American.<ref target="b30" n="34">30</ref> She told the story once that he sent her home with all
the children. She came back with a lot of children. All died except one, who is
living now. She's married to a Mescalero. Those children were born in the wilds.
This woman was a Mescalero. She's a relative of Marion Simms,<ref target="b31" n="35">31</ref> calls him cousin.
</p>
<note place="foot" id="b28" n="32"><seg type="note-symbol">28.</seg><p> This individual has been confused with Apache kid and ia
often spoken of as the Apache Kid by white men who live in the vicinity of the
Mescalero Indian Reaervation.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b29" n="33"><seg type="note-symbol">29.</seg><p> Stephen Gaji, Duncan Balachu, and Benjamin Astoyah are the
persons meant. So far as I know, the first two are still alive at Mescalero. The
last named has died recently.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b30" n="34"><seg type="note-symbol">30.</seg><p> This woman has since died.</p></note>

<note place="foot" id="b31" n="35"><seg type="note-symbol">31.</seg><p> Marion Simms, a prominent Mescalero Apache, has died since
this account was taken.</p></note>

<pb n="384"/>

<p>
On that train we slept the best we could sitting up. Little children were put in
that rack where you put packages.
</p>

<p>
We arrived, the last party, in that place at night, moonlight, about ten or
eleven o'clock. It's a big place made out of cement and stones. It has a great
dungeon under it. It's dark; even in daytime you have to carry a lantern. Those
dungeons are filled with nothing but cannon balls and ammunition. There is a big
place about fifteen yards wide all around on top, with a cement wall about four
feet high so you couldn't fall over. On each corner of that wall is a square, a
little tower made out of stone and concrete with windows on each side. It was a
lookout tower, I believe. On that run-around they had been setting up army tents
thick. We were up there on a cement floor, and we had no privilege to move our
tents. We had to stay right there.
</p>

<p>
And they had a big gate down there where they brought us in, and it was guarded
by soldiers. The Indians were not allowed to leave that gate without permission.
Just certain people were allowed to get out.
</p>

<p>
They began to send the children to schools, the ones about fourteen or fifteen
years old who were able to go. In the morning they strung out those poor
children, and without trying to dress them up like their own class of people,
they sent them to school. Wearing moccasins, some of them, some of them going
barefooted, they were compelled to go to the Catholic school in the city. They
wore their loin cloths, wore rags around their heads, and were bare-legged. And
they sent them into that city to the Catholic school every day until the
Catholic school was burned down one night. These Chiricahua children were turned
in as prisoners every evening. They were watched as well as the older people.
</p>

<p>
Later General R. H. Pratt (Captain Pratt then) was selected as Superintendent of
Carlisle Indian School in Pennsylvania. He came to Fort Marion, took all the
children under the authority of the Department, put them on board ship to New
York somewhere. From there they took

<pb n="385"/>

a train to Carlisle Indian School. Some of those children who were taken from
there are still living today&mdash;Duncan Balachu, Arnold Kinzuni, Charlie Isti, Dora
Isti, Hugh Chee, Asa Dat-ogi, David Kaja, and others. There were over a hundred
children taken. The ones that went to Carlisle were only at St. Augustine one
month.
</p>

<p>
I have told you that Chihuahua was the first, and the biggest bunch, the
faithful tribe, came next. I don't know how many months we were there when
Geronimo and his band came. They shipped him right to an island, to Pensacola,
Fort Pickens. We could see the island from Fort Marion.
</p>

<p>
We were at Fort Marion for about six months. At Fort Marion my mother, my
sister, and I lived in one of those tents. They issued out bread and meat each
day. We did our own cooking. There was no wood there. Wood was given, a little,
and a place to cook was provided in one of the dungeons below. We had to sleep
on the hard cement floor. It was warm there in Florida. Bananas grow there.
</p>

<p>
It was a tough life. I was a little fellow, and I never stole anything, never,
did harm to anyone. They kept me a prisoner for twenty-seven years. It's the
same with Blind Tom.<ref target="b32" n="36">32</ref> He was blind; he wasn't harming
anyone, but he was taken prisoner too. He had to be led around. If I were
offered a hundred more years of life like that, I would say "No." Many died at
St. Augustine. We were not used to the climate.
</p>

<p>
As I told you, the worst bandits, Geronimo and his people, they put on the
island over there, Pensacola. Geronimo, Naiche, Perico, Jasper Kanseah,<ref target="b33" n="37">33</ref> Jewett Tisnoltos, and Asa were there. Chihuahua was not
there then. He had been out with Geronimo on the war-path from the beginning,
but when things got too hot, they separated from Geronimo's band and got chased
to Fort Bowie, Arizona. This was in 1886. They were the first ones to be sent
away. They were sent to Florida&mdash;Chihuahua, Ozoni, his brother, Eugene, Ramona,
Hosea Second, and others. They were all relatives it seems. The women were sent
too, whole families. This was about a month before Geronimo was captured.
</p>

<note place="foot" id="b32" n="36"><seg type="note-symbol">32.</seg><p> Blind Tom Lasinasti was still living at Mescalero
recently.</p></note>
<note place="foot" id="b33" n="37"><seg type="note-symbol">33.</seg><p> Jasper Kanseah was chief of police at Mescalero when this
account was being recorded.</p></note>

<pb n="386"/>


<p>
Kaitah and Martine were taken with Geronimo's people. They had gone up to the
Sierra Madre to get Geronimo to surrender. They had done a valuable service to
the government. Still they were taken prisoner. They took them to San Antonio,
Texas. They had them in prison there for about a month or so. And all those
scouts who had been after Geronimo were straying back to F&oacute;rt Apache. Some got
in in a week; some took longer. They came in on foot, with sore feet, and some
nearly starved. Then they were made prisoners.
</p>

<p>
Geronimo's band was taken to Fort Pickens, Pensacola, an island near the shore
where we were. We knew they were there because when the army ship went from the
shore to the island some men went along and saw them. But they didn't come over
and visit us. They were not allowed to leave. The women of that band were there
too, whole families were there.<lb/><lb/>
Reed College, Portland, Oregon.
</p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
