<?xml version="1.0"?>

<?dlps id="UVA" rend="none"?>
<?dlps page-images="none" figure-images="no"?>
<?dlps transcription="none"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY Somerville_0001.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0001.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0002.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0002.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0003.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0003.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0004.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0004.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0005.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0005.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0006.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0006.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0007.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0007.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0008.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0008.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0009.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0009.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0010.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0010.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0011.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0011.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0012.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0012.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0013.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0013.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0014.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0014.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0015.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0015.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0016.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0016.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0017.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0017.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0018.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0018.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0019.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0019.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0020.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0020.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0021.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0021.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0022.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0022.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0023.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0023.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0024.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0024.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0025.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0025.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0026.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0026.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0027.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0027.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0028.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0028.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0029.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0029.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0030.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0030.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0031.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0031.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0032.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0032.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
<!ENTITY Somerville_0033.tif SYSTEM "Somerville_0033.tif" NDATA uvaBitonal>
]>
<TEI.2 id="UVA" >
<teiHeader type="AACR2">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Brief Epitomes of the Lives of Eminent Women</title>
<author>Rose Somerville</author>
<respStmt>
<resp>TEI P4 XML markup in conformance with the uva-tei-spoken DTD</resp>
<name>AEL Data</name>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
<idno type="DLPS ID">Somerville</idno>
<idno type="Virgo ID">Somerville</idno>
<idno type="title control number">does not exist</idno>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc><bibl/></sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text id="t1">
<front id="t1-front">
<pb n="Front Cover" entity="Somerville_0001.tif"/>
<titlePage id="d3">
<pb entity="Somerville_0002.tif"/>
<docTitle>
<titlePart type="main"><hi rend="gothic">Brief Epitomes <lb/>
of the Libes of <lb/>
Eminent Women</hi></titlePart>
</docTitle>
<figure rend="inline" id="f1"/>
<byline>
<hi rend="gothic">By <lb/>
Rose Somerville</hi>
</byline>
<docImprint>
<publisher><hi rend="gothic">Printed and published by the <lb/>
Women's Printing Society, Limited</hi></publisher>
<pubPlace><hi rend="gothic">66, Whitcomb Street, W.C.</hi></pubPlace>
<hi rend="gothic">Price Threepence</hi> <lb/>
<pb entity="Somerville_0003.tif"/>
<hi rend="italic">This little book has been issued as the <lb/>
first of a series which it is hoped may <lb/>
meet the frequently expressed desire for <lb/>
brief epitomes of the lives of eminent <lb/>
women.</hi>
</docImprint>
</titlePage>
</front>
<body id="t1-body">
<div1 type="part" id="d5">
<pb n="3" entity="Somerville_0004.tif"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">MRS. JOSEPHINE BUTLER.</hi></head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">The</hi> most esteemed leaders of men and of <lb/>
movements have been those who recognised <lb/>
and could supply the need of the hour, those <lb/>
who turned danger into opportunity by making <lb/>
it serve a noble purpose. Not for bravery <lb/>
alone, a general famous, but also for his <lb/>
genius in communicating the same quality to <lb/>
the rank and file of his army. The influence <lb/>
of such a leader is multiplied a thousand times, <lb/>
and he is, in a very real sense, the creator of <lb/>
those virtues in others which his own example <lb/>
has called into existence. Mere contact with <lb/>
great men leads us to strive to imitate them, <lb/>
we unconsciously accept them as our law givers, <lb/>
and mould our actions somewhat after their <lb/>
pattern.</p>
<p>Such a leader is Mrs. Josephine Butler, the <lb/>
champion of Social Purity, and a representative <lb/>
woman of this century. Not only did she <lb/>
ennoble the cause for which she fought, but those <lb/>
serving under her were the better, individually <lb/>
and morally, for her existence. The timid were <lb/>
strengthened, the doubtful convinced, and <lb/>
many who were selfish or apathetic were <lb/>
roused into action by her words and example. <lb/>
Although an ardent worker for Women's <lb/>
<pb n="4" entity="Somerville_0005.tif"/>
Suffrage, it was the misery of the forlorn <reg orig="out-|casts">outcasts</reg> <lb/>
of society which appealed to her most <lb/>
strongly in the name of justice and humanity. <lb/>
In Liverpool, her work in refuges and hospitals <lb/>
had already convinced her that wherever <lb/>
cruelty and injustice go unpunished it is always <lb/>
the women who suffer most. It was no "cure <lb/>
of souls" she sought, but an overwhelming <lb/>
sense of the brotherhood of all humanity that led <lb/>
her to go forth and help those who were too <lb/>
feeble to help themselves, and to bring them <lb/>
within the shelter and warmth of her own home. <lb/>
Writing in answer to vile calumnies she <lb/>
said:&mdash;"I have but one little spare room in my <lb/>
house, and in it I have received with my <lb/>
husband's joyful consent, one after another of <lb/>
these my fallen sisters. We have given to <lb/>
them in the hour of trouble, sickness and death, <lb/>
the best that our house would afford, and <lb/>
requested friends of a higher rank who visited <lb/>
us, to go to a neighbouring hotel."</p>
<p>From this early championship of others'<lb/>
wrongs she was led into the heat and din of a <lb/>
warfare which lasted seventeen years. In 1869<lb/>
Acts had been passed which placed vice under <lb/>
State protection &lpar;<hi rend="italic">regulation,</hi> it was called&rpar;, in all <lb/>
garrison towns and within fifteen miles' radius. <lb/>
We are told, variously, that these Acts were <lb/>
"smuggled through the House of Commons,"<lb/>
<pb n="5" entity="Somerville_0006.tif"/>
that they were "passed in a fit of <reg orig="absent-|mindedness">absentmindedness</reg>," <lb/>
and that "Ministers did not <lb/>
understand their scope or the nature of their <lb/>
operation." But when we remember that their <lb/>
repeal was the result of seventeen years' <reg orig="per-|sistent">persistent</reg> <lb/>
agitation, that the whole country was <lb/>
divided, not into political parties, but into <lb/>
camps "for" and "against" the Repeal, one <lb/>
suspects the "absent-mindedness" in the House <lb/>
of Commons to have been extremely partial!<lb/>
Moreover, we learn that an attempt had been <lb/>
made to frame similar Acts at the beginning of <lb/>
the Queen's reign, but that Lord John Russell <lb/>
and Lord Melbourne protested that they could <lb/>
not ask the young Queen to sign them, as <hi rend="italic">she <lb/>
might want them explained to her!</hi> So the evil day <lb/>
was put off. These facts convince us that <lb/>
ministers had only too well realised "their <lb/>
scope or the nature of their operation."<lb/>
When finally they were presented for Royal <lb/>
Assent the Queen's grief at the death of <lb/>
the Prince Consort had so dulled her senses for <lb/>
a time to outside concerns that she signed them <lb/>
without comment.</p>
<p>It took but a short time for the victims of this <lb/>
infamous legislation to discover the cruelty,insult <lb/>
and misery to which they were subjected under <lb/>
it. Rumours spread, facts were verified, <reg orig="sur-|prise">surprise</reg> <lb/>
and horror quickened into burning <lb/>
<pb n="6" entity="Somerville_0007.tif"/>
indignation, and in the winter of 1867 the <lb/>
agitation for their repeal began. To the lasting <lb/>
honour of men, be it said, the first protest <lb/>
came from them. Daniel Cooper &lpar;of the <lb/>
Rescue Society&rpar; aided by John Stabb, E. W. <lb/>
Thomas, W. Hornbrook and others were the <lb/>
first to take up arms; later Sir James &lpar;then <lb/>
Mr.&rpar; Stansfeld relinquished his political career <lb/>
and sacrificed every worldly consideration for <lb/>
the cause, piloting the Repeal Bill through <lb/>
many a stormy session to its triumphant issue.</p>
<p>Mrs. Josephine Butler,<ref target="n1" n="1">*</ref>
<note id="n1" place="foot" n="1"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg><p><hi rend="italic">Life of Josephine Butler.</hi> W. T. Stead.</p></note>
 after vainly trying to <lb/>
resist the inward call to be "the Lord's <lb/>
Scavenger," bravely came forward and led the <lb/>
women. She, who had never spoken in public, <lb/>
began on this most difficult of all subjects, <lb/>
standing before the eyes of the whole world <lb/>
while every vile and odious epithet the basest <lb/>
could invent, was flung at her, and every evil <lb/>
motive ascribed to her actions. But in all that <lb/>
long struggle her step never faltered nor her <lb/>
courage failed, she spoke, wrote, canvassed <lb/>
and lectured unceasingly, and the movement <lb/>
grew till the whole country was covered with a <lb/>
network of organisations which actively <reg orig="dis-|tributed">distributed</reg> <lb/>
information and printed matter, <lb/>
collected signatures and drew up petitions. <lb/>
Her first appeal was to those in authority&mdash;
<pb n="7" entity="Somerville_0008.tif"/>
bishops, peers and ministers,&mdash;but scarce half a <lb/>
dozen replies were elicited. Grown wiser, she <lb/>
made her next appeal to the people, who ardently <lb/>
supported her,&mdash;for was she not fighting for the <lb/>
honour of their wives and daughters? The <lb/>
enthusiasm of the labouring men in the market <lb/>
place at Newark, on the occasion of her first <lb/>
speech, must have been very touching. She tells <lb/>
us she stood up in a cart on a market night with <lb/>
the men crowding round her, the moonlight <lb/>
shining on their faces, while they listened to <lb/>
"the lady who has come to tell us something <lb/>
about our daughters." In many places the <lb/>
opposition she encountered was intense. At <lb/>
Colchester, during the famous election of 1870, <lb/>
she was sent for by the local organisation to <lb/>
commence a campaign in that town. It was a <lb/>
three-cornered fight, one candidate, Sir Henry <lb/>
Storkes &lpar;L&rpar; against the Repeal &lpar;and throughout <lb/>
their bitterest and most powerful opponent&rpar;, <lb/>
the other two, Dr. Baxter Layly &lpar;L&rpar; and <lb/>
Colonel Learmouth &lpar;C&rpar; being in its favour. <lb/>
Meetings were held, and new adherents to the <lb/>
cause of National Purity daily joined the <lb/>
ranks. Mrs. Butler's influence soon became <lb/>
felt, and gained a hold on the people, which <lb/>
roused her enemies to fury. During one of <lb/>
these meetings an excited mob, chiefly composed <lb/>
of brothel-keepers and their hirelings, vowed she <lb/>
<pb n="8" entity="Somerville_0009.tif"/>
should not leave the hall alive, but she made <lb/>
her escape through a window at the back, and, <lb/>
after sheltering in a deserted yard far a time, <lb/>
regained her lodgings safely. Threats of <reg orig="per-|sonal">personal</reg> <lb/>
violence did not silence her, insult, scorn <lb/>
and fierce persecution did not move her. She <lb/>
altered her dress a little every day to escape <lb/>
observation, assumed her maiden name of <lb/>
"Grey," and continued to counsel and engineer <lb/>
her little band as before. She had the greatest <lb/>
difficulty in obtaining lodgings, for no sooner <lb/>
did her abode become known, than a howling <lb/>
mob would collect round it, smashing the <lb/>
windows and threatening to burn the place <lb/>
down if she were not brought out. Usually, <lb/>
after such a scene, she was respectfully but <lb/>
firmly requested by her host to seek shelter <lb/>
elswhere. On one occasion, she was roused in <lb/>
the night by the terrified innkeeper, who <lb/>
implored her to escape at once while there was <lb/>
time, as there was a crowd round the inn <lb/>
breaking the windows and trying to force the <lb/>
door! She was hurried out at the back to the <lb/>
dwelling of a poor woman where she thankfully <lb/>
finished the night. But her triumph at the <lb/>
poll was complete, the "Repeal" Conservative <lb/>
candidate getting 1,364 votes, Sir Henry <lb/>
Storkes, 853!</p>
<p>Many times her life was in danger from those <lb/>
<pb n="9" entity="Somerville_0010.tif"/>
who trafficked and grew rich on the miseries <lb/>
of "unfortunates." Once, during a women's <lb/>
prayer meeting, held in a loft for lack of better <lb/>
accommodation, a crowd of men attempted to <lb/>
set fire to it, and swarming up the ladder <lb/>
heaped abuse and execrations upon her. <lb/>
Fearing for the safety of her little flock, she led <lb/>
the way by jumping clean from the loft to <lb/>
the ground, the others quickly following. <lb/>
We are told, on this occasion the police looked <lb/>
In to see what was going on, but went away <lb/>
again without offering any assistance!</p>
<p>Public opinion, however, became roused in <lb/>
earnest, and letters of encouragement flowed in <lb/>
from all parts. Garibaldi, Mazzini, Jules <lb/>
Simon, Cardinal Manning, Mary Somerville, <lb/>
Harriet Martineau and a host of others wrote <lb/>
expressing sympathy with the cause. Even <lb/>
the Pope sent a message of approval. Space <lb/>
does not admit of further details being given, <lb/>
but the struggle was continued unabated up to <lb/>
1886, when these infamous Acts were finally <lb/>
repealed, receiving the Royal Assent on April <lb/>
16th, 1886.</p>
<p>In paying the tribute of gratitude and <lb/>
remembrance to those who took their part in <lb/>
the early days of this combat against the most <lb/>
hideous of social evils, we must not forget that <lb/>
women, who spoke publicly what they thought <lb/>
<pb n="10" entity="Somerville_0011.tif"/>
privately, were howled down as "unsexed" or <lb/>
"failures," regarded as desiring notoriety, or <lb/>
as having private grievances to avenge. Mrs. <lb/>
Butler's own words tell us of the rare <reg orig="perfect-|ness">perfectness</reg> <lb/>
of that home life which was hers, giving <lb/>
complete refutation to these charges, were any <lb/>
needed.</p>
<p>"I love my fellow workers and they love me, <lb/>
and nothing could be dearer than the friendship <lb/>
between us, but what I so deeply regret is that <lb/>
comparatively few of them can follow me into <lb/>
the wonderful sweetness and sympathy of family <lb/>
life. &hellip; It I have been anything, I have <lb/>
been a wife and mother, and that has been <lb/>
more than any public work I have ever done. <lb/>
There is a quickening impulse, and of a kind <lb/>
superior to any other in the union for the <lb/>
public good of two souls&mdash;husband and wife. <lb/>
There is a vital force, a family force which is <lb/>
greater than the individual force. It must be <lb/>
because it is doubled. No one knows how <lb/>
much of that force I owe to my husband and <lb/>
my family. Our married life was an idyll all <lb/>
through, and at the end much more romantic <lb/>
than at the beginning. &hellip; My father <lb/>
was a noble man, my brothers were noble men; <lb/>
for nobility of character, justice, sweetness, <lb/>
righteousness, I know of no one to surpass my <lb/>
husband. My sons have a great deal of their <lb/>
<pb n="11" entity="Somerville_0012.tif"/>
father's character, being just and true and good <lb/>
&hellip; they have been a great happiness to me."</p>
<p>Mrs. Butler's efforts to combat the <reg orig="Legisla-|tion">Legislation</reg> <lb/>
of Vice were not confined to England. In <lb/>
1874 she travelled over the Continent, visiting <lb/>
Paris, Lyons, Marseilles, Genoa, Rome, many <lb/>
other places and Switzerland, <reg orig="interview-|ing">interviewing</reg> <lb/>
ministers, inspectors and deputies, visiting <lb/>
prisons and haunts of vice. From these <lb/>
devoted labours sprang the "British, <reg orig="Con-|tinental">Continental</reg> <lb/>
and General Federation for the <lb/>
Abolition of the State Regulation of Vice,"<lb/>
and she at present edits <hi rend="italic">The Dawn</hi>, a quarterly <lb/>
which gives an account of the work done by <lb/>
this Federation.</p>
<p>It remains for others to continue her work. <lb/>
She has made many speeches, and written not <lb/>
a few books, but no words of hers apply more <lb/>
significantly to the present time, than those she <lb/>
uttered in a little book called <hi rend="italic">Government by <lb/>
Police</hi> &lpar;1874&rpar;: "The price of Liberty is eternal <lb/>
vigilance, and never was that vigilance more <lb/>
called for than now. It was by high sacrifice <lb/>
of labour, without pause, even to the death, <lb/>
that the preservation of our best liberties in the <lb/>
past was purchased&hellip; Let us hope that <lb/>
great spirits will again arise amongst us, such as <lb/>
many of those who in the past willingly suffered <lb/>
and died for the maintenance of Liberty."</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="part" id="d6">
<pb n="12" entity="Somerville_0013.tif"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">FRANCES POWER COBBE.</hi></head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">Frances power cobbe</hi> tells us that <lb/>
mere existence has always been a <reg orig="pleas-|ure">pleasure</reg> <lb/>
to her, and as she believes that the views <lb/>
of life taken by a particularly healthy person <lb/>
are presumably more sound than those of one <lb/>
who is not healthy, we may argue from this <lb/>
that the most cheerful view is also the most <lb/>
sound one, and that society does not realise <lb/>
how much it owes to its cheerful members. <lb/>
If the old astrologers may be believed, Miss <lb/>
Cobbe was born at a very propitious hour, at <lb/>
sunrise. The Fates who rule this hour are <lb/>
supposed to give many good gifts to those born <lb/>
under their protection; and certainly little <lb/>
Frances seems to have had a happy life during <lb/>
her childhood in the big family mansion at <lb/>
Newbridge, in Ireland. Strong religious <reg orig="ten-|dencies">tendencies</reg> <lb/>
and a passion for writing verses were <lb/>
among the most marked of her early <reg orig="charac-|teristics">characteristics</reg>. <lb/>
She was brought up in a strictly <lb/>
puritan atmosphere, her parents being <reg orig="evan-|gelicals">evangelicals</reg> <lb/>
of the Clapham sect; Sunday was <lb/>
rigidly kept and prayers read daily. Frances, <lb/>
however, at that time, found keen pleasure in <lb/>
prayers and Bible readings, and when, later, <lb/>
doubts concerning the dogma of her early belief <lb/>
<pb n="13" entity="Somerville_0014.tif"/>
began to creep in and cloud her spiritual horizon, <lb/>
she would return to her first faith in a passion <lb/>
of tears and repentance. But the period of <lb/>
spiritual storm and stress inevitable to such a <lb/>
nature as hers had to be faced, and after much <lb/>
tribulation of mind, she at last floated into the <lb/>
peaceful waters of Theism, finding there a <lb/>
belief broad and strong enough to carry her <lb/>
through life.</p>
<p>Her education was carried on at home, <lb/>
until she was sent to a school in London to be <lb/>
"finished." Of education for women in her <lb/>
day she draws an astounding picture, and the <lb/>
account she gives of a finishing establishment <lb/>
for ladies of "birth and position" is as valuable <lb/>
as it is amusing. Deportment and music came <lb/>
first, English, writing and arithmetic last, on <lb/>
its curriculum. Competitive examinations <lb/>
seem to have been unheard of, but "every <lb/>
movement of the body in entering a room, in <lb/>
taking a seat and in rising from it was duly <lb/>
criticised." These high born young ladies <lb/>
were daily instructed in the art of "ascending <lb/>
and descending" &lpar;like Jacob's angels'&rpar; with <lb/>
calmness and grace, and without a too liberal <lb/>
display of ankle, from a dilapidated chariot that <lb/>
had been taken off its wheels and propped up <lb/>
somewhere in the back premises! On Ash <lb/>
Wednesday they were exhorted to abstain <lb/>
<pb n="14" entity="Somerville_0015.tif"/>
from roast mutton as "it would be good for <lb/>
their souls and figures!"<ref target="n2" n="1">*</ref>
<note id="n2" place="foot" n="1"><seg type="note-symbol">*</seg><p>Miss Cobbe's Autobiography.</p></note>
 It is difficult to believe <lb/>
that this was the only mental and moral training <lb/>
considered necessary to fit girls to serve the <lb/>
State in the capacity of wives and mothers, no <lb/>
other vocation being open to them, even <lb/>
supposing they had been qualified.</p>
<p>Miss Cobbe has been a prolific writer, <lb/>
although, so far as she knows, "not one of her <lb/>
ancestors ever dabbled in printer's ink." Her <lb/>
pen has pleaded vigorously and continuously <lb/>
for all reforms that have claimed her sympathy. <lb/>
It seemed inevitable that as soon as her feelings <lb/>
were stirred by any injustice, cruelty, or wrong, <lb/>
that her active brain should set to work <reg orig="with-|out">without</reg> <lb/>
delay to point out the evil, and, what is of <lb/>
still more value, suggest the remedy. She was <lb/>
on the staff of the <hi rend="italic">Echo</hi> &lpar;the first halfpenny <lb/>
paper&rpar; for seven years from its commencement, <lb/>
writing the social Leading Article, and during <lb/>
the whole of that time never once failing to go <lb/>
into the City daily in order to write it at the <lb/>
office! She contributed also to <hi rend="italic">Fraser's <lb/>
Magazine, Macmillan's</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Economist</hi> <lb/>
and many others, and it is difficult to <lb/>
over-estimate the good results arising from <lb/>
this union of heart and brain, for her broad and <lb/>
<pb n="15" entity="Somerville_0016.tif"/>
liberal views on social questions were embodied <lb/>
in essays, pamphlets and leaflets, and found <lb/>
their way into thousands of homes where they <lb/>
must have helped very largely to form public <lb/>
opinion, which is, after all, the real arbiter in <lb/>
these matters.</p>
<p>After her father's death, Miss Cobbe spent a <lb/>
year travelling on the continent, and then joined <lb/>
Mary Carpenter at Bristol in her Reformatory <lb/>
and Ragged School labours, continuing the <lb/>
work after Miss Carpenter's death. She visited <lb/>
workhouses and reformatories in many towns, <lb/>
and dived into the Bristol slums to find out what <lb/>
could be done to improve the condition of the <lb/>
Ragged School children at home, and she gives <lb/>
a pathetic account of the abject poverty and <lb/>
misery she found there. One story of a <reg orig="work-|house">work-house</reg> <lb/>
hospital in a provincial town is particularly <lb/>
suggestive. The matron had only lately been <lb/>
appointed to the post, and there were nearly <lb/>
500 sick and infirm patients. She remarked <lb/>
that the matron must find it heavy charge <lb/>
with only pauper nurses to assist her, <lb/>
but doubtless she had gone through a course <lb/>
of hospital training, and knew how to direct <lb/>
everything? "Oh dear no, madam,' the <lb/>
matron replied, with a toss of her capstrings, <lb/>
"it was <hi rend="italic">misfortune</hi> that brought me to this!" <lb/>
One fears her poor charges had quite as much <lb/>
<pb n="16" entity="Somerville_0017.tif"/>
reason to regret that;"misfortune" as she seemed <lb/>
to have! Her descriptions of the dreariness and <lb/>
utter blankness of the lives of these poor <reg orig="work-|house">work-house</reg> <lb/>
inmates and the coldness and harshness <lb/>
with which they were treated, make one rejoice <lb/>
that the advent of Women Guardians has made <lb/>
this state of things no longer possible, for Mary <lb/>
Carpenter was profoundly convinced that the <lb/>
cleverest Guardian of <hi rend="italic">her</hi> day "could be <lb/>
bamboozled by a matron in every department <lb/>
of her work."</p>
<p>Miss Cobbe, in addition to calling public <lb/>
attention to these evils through pamphlets and <lb/>
the press, sent round circulars, suggesting plans <lb/>
for the amelioration of the condition of pauper <lb/>
incurables, to all the workhouses in England. <lb/>
To many of these she received replies, warmly <lb/>
approving her scheme, and some Unions <lb/>
proceeded to carry out the reforms without <lb/>
delay, thus proving that evil is indeed wrought <lb/>
from want of thought at least as much as from <lb/>
want of heart. Her advice to those who visit the <lb/>
inmates of workhouses is excellent, and might <lb/>
be made to apply equally well to district visitors <lb/>
of the poor in their own homes. She says, <lb/>
"Do not imagine that your conversation <lb/>
will best cheer the poor souls, however well <lb/>
designed to entertain and instruct them. What <lb/>
will really brighten their dreary lives will be to <lb/>
<pb n="17" entity="Somerville_0018.tif"/>
make them talk themselves and so enjoy the <lb/>
privilege of a good listener. Draw them out <lb/>
about their old homes, ask them about their <lb/>
early lives, tell them any late news about the <lb/>
place where they lived, but, before all things, <lb/>
make them talk and show yourself interested <lb/>
in what they say."</p>
<p>During one of her trips to Italy, she inspected <lb/>
the hospitals there and was shocked to find <lb/>
that patients, suffering from the most horribly <lb/>
infectious diseases, were nursed in the same <lb/>
wards with cases of ordinary rheumatism and <lb/>
other minor complaints. She found the nurses, <lb/>
who in those days were all Sisters of Charity, <lb/>
"very proud of their tidy cupboards, full of <lb/>
lint and bandages, but very indifferent to their <lb/>
patients!"</p>
<p>The question of Women's Suffrage was first <lb/>
strongly brought to Miss Cobbe's notice by the <lb/>
Rev. J. J. May of Syracuse, Mass., who, when <lb/>
paying them a visit at Bristol, asked her why <lb/>
she should not have a vote? At once she <lb/>
began to wonder why the most law-abiding, <lb/>
temperate, and merciful half of the community <lb/>
"should be prevented from using the simplest <lb/>
and most direct means of achieving some public <lb/>
good or remedying some evil, merely because <lb/>
they were women?" Pamphlets and articles on <lb/>
the subject flowed from her pen. In one of <lb/>
<pb n="18" entity="Somerville_0019.tif"/>
these, which was reprinted several times, and <lb/>
which she called <hi rend="italic">Criminals, Idiots, Women <lb/>
and Minors,</hi> she enquired "whether the <reg orig="classi-|fication">classification</reg> <lb/>
should be counted sound?" She has <lb/>
also made many speeches on behalf of the <lb/>
Suffrage movement. But of all the work she <lb/>
has done for women, that in which she <lb/>
endeavoured to obtain the legal protection of <lb/>
ill-treated wives from the brutality of their <lb/>
husbands, has given her the most satisfaction. <lb/>
Being specially horrified one day at the long <lb/>
list of assaults on wives published in the <reg orig="news-|paper">newspaper</reg>, <lb/>
she procured statistics, proving that <lb/>
there were 1,500 cases of the kind every year <lb/>
in England, averaging four a day. At that time <lb/>
the only effectual remedy, divorce, was too <lb/>
costly a luxury for the poor, and there was <lb/>
nothing to prevent the enraged husbands <lb/>
returning, after a term of imprisonment, to kick <lb/>
and illtreat their poor victims worse than ever. <lb/>
Again she took up her pen in protestation, and <lb/>
through her influence a Bill, embodying her <lb/>
views, was drafted and read a first time in the <lb/>
House. Lord Penzance, however, having seen <lb/>
it, included it within the scope of his own <lb/>
"Bill to amend the Matrimonial Causes Acts," <lb/>
which, after many delays, eventually became <lb/>
law in 1878. Under this Act an ill-treated wife <lb/>
can obtain legal separation from her husband, <lb/>
<pb n="19" entity="Somerville_0020.tif"/>
retaining the care of her children &lpar;under ten <lb/>
years of age&rpar;, while her husband is bound to <lb/>
maintain her and them.</p>
<p>Miss Cobbe's name has always been <reg orig="con-|spicuously">conspicuously</reg> <lb/>
associated with the Anti-Vivisection <lb/>
movement. The horrors of vivisection on the <lb/>
continent first came under her notice in 1863, <lb/>
and swift went forth her indignant <reg orig="condem-|nation">condemnation</reg>, <lb/>
embodied in <hi rend="italic">The Rights of Man and <lb/>
the Claims of Brutes</hi>. She also drafted a <lb/>
Memorial which was sent to Professor Schiff, <lb/>
of the Specola at Florence, where animals were <lb/>
subjected for hours to the most unspeakable <lb/>
tortures at the hands of the vivisectionist. <lb/>
Although the Memorial was contemptuously <lb/>
tossed aside, it caused the subject to be <lb/>
discussed. Miss Cobbe exerted all her influence <lb/>
and a Bill was drafted for regulating <lb/>
the practice of vivisection in England; a <lb/>
Society was formed, which for four days <lb/>
consisted of four members&mdash;the Archbishop of <lb/>
York, Lord Shaftesbury, Dr. Hoggan and <lb/>
herself; it was then called the "Society for <lb/>
the Protection of Animals liable to Vivisection," <lb/>
and still has its offices at 20, Victoria Street. <lb/>
A deputation waited upon Lord Cross, urging <lb/>
him to bring in a Bill in accordance with the <lb/>
recommendations of a Royal Commission that <lb/>
had been appointed; this deputation was most <lb/>
<pb n="20" entity="Somerville_0021.tif"/>
favourably received, and a suitable Bill was <lb/>
framed which received the approval of the <lb/>
press, and which actually reached its second <lb/>
Reading in the House, when suddenly the <lb/>
medical profession rose in a body and protested <lb/>
in loud and vigorous terms against the <lb/>
insult which involved submitting <lb/>
their experiments on living animals to legal <lb/>
control. For note, this was not a Bill <reg orig="pro-|hibiting">prohibiting</reg> <lb/>
vivisection, but merely that it should <lb/>
be subject to legal supervision. Three thousand <lb/>
doctors signed the Memorial to the Home <lb/>
Secretary to reverse measure and make it <lb/>
one to legalise vivisection. This was presented <lb/>
by 300 &lpar;some say 800&rpar; doctors, and owing to <lb/>
the pressure brought to bear upon Parliament <lb/>
by the medical profession, a Bill to this effect <lb/>
was carried in 1876. Referring to this terrible <lb/>
blow to hopes that had been so near fulfilment, <lb/>
even after the lapse of eighteen years, Miss <lb/>
Cobbe speaks despondingly, "The world has <lb/>
never seemed quite the same to me since that <lb/>
dreadful time. Justice and mercy seemed gone <lb/>
from the earth."</p>
<p>Having once gauged the strength of the <lb/>
enemy by this bitter experience, she became <lb/>
convinced that nothing short of the total <lb/>
prohibition of vivisection would do any good. <lb/>
In six years 320 books and pamphlets have <lb/>
<pb n="21" entity="Somerville_0022.tif"/>
been issued from the Society, of which 271,351 <lb/>
copies have been printed. Miss Cobbe wrote <lb/>
173 of these papers herself. The work is still <lb/>
progressing, and the controversy is now one of <lb/>
the foremost questions of the day. In her essay, <lb/>
<hi rend="italic">Hopes of the Human Race</hi>, Miss Cobbe sets <lb/>
forth her belief that these hopes consist in <lb/>
the "dying out of the animal and the <reg orig="develop-|ment">development</reg> <lb/>
of the spiritual in man"; and it cannot <lb/>
fail to be a source of thankfulness to her that <lb/>
the Anti-Vivisection movement, which was once <lb/>
the concern solely of a society of four, is now <lb/>
an impulse finding its way to all sections and <lb/>
classes, and arresting the attention of some of <lb/>
the foremost thinkers of the day.</p>
<p>Miss Cobbe seems to have known most of <lb/>
her contemporaries who were in any way <lb/>
illustrious; she was an inveterate diner-out, <lb/>
calculating that in twenty years she went to <lb/>
no less than 2,000 dinners. In spite of her <lb/>
arduous labours, and perhaps because of them, <lb/>
she has found this world so pleasant a place <lb/>
that she would gladly live over again her span <lb/>
of seventy years&mdash;and this though no love affair <lb/>
has ever coloured it with romance. On this <lb/>
last point she speaks emphatically. Her book, <lb/>
she thinks, will be valuable "as affording <lb/>
evidence of how pleasant and interesting, and <lb/>
not altogether useless, life has been to a <lb/>
<pb n="22" entity="Somerville_0023.tif"/>
woman, although no man has desired to share <lb/>
it, nor has she seen a man whom she would <lb/>
have wished to have asked to have done so." <lb/>
Remembering that when Miss Cobbe was <lb/>
young, marriage was still the prevailing fashion, <lb/>
and that girls were brought up to consider the <lb/>
married state to be the only object in life <lb/>
worthy of attainment, one comes to the <reg orig="con-|clusion">conclusion</reg> <lb/>
that the "New Woman," so-called, is <lb/>
not the exclusive production of this latter end <lb/>
of the nineteenth century, but has flourished <lb/>
wherever women have had the courage to <lb/>
shape their lives according to the dictates of <lb/>
their own consciences.</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="part" id="d7">
<pb n="23" entity="Somerville_0024.tif"/>
<head><hi rend="bold">SISTER DORA.</hi></head>
<p><hi rend="small-caps">Dorothy pattison</hi>, the daughter of a <lb/>
clergyman and the youngest but one of <lb/>
twelve children, was born at Hauxwell in <lb/>
Yorkshire on January 16th, 1832. Very <lb/>
delicate when a child, she developed into a <lb/>
superb specimen of healthy, beautiful <reg orig="woman-|hood">womanhood</reg>, <lb/>
endowed with quick perceptions, a bright <lb/>
intellect and a perfectly inexhaustible fund of <lb/>
humour and good spirits. These qualities <lb/>
helped her over many difficult places in life and <lb/>
contributed in no small measure to her success. <lb/>
In spite of the pleasures of her free country life <lb/>
she early realised it could not give full scope to <lb/>
all the powers within her, and when Florence <lb/>
Nightingale's call to duty rang over England, <lb/>
penetrating even to the peaceful vicarage at <lb/>
Hauxwell, her whole nature responded to it, <lb/>
and she pleaded earnestly, but unsuccessfully, <lb/>
with her parents to be allowed to go out to the <lb/>
Crimea.</p>
<p>Several uneventful years slipped by, during <lb/>
which she did not relinquish her desire for a <lb/>
life of active service in the world, and at the <lb/>
age of twenty-nine she finally left home, even <lb/>
then against her father's wish, to be mistress <lb/>
of the village school at Little Woolston, near <lb/>
<pb n="24" entity="Somerville_0025.tif"/>
Bletchly. For a time she lived a happy busy <lb/>
life, winning all hearts by her sympathy and <lb/>
brightness. She did not here, however, find <lb/>
her true vocation. Of a deeply religious nature, <lb/>
this warm-hearted enthusiast longed still more <lb/>
to labour amongst the poor, and at the end of <lb/>
three years she left the school and joined the <lb/>
Sisterhood of the Good Samaritans at Coatham. <lb/>
On her entrance, she was put through a severe <lb/>
course of training. The unquestioning <reg orig="obedi-|ence">obedience</reg> <lb/>
exacted by the rules of the Order, even in <lb/>
the smallest details of life, must have tried her <lb/>
impetuous spirit sadly, but she laboured and <lb/>
obeyed, making beds, sweeping and dusting, <lb/>
her muscles aching with the unaccustomed <lb/>
strain, and finally, for a time, becoming cook in <lb/>
the kitchen et Coatham. Whether under the <lb/>
rigorous discipline of the Good Samaritans her <lb/>
ardent nature found all it craved for, we are <lb/>
not told, but an act of unjustifiable severity <lb/>
caused a breach which finally severed her from <lb/>
them. On being questioned on the matter of <lb/>
her leaving, her sole reply was, "I am a <lb/>
woman and not a piece of furniture." The <lb/>
crisis arose as follows. She had been sent to <lb/>
start a small cottage hospital at Walsall, and <lb/>
so strongly did the rough inhabitants of that <lb/>
bleak mining district become attached to her, <lb/>
that, when she received orders to go to <reg orig="Devon-|shire">Devonshire</reg>, <lb/>
<pb n="25" entity="Somerville_0026.tif"/>
to take charge of a private case, the <lb/>
Hospital Committee remonstrated with the <lb/>
good Sisters at headquarters. Before the <lb/>
matter was settled she received news that her <lb/>
father was dangerously ill and desired to see <lb/>
her at once. She telegraphed to the Home for <lb/>
permission to go, but the incredible answer <lb/>
came back, "No, you must go at once to <lb/>
Devonshire." Her training in obedience at <lb/>
Coatham now bore fruit. She went to <reg orig="Devon-|shire">Devonshire</reg>, <lb/>
though in what agony and bitterness of <lb/>
spirit we may dimly guess, and shortly after <lb/>
her arrival news reached her that her father <lb/>
was dead, his wish to see her ungratified. <lb/>
After this sorrow she threw herself more than <lb/>
ever into her work. Grief, remorse and <reg orig="resent-|ment">resentment</reg> <lb/>
against the Sisters, cast a shadow over <lb/>
her life, and made her reckless of her own <lb/>
health. She had several sharp illnesses from <lb/>
time to time, often brought on by exposure, <lb/>
but she rallied quickly from them and resumed <lb/>
her post at the hospital. Beginning work very <lb/>
quietly at Walsall, only a short time elapsed <lb/>
before "Send for Sister Dora" became the <lb/>
invariable cry in times of sickness or sorrow. <lb/>
Wherever humanity was to be found, there also <lb/>
went Sister Dora, even in the most wretched <lb/>
and degraded seeing not the sin and misery, <lb/>
but only that spark of divinity which is latent <lb/>
<pb n="26" entity="Somerville_0027.tif"/>
in every man. No dark corner of the town <lb/>
was unvisited by her, ever ready to heal <lb/>
both souls and bodies, she would pity, cheer, <lb/>
console, persuade, bringing all under the spell <lb/>
of her influence, and breathing out vigour and <lb/>
health to the stunted life in the dingy slums <lb/>
and alleys.</p>
<p>Her wonderful powers of endurance enabled <lb/>
her to get through an incredible amount of <lb/>
work at the hospital. Except for one or two <lb/>
lady pupils, she had no regular, efficient help, <lb/>
yet after a long night's nursing the morning <lb/>
would find her brimming over with good <lb/>
humour and fresher than many who had been <lb/>
to bed. She always averred she could do very <lb/>
well with seven nights' nursing provided she <lb/>
could go to bed on the eighth! Like many <lb/>
other capable, energetic people she preferred <lb/>
to have her work under own control, and <lb/>
under her supervision the hospital became one <lb/>
of the best and most cheaply managed in the <lb/>
kingdom. Her day began at six. The <lb/>
patients in the ward claimed her till twelve <lb/>
o'clock dinner, then followed some hours with <lb/>
the out-patients, sixty to one hundred being no <lb/>
unusual number to pass through her hands in a <lb/>
single afternoon. The doctors had entire <reg orig="confi-|dence">confidence</reg> <lb/>
in her surgical skill, leaving the sewing-up <lb/>
of wounds, the setting of broken arms, tooth <reg orig="draw-|ing">drawing</reg> <lb/>
<pb n="27" entity="Somerville_0028.tif"/>
and all such minor cases to her, and each <lb/>
new patient was received with the same good <lb/>
humour, sympathy and care. Her biographer, <lb/>
Miss Lonsdale, tells an amusing story of a boy <lb/>
who came rushing up to the hospital, having <lb/>
just chopped off one of his fingers. "Where's <lb/>
the finger?" enquired Sister Dora. "It's at <lb/>
home," replied the boy. "You stupid fellow, <lb/>
go and fetch it at once, and mind you are <lb/>
quick." On his return with the missing article <lb/>
she bandaged it so cleverly that it healed <reg orig="per-|fectly">perfectly</reg> <lb/>
and became a useful member.</p>
<p>After finishing off the last out-patient, her <lb/>
return to the ward would be greeted by a <lb/>
chorus of lamentations and requests, and still <lb/>
the fount of her love and sympathy flowed on <lb/>
unstinted. Soothing and chiding by turns, <lb/>
using every womanly wile she knew to gain her <lb/>
ends with her "children" as she called them, <lb/>
what wonder that the rough miners gradually <lb/>
softened under the influence of this beautiful, <lb/>
vigorous woman, who would pick them up in <lb/>
her arms when they rolled out of bed &lpar;as they <lb/>
not unfrequently did&rpar; and yet who would dress <lb/>
their wounds with a touch as light and firm as <lb/>
that of a surgeon? The Hospital Committee <lb/>
she managed with equal diplomacy, using <lb/>
whatever form of persuasion seemed best <lb/>
suited to the occasion, even threatening to <lb/>
<pb n="28" entity="Somerville_0029.tif"/>
leave, when all other means failed to bring <lb/>
them to submission. On one occasion when <lb/>
she sent in her resignation the docter vowed, <lb/>
most unprofessionally, he would lay his head <lb/>
under a railway train if she did not relent!</p>
<p>She was an excellent surgeon, making the <lb/>
anatomy of the eye a special study, and this <lb/>
knowledge proved of great service in the <reg orig="fre-|quent">frequent</reg> <lb/>
cases of blindness caused by flying <lb/>
bits of metal or burning cinders from the <lb/>
furnaces at the iron works. In conservative <lb/>
surgery she was particularly successful. <lb/>
Accidents occurred constantly, colliers were <lb/>
brought in burnt or mangled almost beyond <lb/>
recognition, and on hearing the doctor's verdict <lb/>
"Amputation," all the tenderness in her nature <lb/>
would be kindled by the distress of these rough <lb/>
bread-winners. "You may as well kill me at once, <lb/>
as take off my leg, for what will become of my wife <lb/>
and children if I cannot work?" One young man, <lb/>
brought into the hospital with his arm literally <lb/>
torn in pieces, cried, "Oh, Sister, save my arm, <lb/>
it is my <hi rend="italic">right</hi> arm!" and, in spite of the doctor's <lb/>
opposition, who, prophesying that death would <lb/>
ensue, angrily washed his hands of the whole <lb/>
affair, she undertook the case. Night and day <lb/>
she watched during the anxious weeks that <lb/>
followed, for a human life lay in her hands, but <lb/>
in the end she triumphed and the cure was <reg orig="com-|plete">complete</reg>. <lb/>
<pb n="29" entity="Somerville_0030.tif"/>
Referring to it afterwards, she said, <lb/>
"How I prayed over that arm!" The doctor <lb/>
was generous in acknowledging her success and <lb/>
insisted on exhibiting the "arm" to the entire <lb/>
hospital staff as an illustration of efficient nursing. <lb/>
Later, when Sister Dora herself lay dangerously <lb/>
ill, its grateful owner would walk eleven miles on <lb/>
Sunday, his only holiday, to enquire for her. <lb/>
"Tell Sister it was her 'arm' that rang the <lb/>
bell" he would say as he turned away and <lb/>
walked back again.</p>
<p>One of her most remarkable feats in nursing <lb/>
was in connection with small-pox. After the <lb/>
first outbreak, a special hospital had been built <lb/>
outside Walsall, but when the epidemic again <lb/>
visited the town the poor people could not be <lb/>
induced to send their sick thither, and the Town <lb/>
Council was in despair until Sister Dora <reg orig="volun-|teered">volunteered</reg> <lb/>
to lead the way. Then quickly the <lb/>
news was passed round that Sister had gone to <lb/>
the hospital, and a few hours later the <reg orig="twenty-|eight">twenty-eight</reg> <lb/>
beds were full. No helpers could be <lb/>
induced to go near the place, but devoted <lb/>
friends brought her books and flowers and <lb/>
rendered what service they could. Two decrepid <lb/>
old women from the workhouse assisted in the <lb/>
loathsome washing of linen, and the porter <lb/>
proved useful&mdash;he, however, occasionally <lb/>
absented himself for a whole night when a <lb/>
<pb n="30" entity="Somerville_0031.tif"/>
drinking fit seized him, leaving her entirely <lb/>
alone with the patients, many of whom were <lb/>
delirious. In one of her letters she says, "I <lb/>
have not had a creature to do a hand's turn <lb/>
since last Thursday." And again, "My Irish <lb/>
woman, &lpar;the servant&rpar; walked off this afternoon <lb/>
and went drinking, even in the middle of <lb/>
washing&hellip; it is now past seven, and she <lb/>
left me at two, and there is a boy raving, I am <lb/>
sure he will die, poor fellow." For six months <lb/>
she lived here in isolation, going out but seldom, <lb/>
but her spirit was equal to every emergency&mdash; <lb/>
nursing infected babies, grappling with strong <lb/>
men in their delirium and sitting up at night <lb/>
with a sensational "yellow-back" to keep her <lb/>
awake! And yet we find her afterwards <lb/>
referring to this period of her life as the time <lb/>
"when I was at the <hi rend="italic">dear</hi> Epidemic Hospital!"</p>
<p>On another occasion an explosion occurred <lb/>
at some iron works near, eleven men being <lb/>
frightfully injured with the burning metal. <lb/>
Their charred bodies were brought into the <lb/>
hospital, making the air f&oelig;tid with the smell <lb/>
of burnt flesh. For ten days she hardly left <lb/>
them, even to eat. The whole town was <lb/>
stirred, and many came to volunteer assistance, <lb/>
but the foul atmosphere of the wards soon sent <lb/>
them fainting on to the stairs, where Sister <lb/>
Dora would find them and kindly bid them go <lb/>
<pb n="31" entity="Somerville_0032.tif"/>
home at once. Even under this great strain <lb/>
her cheerfulness did not desert her, and she <lb/>
went from one bed to another, using every <lb/>
resource to divert the men's minds from their <lb/>
sufferings; eventually all died but two.</p>
<p>Her activity also embraced Mission work&mdash; <lb/>
indeed every scheme for helping and serving <lb/>
others called forth her ready sympathy, and <lb/>
into each new work she would throw herself <lb/>
with as much vigour as if it alone had the <lb/>
only claim upon her.</p>
<p>The first warning of the disease from which <lb/>
she died came in the flagging of physical <lb/>
strength, and a few months later she realised <lb/>
that her complaint was incurable. But not till <lb/>
the very end did she give way. She, who had <lb/>
helped so many in her strength desired no pity <lb/>
in her weakness. For many months she hid <lb/>
all traces of illness, eagerly striving to make <lb/>
the most of the time that remained. When <lb/>
the truth could be no longer hidden, Walsall <lb/>
was incredulous. She who had fought death <lb/>
so often for others, would not herself be <lb/>
vanquished! "Her'll get well, her <hi rend="italic">never</hi> can be <lb/>
going to die," they said. Life without Sister <lb/>
Dora seemed impossible, and many believed she <lb/>
would recover. This hope was fostered by her <lb/>
unfailing cheerfulness, even when suffering <lb/>
great agony, but after lingering through many <lb/>
<pb n="32" entity="Somerville_0033.tif"/>
painful months she died on December 24th, <lb/>
1878. A great throng of mourners attended <lb/>
her funeral, no class or society in the district <lb/>
was unrepresented, for she had been a "Sister"<lb/>
to all. A statue in her honour has been erected <lb/>
at Walsall that her memory may live before <lb/>
the eyes of future generations, but those she <lb/>
served need only the shrine that gratitude and <lb/>
love have raised in their hearts where her name <lb/>
is held in perpetual remembrance.</p>
<ornament type="line"/>
<p>Women's Printing Society, Limited, 66, Whitcomb Street, W.C.</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
