<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000002755_0019 SYSTEM "000002755_0019" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002755_0020 SYSTEM "000002755_0021" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002755_0021 SYSTEM "000002755_0022" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002755_0022 SYSTEM "000002755_0022" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>

<TEI.2 id="watts18620101">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Watts  to Children  <date value="1862-01-01">Jany 1st, 1862</date>
                </title>
                <author>Watts, Robert William, Rev., 1825-1910</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">16</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">watts18620101</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Watts-letters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letters from Robert William Watts to members of his family in Albemarle County, Va</title>
                        <author>Watts, Robert William, Rev., 1825-1910</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>4 page</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 809</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">3928516-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a3928516 </idno>
                      
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">
            <div1 type="letter" id="d3">
                <head>Watts  to Children  <date value="1862-01-01">Jany 1<hi rend="super">st</hi>, 1862</date></head>
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0019"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline><name type="place">Warrenton</name>
                        <date value="1862-01-01">Jany 1<hi rend="super">st</hi> 1862.</date></dateline>
                    <salute>My dear Children,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p rend="indent5">
                        What can be<lb/>
                    The matter that you have not written <unclear>[-]</unclear> <reg orig="re-|ply">reply</reg><lb/>
                    to my letter sent immediately upon<lb/>
                    my arrival here more than ten days ago?<lb/>
                    I take it for granted that you are both<lb/>
                    well or there would have been some <reg orig="commun-|ication">communication</reg><lb/>
                    from some one, and I presume<lb/>
                    that you all are or have been so taken up<lb/>
                    with Xms that you haven't found time <lb/>
                    to think of me much.  Remember I am<lb/>
                    disposed to be a little jealous of y'r <reg orig="affect-|tion">affecttion</reg><lb/>
                    and can't afford to give it up on<lb/>
                    any terms.  It may be that my letter<lb/>
                    has not reached you.  I wrote it in <reg orig="Lou-|doun">Loudoun</reg><lb/>
                    and would have sent it next day<lb/>
                    but it escaped my memory while in<lb/>
                    Lees burg, and on reaching this place<lb/>
                    handed it to a man to put in the<lb/>
                        
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0020"/>
                        office and he may have neglected it<lb/>
                    But you ought to have written any how<lb/>
                    I have been anxious to hear whether Mr<lb/>
                    Brown has written to cous: John about<lb/>
                    the school or not.  I gave a description<lb/>
                    to this friend of the neighborhood and<lb/>
                    requested them to write at once, stating<lb/>
                    qualifications &amp;C.  I have seen no notice<lb/>
                    of any one else, and presume if he is <lb/>
                    willing to teach under the circumstances,<lb/>
                    it will be the best that Cousins J. &amp; L.<lb/>
                    can do.  So far as I am concerned I<lb/>
                    am well satisfied with Cousins Lizie &amp;<lb/>
                    Mollie's teaching from the evidence I<lb/>
                    see in the improvement of you both<lb/>
                    If they can stand the confinement I think<lb/>
                    all of you are doing finely  I am truly<lb/>
                    glad that you have such a friend &amp; <lb/>
                    manager in Cousins John &amp; Lizie, and <lb/>
                    hope they will not become tired of you<lb/>
                    this year.  And I trust that both of you<lb/>
                    will try to render y'rselves agreeable<lb/>
                    
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0021"/>
                    &amp; obedient ot every command, as you<lb/>
                    know nothing will be required but for<lb/>
                    y'r good.  This is decidedly the most<lb/>
                    crowded place of which I've ever lived<lb/>
                    and there is no school here of any <lb/>
                    note except a Baptist seminary, which<lb/>
                    is not suitable for you two.  Another <lb/>
                    year perhaps you &amp; Cissa &amp; Sallie &amp; <add place="top" hand="author">&amp; Mollie</add> may<lb/>
                    be able to go to school together, all<lb/>
                    boarding with me.  I shall not <reg orig="occu-|py">occupy</reg><lb/>
                    the parsonage here as it is right<lb/>
                    much out of repair and surrounded<lb/>
                    by hospitals of sick soldiers with all<lb/>
                    sorts of diseases, and consequently am<lb/>
                    boarding at a very nice place, having<lb/>
                    a good room, &amp; the stable of the <reg orig="par-|sonage">parsonage</reg><lb/>
                    sonage for Billie.  Miss M. seems to <lb/>
                    be desirous that we should keep house <lb/>
                    so that you both might be with us but<lb/>
                    this I find to be altogether impractical.<lb/>
                    She expects to take <unclear>leave</unclear> here in<lb/>
                        April and if there be no difficulty<lb/>
                        
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0022"/>
                    it is possible we may <hi rend="underline">room together</hi><lb/>
                    If my business will allow it, I want to <lb/>
                    Slip over &amp; see you before that time, but<lb/>
                    Cannot now tell.  I have more preaching<lb/>
                    &amp; more pastoral visiting to do than ever<lb/>
                    before.  This place has nearly the work<lb/>
                    of a full station, and if it could, ought<lb/>
                    to have a stationed preacher.  Have you<lb/>
                    both commenced the Latin, and did you<lb/>
                    receive the music I sent you?  Try<lb/>
                    to apply y'rselves &amp; thus make the<lb/>
                    most of y'r times, and don't neglect the<lb/>
                    fundamental studies such as Arithmetic.<lb/>
                    Would like for you to commence <reg orig="Alge-|bra">Algebra,</reg><lb/>
                    and if no teacher is obtained, why<lb/>
                    Ciss can teach you.  I reckon she can<lb/>
                    find the time.  Tho' this I leave to Cous:<lb/>
                    Lizie.  I have never seen as much of<lb/>
                    death before, except on the battle field,<lb/>
                    since I've been here, some times as many<lb/>
                    as seven or eight a day among the <reg orig="sol-|diers">soldiers,</reg><lb/>
                    besides the citizens.  The scarlet<lb/>
                    
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0019"/>   
                    <note id="n1" n="1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol">{1}</seg>
                        <p>[This section is written perpendicularly over the beginning of the letter on page one.]</p>
                    </note>
                        fever<ref target="n1" n="1">{1}</ref> is here among <lb/>
                    the grown people.  I<lb/>
                    buried a lady who died<lb/>
                    with <!--[it]--> soon after getting<lb/>
                    here, and now the<lb/>
                    under taker is down<lb/>
                    with it.  His sister is<lb/>
                    very low also, and I had<lb/>
                    to visit her the other<lb/>
                    day as she sent for<lb/>
                    me.  I have had it, but<lb/>
                    they say here, one can<lb/>
                    have it twice.  I am<lb/>
                    sorry that Mollie Watts<lb/>
                    took the fever and was<lb/>
                    disappointed about her<lb/>
                    visit to you all.  I told<lb/>
                    y'r G. Pa he better not send for you, as there<lb/>
                    were new cases every wk<lb/>
                    I hope the fever will all<lb/>
                    be gone before I come out <lb/>
                    and then you can go there<lb/>
                        Tell Cousin L that all of<lb/>
                    you must go up to pa's<lb/>
                    in the Spring &mdash;<lb/>
                        <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0020"/>
                    <note id="n2" n="2" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol">{2}</seg>
                        <p>[The next two sections is transcription for letter written perpendicularly over pages two &amp; three.]</p>
                    </note>
                        There<ref target="n2" n="2">{2}</ref> are three very pretty, well behaved girls boarding or rather<lb/>
                    belonging to the family here, and they make me think of you<lb/>
                    all any time I look at them.  The other day little Jose came <reg orig="trip-|ping">tripping</reg><lb/>
                    up the steps and rapping at the door said very sweetly, Here's<lb/>
                    a letter for you Mr. Watts," and then modestly retired.  I love her<lb/>
                    very much &mdash; Well this is New Year's day, my children, the first<lb/>
                    day in the year and we ought to resolve to consecrate the year<lb/>
                    to God &mdash; Begin it rightly and see if you can't improve it more<lb/>
                    than the year now gone forever &mdash; Think of all the misdeeds you<lb/>
                    have done in the past years and then think of the Goodness<lb/>
                    of God in sparing y'r lives, and giving you such kind friends<lb/>
                    to care for you and see y'r best interests.  Think of the many<lb/>
                    who commenced last year with hopes as high as y'rs are now,<lb/>
                    who long since were laid in the cold &amp; select grave. My dear <lb/>
                        children; may God impress these things on y'r minds, and make<lb/>
                    you just such Christians as may be acceptable in his sight.<lb/>
                    I hope you &amp; Lizie &amp; Jimmie &amp; Mollie &amp; Sallie &amp; all the<lb/>
                    
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0021"/>
                    cousins may dedicate y'r hearts to God, and all be made<lb/>
                    happy trying to do y'r duties faithfully &mdash; Then you may <reg orig="be-|come">become</reg><lb/>
                    useful &amp; live to purpose.  Thus alone can you fulfill<lb/>
                    the destiny for which God has created you.  "Remember now thy<lb/>
                    creator in the days of thy youth, before the end days come'<lb/>
                    and then none of the days will be evil, there will be good<lb/>
                    in every one of them.  Bettie my child wrestle with y'r temper<lb/>
                    and seek for grace to bring it under command, and it will be<lb/>
                    a great benefit to you.  Pray often my child, and be regular in<lb/>
                    reading y'r bible.  Winkie, dearest do the same, and try to be<lb/>
                    employed in something useful every day.  God grant that my<lb/>
                    two little girls may grow up to be useful, pious women, living<lb/>
                    to exert a good influence upon every one around.  Give<lb/>
                    my love and a Happy New Year to Cousins J. &amp; L. T. &amp; M.<lb/> Uncle
                    Wm &amp; Aunt Sallie &amp; to all the children of both families.<lb/>
                        
                </p>
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0022"/>
                <closer>
                    <note id="n3" n="3" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol">{3}</seg>
                        <p>[The following is written upside down at the bottom of page four.]</p>
                    </note>
                        <salute>Yr<ref target="n3" n="3">{3}</ref> affectionate father &mdash;</salute>
                    <signed><name>R. W. Watts</name>
                    </signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
          </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>

