<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % POSTKB "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % MANUSCRIPT "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/uva-dl-tei/uva-dl-tei.dtd">
<!ENTITY % dlps-teiHeader SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/ent/dlps-teiHeader.ent"> %dlps-teiHeader;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat1 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat1.ent"> %ISOlat1;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOlat2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-lat2.ent"> %ISOlat2;

<!ENTITY DSSR_000002755_0023 SYSTEM "000002755_0023" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002755_0024 SYSTEM "000002755_0024" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002755_0025 SYSTEM "000002755_0025" NDATA uvaHighRes>
<!ENTITY DSSR_000002755_0026 SYSTEM "000002755_0026" NDATA uvaHighRes>
]>

<TEI.2 id="watts18620211">
    <teiHeader type="AACR2">
        
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                
                <title>Watts  to Bettie <date value="1862-02-11">Feb 11th, 1862</date>
                </title>
                <author>Watts, Robert William, Rev., 1825-1910</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of machine-readable version: </resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services , University of Virginia Library</name>
                    <resp>Conversion to TEI.2-conformant markup:</resp>
                    <name>Digital Curation Services</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Creation of digital images:</resp>
                    <name>Digitization Services, University of Virginia Library</name>
                </respStmt>
                
            </titleStmt>
            
            <extent>ca. <num type="kilobytes">13</num> kilobytes</extent>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>University of Virginia Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, Virginia </pubPlace>
                <idno type="DCS">watts18620211</idno>
                <date value="2010">2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>University of Virginia Library, Text collection</title>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Text</idno>
                <idno type="uva-set">UVA-LIB-Watts-letters</idno>
            </seriesStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                
                <biblFull>
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title>Letters from Robert William Watts to members of his family in Albemarle County, Va</title>
                        <author>Watts, Robert William, Rev., 1825-1910</author>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <extent>4 page</extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        
                        <idno type="Accession No.">MSS 809</idno>
                        <idno type="Virgo ID">3928516-1001</idno>
                        <idno type="title control number">a3928516 </idno>
                     
                        <availability>
                            <p> Albert &amp; Shirley Small Special Collections, University of
                                Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia, USA</p>
                        </availability>
                    </publicationStmt>
                </biblFull>
                
            </sourceDesc>
            
            
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <!-- Per Matt we need to work on this statement-->
                <p> Prepared for the University of Virginia Library by Digital Curation Services staff
                    and volunteer Mary Roy Dawson Edwards, Transcriber. 2005.</p>
            </projectDesc>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <handList>
                <hand id="author"/>
                <hand id="unknown"/>
                <hand id="cataloger"/>
            </handList>
        </profileDesc>
        
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text id="d1">
        <body id="d2">
            <div1 type="letter" id="d3">
                <head>Watts  to Bettie <date value="1862-02-11">Feb 11<hi rend="super">th</hi>, 1862</date></head>
                <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0023"/>
                <opener>
                    <dateline><name type="place">Warrenton</name>
                        <date value="1862-02-11">Feb 11<hi rend="super">th</hi> 1862.</date></dateline>
                    <salute>My dear Bettie,</salute>
                </opener>
                <p rend="indent5">
                    I have just arrived<lb/>
                    From my fatiguing trip to see an old<lb/>
                    minister expected to die, and found y'r<lb/>
                    letter of the 7<hi rend="super">th</hi> awaiting me.  I am very<lb/>
                    glad of its reception, as it reassures me <lb/>
                    of y'r continued affection &amp; welfare.  But<lb/>
                    my spirits are so affected upon the <reg orig="re-|ceipt">receipt</reg><lb/>
                    of so much unfavorable news that<lb/>
                    I hardly feel like doing any thing.  <reg orig="Be-|sides">Besides</reg><lb/>
                    I am a little complaining again<lb/>
                    from disease with which I was <reg orig="afflict-|ed">afflicted</reg><lb/>
                    seven or eight days after writing to<lb/>
                    you.  It seems that exposure to cold brings<lb/>
                    it on me and Laudanum does me no<lb/>
                    good, have to resort to Blue Mass.  Just<lb/>
                    as I was about rid of it last week, I<lb/>
                    went to the Stable to see Bill, and<lb/>
                    
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0024" n="[page 2]"/>
                    concluded to lead him to water with<lb/>
                    only the halter on him.  He commenced<lb/>
                    rearing and then turned his heels to me<lb/>
                    and kicked me twice before I could<lb/>
                    get out of the way: just above my right <lb/>
                    knee.  Strange to say, my leg was not <reg orig="bro-|ken">broken,</reg><lb/>
                    nor did I let him loose.  He had<lb/><lb/>
                    been standing up for some time, and <reg orig="want-|ed">wanted</reg><lb/>
                    to play, and I think he thought by<lb/>
                    kicking at me, it would frighten me and<lb/>
                    make me let him go.  By the application<lb/>
                    of Volatile Linament, my leg has not<lb/>
                    been greatly lamed, and I feel very <reg orig="thank-|ful">thankful</reg><lb/>
                    to Providence that it is no worse.<lb/>
                    Well you have no doubt seen the news<lb/>
                    from Roanoke island; I suppose <reg orig="Wes-|ley">Wesley</reg><lb/>
                    is among the prisoners, as I see<lb/>
                    all were taken except twenty five.  I <lb/>
                    feel very anxious to hear further news <lb/>
                    to night.  Our people were becoming<lb/>
                    too confident, and too prayerless, and<lb/>
                    the Good Lord seems to be against us<lb/>
                    
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0025" n="[page 3]"/>
                    <!--[Written in red at the top of this page: "=War"]-->
                    Our troops about Centerville seem to<lb/>
                    be desponding and the other day thirty<lb/>
                    of the Amelia cavalry ran from twenty<lb/>
                    Yankees; but they say they thought<lb/>
                    there was a large force trying to cut<lb/>
                    them off.  Nearly half of our horses<lb/>
                    there are dead and the other half are<lb/>
                    so poor that they are fit for nothing<lb/>
                    scarcely.  I never saw such negligence<lb/>
                    in all my life.  Some times teams <unclear>stop</unclear><lb/>
                    here and the drivers get drunk and<lb/>
                    keep their horses standing all night<lb/>
                    without any thing to eat.  But our<lb/>
                    cause we much try and trust in the<lb/>
                    hands of the Lord, hoping that a change<lb/>
                    for the better may take place.  Try my<lb/>
                    dear child to give y'r heart fully and<lb/>
                    unreservedly to y'r blessed Savior.  You can<lb/>
                    only do this by seeking for grace in <reg orig="ear-|nest">earnest</reg><lb/>
                    prayer, to enable you to give up every<lb/>
                    thing else that binds it to earthly things<lb/>
                    I do so much desire that you and Winkie<lb/>
                    
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0026" n="[page 4]"/>
                    both may be Christians!  Oh! If either<lb/>
                    one of you should be taken sick and<lb/>
                    die, without a hope of being saved, it<lb/>
                    would distress me very much, and then<lb/>
                    the irreparable loss to you; who can <reg orig="es-|timate">estimate</reg><lb/>
                    it!  Well you may die any time<lb/>
                    "In such a moment as ye think not the<lb/>
                    son of man cometh" &mdash; Be regular my<lb/>
                    child in praying, don't forget it, I entreat<lb/>
                    you, and don't let Satan tempt you to give<lb/>
                    up y'r hope in Christ, for that will be<lb/>
                    worth any thing else besides.  Don't let the<lb/>
                    company of boys; not even cousins, draw <lb/>
                    y'r mind from y'r regular duties.  Be polite<lb/>
                    &amp; kind, <hi rend="underline">my darling</hi> child, but don't <reg orig="encour-|age">encourage</reg><lb/>
                    undue familiarity.  My heart yearns over<lb/>
                    you and if you love me, keep my wishes.<lb/>
                    Y'r letter of 25<hi rend="super">th</hi> Jany was not a day after<lb/>
                    my last to you &mdash; <hi rend="underline">My darling</hi> Winkie,<lb/>
                    let me know in the next, how your are <reg orig="com-|ing">coming</reg><lb/>
                    on in y'r duties.  I have written most<lb/>
                    all of this to Bettie, because she may need<lb/>
                    it, and this letter to you must answer now<lb/>
                    while the same advise given to y'r sister is<lb/>
                    also urged on you.  I want you to think of<lb/>
                    y'r soul, and try to become good; for you are<lb/>
                    not too young to die.  If I could well leave<lb/>
                    my work I would go over and see you all<lb/>
                    but, having to go in April, I don't see how<lb/>
                    I can spare the time now &amp; then too<lb/>
                    
                    <pb entity="DSSR_000002755_0023"/>
                    <note id="n1" n="1" place="end"><seg type="note-symbol">{1}</seg>
                        <p>[The last part of this letter is written perpendicularly over page one.]</p>
                    </note>
                   I <ref target="n1" n="1">{1}</ref> want you and all the little cousins to think about religion, for<lb/>
                    if they put it off until they are older, they &amp; you will think<lb/>
                    less about it then, than you do now.  The heart gets harder and<lb/>
                    harden every day and the more you resist - the Spirit the less<lb/>
                    will you feel his stirrings.  I was very glad to find that<lb/>
                    y'r disposition has softened so much since you have been<lb/>
                    with Cousin Lizzie, and that you &amp; y'r sister had learned to<lb/>
                    be more patient with each other.  I never doubted y'r love for each<lb/>
                    other, but there was often a spirit of temper and impatience<lb/>
                    manifested when every thing didn't go exactly as you both wished<lb/>
                    God loves little children that love each other.  I am trying to<lb/>
                    notice children more than ever before, and hope to be able to<lb/>
                    make then love me all round the circuit.  Give my best love<lb/>
                    to Cousins John &amp; Lizzie, Sissie &amp; Mamie &amp; all the children, and<lb/>
                    also to the family at Edgewood.  You must write to me the<lb/>
                    next time y'r sister writes, and tell me all about yrself.</p>
                <closer>
                    <salute>Y'r affectionate father.</salute>
                    <signed><name>R. W. Watts</name></signed>
                </closer>
            </div1>
          </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>

