<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- NOTE: Update last modified date manually when editing this file -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->

<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/dtd/tei/tei-p4/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM "http://pogo.lib.virginia.edu/dlps/dtd/tei/teitech/teitech.ent">
<!ENTITY % TEI.extensions.dtd SYSTEM "http://pogo.lib.virginia.edu/dlps/dtd/tei/teitech/teitech.dtd">
<!ENTITY % ISOnum SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-num.ent"> %ISOnum;
<!ENTITY % ISOpub SYSTEM "http://text.lib.virginia.edu/charent/iso-pub.ent"> %ISOpub;

<!ENTITY rarr "&#x2192;"><!-- rightward arrow -->
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Rimage Workflow for Batch-Reading Archival Discs</title>
<author>Greg Murray (gpm2a@virginia.edu), Digital Library Production Services</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Digital Library Production Services, University of Virginia Library</publisher>
</publicationStmt>
</fileDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text id="d1">
<body id="d2">
<argument>

<p>This document describes the workflow for reading a batch of
archival discs using the Rimage system at Digital Library Production
Services (DLPS), University of Virginia Library. It is intended for
use by internal DLPS staff.</p>

<p>This workflow makes it possible to transfer large sets of data from
CDs or DVDs to a hard disk (or any disk or server accessible to the
Rimage PC) with minimal effort.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Note:</hi> This documentation pertains to version
7.0 of the Rimage OfficeNet software.</p>

<!-- =============================================================== -->
<!-- NOTE: Update last modified date manually when editing this file -->
<!-- =============================================================== -->

<p><hi rend="bold">Last modified:</hi> <date type="last-modified" value="2006-11-16">11/16/2006</date></p>
</argument>

<div1 id="d3">
<head>Set Up</head>
<list>

<item>Open the Rimage System Manager (Start &rarr; All Programs &rarr;
Rimage &rarr; Rimage System Manager).</item>

<item>Open the main settings window:

  <list>

  <item>In the main toolbar, make sure <gizmo>Control Centers</gizmo>
  is selected.</item>

  <item>In the left-hand navigation pane, select the <gizmo>Control
  Center</gizmo>.</item>

  <item>Click the <gizmo>Desktop 1500 Settings...</gizmo> button (or
  <gizmo>Rimage 2000i Settings...</gizmo> button).</item>

  </list>
</item>

<item>In the <gizmo>Bins/Media</gizmo> tab, under the
<gizmo>Media:</gizmo> section, check the <gizmo>Media type</gizmo>
setting. It will be set to either DVDR or CDR.</item>

<item>If the setting already corresponds to the type of discs you will
be reading, then just click <gizmo>OK</gizmo>. If it doesn't, you
<emph>must</emph> set it to the type of media you will be using:

  <list>

  <item>Click the "pause" button (looks like a VCR pause button with
  the || symbol) near the top of the window.</item>

  <item>Change the <gizmo>Media type</gizmo> setting to DVDR or CDR as
  appropriate.</item>

  <item>Click <gizmo>OK</gizmo> to save the settings and close the
  settings window.</item>

  </list>
</item>

<item>In the left-hand navigation pane, select <gizmo>Production
Server</gizmo>.</item>

<item>Pause the production server (if you haven't done so already in a
previous step) by clicking the "pause" button (looks like a VCR pause
button with the || symbol).</item>

<item>Click the <gizmo>Server Settings...</gizmo> button.</item>

<item>Set the following options:<lb/><lb/>

<table>
<row>
<cell role="label">Tab</cell>
<cell role="label">Option</cell>
<cell role="label">Setting to use</cell>
<cell role="label">Description</cell>
</row>

<row>
<cell><gizmo>Server</gizmo></cell>
<cell><gizmo>Operating Mode</gizmo></cell>

<cell><gizmo>Automatic Bulk Read</gizmo></cell>

<cell>This puts the Production Server in automated batch-reading
mode.</cell>
</row>

<row>
<cell><gizmo>Server</gizmo></cell>
<cell><gizmo>Use FIFO mode</gizmo></cell>
<cell>Checked, if disc order is relevant</cell>

<cell>If maintaining the original sequence of the discs is important,
check this checkbox to enable first-in-first-out (FIFO) mode, so that
the discs are output in the same order by which they were input. If
the original disc sequence is irrelevant, you can leave this checkbox
cleared to increase the overall speed of the process.</cell>
</row>

<row>
<cell><gizmo>Reading</gizmo></cell>
<cell><gizmo>Base Folder for Images</gizmo></cell>

<cell>Any valid path, such as <path>C:\temp</path> &mdash; though
normally you will want to use an external drive with plenty of free
disk space, typically <path>E:\</path></cell>

<cell>This is the location to which folders and files from the disc
will be copied.</cell>
</row>

<row>
<cell><gizmo>Reading</gizmo></cell>
<cell><gizmo>Use Volume ID ... as Image Folder Name</gizmo></cell>

<cell>Checked</cell>

<cell>For each disc, a new folder with the same name as the disc name
will be created to contain the folders/files from that disc.</cell>
</row>

<row>
<cell><gizmo>Reading</gizmo></cell>
<cell><gizmo>Extract ISO9660 Images to Folders and Files</gizmo></cell>

<cell>Checked</cell>

<cell>As each disc is read, the data from that disc will be copied as
actual folders and files, rather than as a single large disc image
(.img) file containing the entire contents of the disc.</cell>
</row>

</table>
</item>

<item>Click <gizmo>OK</gizmo> to save the settings and close the
settings window.</item>

</list>
</div1>

<div1 id="d4">
<head>Read Discs</head>

<list>

<item>Load the input bin with the DVDs or CDs to be read. (On the
Desktop 1500, the input bin is the one with the three prongs to hold
the discs. On the 2000i, the input bin is the left bin.)

<admon type="tip"><p>If you have enabled FIFO (first-in-first-out)
mode (see above for details), you can place the discs in the input bin
in reverse order, and when reading is complete they will be in the
desired order. For example, if you have three discs to read, put disc
1 on the bottom of the stack, disc 2 in the middle, and disc 3 on
top. Disc 3 will be picked up and read first, and placed on the ouput
spindle first. Disc2 will be output second, and disc 1 will be output
last, so that it is on top of the output stack. That way, the discs
are in the correct order at the end of the process.</p></admon>

</item>

<item>To begin reading discs, click the "resume server" button (looks
like a VCR play button with a green triangle). The arm of the Rimage
will place a disc in each of the two CD/DVD drives and begin reading
the discs.</item>

<item>While the discs are being read, you can click the
<gizmo>Server Orders</gizmo> tab to view the status of the current
discs, and for any error messages.</item>

<item>When all discs in the input bin have been retrieved, the Rimage
System Manager will display an error dialog saying that there are no
more discs in the input bin. If there are more discs to be read, put
them in the input bin and click <gizmo>Retry</gizmo>. If you're
finished, click <gizmo>Stop Line</gizmo>.</item>

<item>When you're finished reading all discs, return the Production
Server to its normal state:

  <list>

  <item>Click the "pause" button (looks like a VCR pause button with
  the || symbol) for the Production Server.</item>

  <item>Click the <gizmo>Server Settings...</gizmo> button.</item>

  <item>On the <gizmo>Server</gizmo> tab, set the <gizmo>Operating
  Mode</gizmo> to <gizmo>Normal</gizmo>. Click
  <gizmo>OK</gizmo>.</item>

  <item>Click the "resume server" button (looks like a VCR play button
  with a green triangle).</item>

  </list>

</item>
</list>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
